<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The judgment of the fathers concerning the doctrine of the Trinity opposed to Dr. G. Bull's Defence of the Nicene faith : Part I. The doctrine of the Catholick Church, during the first 150 years of Christianity, and the explication of the unity of God (in a Trinity of Divine Persons) by some of the following fathers, considered.</title>
            <author>Smalbroke, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21143</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12054557</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12054557</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60380)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 580:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The judgment of the fathers concerning the doctrine of the Trinity opposed to Dr. G. Bull's Defence of the Nicene faith : Part I. The doctrine of the Catholick Church, during the first 150 years of Christianity, and the explication of the unity of God (in a Trinity of Divine Persons) by some of the following fathers, considered.</title>
                  <author>Smalbroke, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Smalbroke by Halkett &amp; Laing and NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Also attributed to Stephen Nye. Nye repudiated this in a reply to Peter Allix, D.D. written in 1701. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>No more published.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bull, George, 1634-1710. --  Defensio fidei Nicaenae.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Trinity.</term>
               <term>Socinianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53124:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JUDGMENT OF THE FATHERS Concerning the Doctrine of the TRINITY; Oppoſed to Dr. <hi>G. Bull</hi>'s DEFENCE of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith. PART I. The Doctrine of the Catholick Church, during the firſt 150 Years of Chriſtianity; and the Explication of the Unity of God (in a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Divine Perſons) by ſome of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Fathers, conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53124:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53124:2"/>
            <head>The J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGMENT of the <hi>Fathers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Doctrine of the Trinity.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>I. The Deſign of Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Book.</head>
               <p>I Intend, in theſe Sheets, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s
<hi>Defence of the Nicene Faith:</hi> I ſhall preſcribe to my ſelf, to be as brief as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I can, and to deal fairly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly.</p>
               <p>What is the Pretence of his Book, he tells us at <hi>pag.</hi>
5<hi>th</hi> and 6<hi>th</hi> of his Preface to it, in theſe Words;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"To evince, that all the <hi>approved Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> and Fathers of the Church, from the very Age of the Apoſtles to the firſt Nicene Council, agreed, in one common and ſelf-ſame Faith, concerning the Divinity of our Saviour, with the ſaid Nicene Council.</q>
                  <hi>A ridiculous Offer;</hi> for taking care, as he does, to limit himſelf to the <hi>approved Doctors</hi> and Fathers; who is ſo dull (does Mr.
<hi>Bull</hi> think?) as not to underſtand, that no Father or Doctor ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this (new and rare) Title of <hi>Doctor probatus, approved Doctor,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> and he cannot accord about the Nicene Faith? What if an Arian or Socinian ſhould make the like (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent) Propoſal, even to ſhow that all <hi>the approved</hi> Doctors and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before the Nicene Council, did agree with <hi>Arius</hi> or <hi>Socinus;</hi> would it not be laugh'd at? For would not the Reader reply immediatly, that this (inſidious) word <hi>approved</hi> makes his Attempt to be of no uſe at all: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will be ſure <hi>not to approve</hi> any Doctor or Father, who is not of the Party of <hi>Socinus</hi> or <hi>Arius.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> would have ſpoke to the purpoſe, he ſhould have ſaid ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; that <hi>all</hi> the Ante-nicene Fathers or Doctors were of the ſame Mind with the Doctors and Fathers in the Nicene Council, in the Queſtion of our Saviour's Divinity: this had come up to the famous
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Rule of Orthodoxy and Truth, ſuggeſted firſt by <hi>Vincentius,</hi> and approved by all Parties;
<hi>quod ab omnibus, quod ubique, id demum Catholicum eſt; i. e.</hi> that which <hi>all</hi> the Antient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors have taught, and in <hi>all</hi> Places, is Catholick and Fundamental. But Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> durſt not pretend to <hi>all</hi> the<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53124:3"/>Doctors and Fathers before the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Council; but only to certain <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</hi> Fathers and Writers among them, about 20 among upwards of 200. The Reaſon is evident; he foreſaw, that we ſhould preſently mind him of <hi>Theodotion, Symmachus, Paulus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> of <hi>Byzantium, Apollonides, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mophilus, Lucianus;</hi> the Authors of the Apoſtolical Conſtitutions and of the Recognitions; of <hi>Melito</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sardis,</hi> who publiſhed a Book with this Title,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of the Creation and Birth of Chriſt:</hi> not to mention here the Nazarens or Ebionites, who inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
<hi>Judea, Galilee, Moab,</hi> the moſt part of <hi>Syria,</hi> and a great part of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia;</hi> or the <hi>Mineans,</hi> who had their Synagogues or Churches (ſays St. <hi>Jerom, Epiſt. ad Auguſt.</hi>) over all
<hi>Aſia;</hi> or the 15 firſt Biſhops of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As theſe were more in number, ſo they were vaſtly ſuperiour in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to Mr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s <hi>approved Doctors</hi> and Fathers. For it was <hi>Theodotion</hi> and <hi>Symmachus,</hi> who (diſtinctly) tranſlated the Bible into Greek; ſo dextrouſly, that their Tranſlations, together with the Tranſlations of the LXX and of
<hi>Aquila,</hi> made the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (or fourfold Tranſlation) of <hi>Origen;</hi> which was the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as well as moſt celebrated (The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological) Work, of all Antiquity. It was
<hi>Lucianus,</hi> who reſtored the Bible of the LXX to its Purity. Of
<hi>Theodorus</hi> or <hi>Theodotus,</hi> St. <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> (tho a great Oppoſer of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians) confeſſes, that he was
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>very Learned. Paulus</hi> Patriarch and Archbiſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> was ſo elegant a Preacher, that they always hummed, and clapped him: and tho <hi>two</hi> Councils of the adverſe Party, aſſembled at <hi>Antioch</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him, for the Truths he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; the Antiochians deſpiſed theſe
<hi>(ſeditious)</hi> Councils, who had <hi>(riotouſly)</hi> combined againſt their <hi>Primate,</hi> and would by no means part with
<hi>Paulus.</hi> Of the whole Unitarian Party in general, it is noted in
<hi>Euſebius,</hi> that they were Learned in Logick, Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, Geometry, Phyſick, and the other liberal Sciences: and 'tis there (ridiculouſly) impured to them as a Fault, that they excelled in ſecular Learning; and (much more ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly) that they were great Criticks, and extremely curious in procuring correct Copies of the Bible. <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28. They were perfectly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, to judg of good Copies, and to correct faulty ones; by their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate Knowledg of the Hebrew Tongue: for St. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> (tho ſo much their back-Friend) aſſures us, that they were <hi>Hebraicae Linguae ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiſſimi, great Maſters in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Tongue.</hi> Epiph. Haereſ. Naz. c. 7.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> appeals here to <hi>the approved</hi> Doctors and Fathers: but it appears, that he would have it thought, that beſides the 20 Fathers (or thereabouts) whom he has cited; thoſe Fathers alſo whoſe Works are (ſo unhappily) loſt, were no leſs Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox (as 'tis called) in this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53124:3"/>about our Saviour's Divinity. But the Criticks, who have written ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and impartially concerning the Fathers, are of opinion, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there are now loſt about 200, for (ſome) 20 Ante-nicene Writers and Fathers who have been preſerved; we are to impute this Loſs, to the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors contained in their Books; more plainly, to their too manifeſt Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Arian and Minean (now called the Socinian) Hereſies. The famous Critick <hi>H. Valeſius,</hi> (whom Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, nay extols) in his firſt Note on <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11. ſpeaking of the Hypotypoſes of St. <hi>Clemens;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, <hi>Photius</hi> had obſerved, that they are full of Arian Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as that <hi>the Son is but a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and ſuch like: I ſay, that by occaſion of the ſaid Hypotypoſes, <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſius</hi> maketh this Note; <hi>Iſti libri ob errores (quibus ſcatebant) negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius habiti, tandem perierunt; nec alia (meo judicio) cauſa eſt, cur Papiae &amp; Hegeſippi (aliorum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum) libri interciderint.</hi> 'Tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, that the Errors intended by <hi>Valeſius,</hi> are the Seeds of Arianiſm and Unitarianiſm, which ſo much abounded in the Hypotypoſes of St. <hi>Clemens;</hi> and he ſaith thereupon, the becauſe of theſe Errors, not only the Hypotypoſes of
<hi>Clemens,</hi> but the Works of <hi>Hegeſippus, Papias,</hi> and other Primitive (Ante-nicene) Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, were firſt ſlighted, and then loſt. Which is in effect to ſay, that the viſible Agreement of the antient Fathers and Doctors with the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, hath been the Cauſe, that their Writings have miſcarried, are either loſt or elſe deſtroyed; ſo that of above 200 Ante-nicene Writers, ſcarce 20 are left to us, and thoſe alſo very imperfect. Therefore, if it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo, that Mr.
<hi>Bull</hi>'s <hi>approved Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> did really agree in their Faith about the Lord Chriſt, with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors or Fathers in the Nicene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; as he undertakes to prove, and thinks he has proved: yet his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance amounts to no more but this; that of the Writers or Fathers who preceded the Nicene Council, about 20 were for the Divinity of our Saviour, and more than
200 againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>II. The Characters of the Fathers, and their Works; more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of St. <hi>Barnabas, Hermas,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHEN a Man appeals to the Judgment and Authority of any ſort of Writers; the firſt thing to be conſidered, is, what is the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of thoſe Writers, and their Writings: Were the Writers skilful in that ſort of Learning, of which they are called to be Judges? Are the Works or Writings that are imputed to them, certainly genuine, really<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53124:4"/>and undoubtedly theirs? If ſo; yet have they not been corrupted, by (notorious) Additions, or Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo that 'tis queſtioned, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different and impartial Perſons, what was written by the Author; and what by the Interpolator? Farther, whereas Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Book is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Faith of the Nicene Fathers, that it agreed perfectly with the Faith of the Fathers who flouriſhed and wrote before that Council; it will be another neceſſary Queſtion, what was the Faith of the Nicene Fathers, either concerning the Divinity of our Saviour, or concerning the (pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Trinity? Laſtly, Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed given us his Opinion concerning the Faith of the Ante-nicene Fathers; but what ſay other (famous) Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; who, tho they were zealous Trinitarians, yet being more ſincere and impartial, it may be, they grant that the Doctrine of the Ante-nicene Writers of the Church, was no leſs than <hi>diametrically contrary</hi> to the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Faith, as well as to
<hi>the Reform</hi> that has been made of that Faith, by the Divines of the Schools. I ſhall reſolve all theſe Queſtions, in proper Places; at preſent, to the firſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>What is the true Character of theſe Writers, to whom Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed? He anſwers, concerning one, that he is
<hi>doctiſſimus, moſt learned;</hi> of another, that he is
<hi>peritiſſimus, moſt able:</hi> and not to tranſcribe all his Flowers, on theſe Fathers, he dubs them all, <hi>Doctores probati, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Doctors;</hi> which is the leaſt he ever ſays of them. It is in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree excuſable, becauſe it may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to his Zeal, or his Art; that he vends <hi>all his Geeſe for Swans:</hi> but ſure the very ſillieſt Idolaters of his (weak) Book, will hardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it; that he divides even all the Divine Attributes too, among theſe his (ſuppoſed) Friends. For one he calls <hi>ſanctiſſimus, moſt holy;</hi> another is
<hi>beatiſſimus, moſt bleſſed;</hi> a third is <hi>optimus, moſt gracious;</hi> and a fourth, <hi>maximus, the moſt high.</hi> There is hardly a Page of his Book, but you meet with one or more of theſe Extravagancies: I ſuppoſe, he tarried longer at School than is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; and ſo being an old Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, he could never ſince ſpeak but only in <hi>the ſuperlative Degree,</hi> no not when it borders on Blaſphemy it ſelf. But tho it is true, that few (I believe, none but Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>) have ſpoke or thought of the (remaining) Ante-nicene Fathers, at this wild rate: yet the Opinion that Men ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally have of theſe Authors, is, that they were certain moſt grave, learned, ſage, and experienced Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; and called Fathers, not more for their Antiquity, than for their profound Judgment, and perfect Knowledg, in all the Parts of the Chriſtian Religion. Becauſe the Heads and Patrons of Sects, affect to quote the Fathers; and, if poſſible, to fill their Margin with References to Places in the Fathers: it is therefore almoſt univerſally ſuppoſed, that ſo great Deference has not been paid to them, without moſt juſt Cauſe for it.<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53124:4"/>'Tis in the Father, that the Papiſt finds the whole Doctrine of the Council of
<hi>Trent:</hi> in the Fathers, the Lutheran finds alſo his Articles; the Calviniſt and the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> theirs. The very Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Anabaptiſts, and Antinomians, are now turned Father-mongers; and in the Fathers find their Diſcipline and Doctrine, no leſs than their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers find alſo theirs. In ſhort, there is ſuch a ſcuffling for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by all Parties, that 'tis no wonder, if Perſons who have not themſelves read 'em, have a very raiſed and noble Idea of theſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But all the Glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (I ſpeak of the Ante-nicene Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and except alſo <hi>Origen</hi> out of the Number) is wholly due to the Vanity of modern learned Men; who quote theſe Books, not becauſe indeed they value them; but becauſe being antient Monuments, known to few, and underſtood by fewer; he ſeems a great learned Man, who can drop Sentences out of theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Books. But let us begin, to ſee what indeed they were.</p>
               <p>The firſt of the Fathers and their Writings, alledged by Dr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> is an Epiſtle (if it pleaſe Heaven) of St.
<hi>Barnabas,</hi> the Apoſtle. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that St. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt and Coadjutor of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is alſo honoured with the Title of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; <hi>Acts</hi> 14.4. but that he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him an Epiſtle, I ſhall deſire a better Proof than I have yet ſeen. What Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> ſays of him, is,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Our <hi>moſt learned Hammond,</hi> and
<hi>the moſt high Voſſius</hi> believe, this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was written by St. <hi>Barnabas;</hi> chiefly for this Reaſon; becauſe it is cited under the Name of <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinue, Origen,</hi> and othe Antients. Nor can thoſe of the adverſe Party, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg any thing to the contrary, but only this; that the Author of this Epiſtle expounds too myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſome Paſſages of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</q>
               </p>
               <p>No; no other Reaſon to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, why this Epiſtle was not written by the Evangeliſt <hi>Barnabas?</hi> Does he not know, that divers Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks have obſerved, that if the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents had really believed that St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> the Companion, Fellow-Evangeliſt, and Fellow-Apoſtle of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> had wrote this Epiſtle; they would (undoubtedly) have reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned it among the Canonical Books of Scripture, as St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles are. And has not <hi>Euſebius</hi> informed us, why this Epiſtle was not counted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical; when he ſays:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Some Books are received as Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<hi>by the common Conſent of all;</hi> namely, the four Goſpels, the
<hi>Acts,</hi> the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>John,</hi> the firſt of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and (if you will) the Revelation of St. <hi>John.</hi> ſome other Books are <hi>of queſtioned and doubtful Authority,</hi> as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of <hi>James</hi> and
<hi>Jude,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſecond and thrid of St. <hi>John:</hi> but <hi>theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are counterfeit pieces,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; the<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53124:5"/>Acts of
<hi>Paul,</hi> the Revelation of Peter, <hi>the pretended Epiſtle of</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe are Counterfeits.</q> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> may conſider at his leiſure, of what Weight the Judgment of (his <hi>moſt learned</hi>) <hi>Hammond</hi> and <hi>(the moſt high) Voſſius</hi> may be, when put into the Scale againſt <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> ſpeaking (not his own, but) the Senſe of the Primitive Church. And when his Hand is in, let him tell us, what might be in the Mind of <hi>the pretended Barnabas,</hi> as
<hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> calls him, to ſcandalize all the Apoſtles, by ſaying; that before they were called to be Apoſtles, they were (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>the moſt flagitious Men in the World.</hi> I am of opinion, we ought to anſwer, that 'tis not to be wondred at, if <hi>a counterfeit Apoſtle belies the true ones.</hi> This Crimination of the true Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles is in the 5<hi>th</hi> Chapter of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>The more learned and impartial Criticks freely obſerve, concerning this Epiſtle, that 'tis full of <hi>ſtrained and dull</hi> Allegories, <hi>extravagant and incongruous</hi> Explications of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and abundance of <hi>ſilly and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Fables concerning Animals.</hi> And what all judicious Men think of the Epiſtle, is, that it is indeed very antient, being quoted by <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</hi> and <hi>Origen:</hi> but that it was forged about the beginning of the 2<hi>d</hi> Century, or the
2<hi>d</hi> Century being well advanced; when alſo the Goſpels of St.
<hi>Thomas,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Matthias,</hi> the Acts of St.
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> and other Apoſtles, were deviſed and publiſhed, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebiue</hi> witneſſes, <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 3.
<hi>c.</hi> 25. But leſt this Epiſtle ſhould be thought to be of ſomewhat the more Credit, becauſe 'tis (barely) quoted by <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> and <hi>Origen;</hi> the Reader may take notice, that <hi>Clemens</hi> cites alſo other counterfeit Works of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as particularly the Revelation of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as has been noted by <hi>Euſebius, H. E. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 14. And nothing is more common with <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> than to quote ſuch ſuppoſititious Writings; as (for Inſtance) the Book of <hi>Enoch,</hi> the Revelation of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the Doctrine of St.
<hi>Peter,</hi> and many more; concerning which Citations the Reader may ſee what Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> has obſerved at large, <hi>Cent.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi>
113.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s next <hi>approved Father</hi> is the great, either Prophet or Impoſtor, <hi>Hermas;</hi> in his Book called the
<hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> or Shepherd.</p>
               <p>We grant, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions one <hi>Hermas,</hi> Rom. 16.14. and we doubt not, that the Author of <hi>the Shepherd</hi> would be underſtood to be that <hi>Hormas,</hi> for he makes himſelf contemporary with <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> (mentioned alſo by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil.
4.3.) Viſion 2<hi>d. Chap.</hi> 4. The Shepherd of <hi>Hermas</hi> is diſtinguiſhed into 3 Books; whereof the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains 4 Viſions, the ſecond 12 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the third 10 Similitudes: but both the Commands and Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes may be called Viſions and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies; becauſe they are Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Charges, made to him by Angels. The Scene of theſe Viſions<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53124:5"/>is <hi>Arcadia;</hi> and that we may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that this Author would be taken for a Prophet, and would have his Book paſs for a Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation: he introduces the Angel (in his 2<hi>d Viſion, Chap.</hi> 4.) as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him, that he ſhould prepare 3 Copies of theſe Viſions; one for <hi>Clement</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be ſent by him to all the Churches; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for <hi>Grapte,</hi> who ſhould inſtruct out of it the Widows and their Children; the third
<hi>Hermas</hi> himſelf was to read to the Presbyters of the City of
<hi>Rome.</hi> This is the Book and Author, in which Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> finds (or thinks he finds) ſome Paſſages in favour of our Saviour's Divinity; as I ſaid at firſt, we muſt carefully exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what is the true Character of this Work and Writer.</p>
               <p>By what has been ſaid, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to every one; that this (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) <hi>Hermas</hi> either was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet or an Impoſtor: there is no Middle between theſe two, when the Perſon pretends to Viſions, to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences with Angels, and ſuch like extraordinary things. That the (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) <hi>Hermas</hi> was not a Prophet, is certain to me, by theſe Arguments. 1. He owns, in the third <hi>Command,</hi> that he was a moſt egregious, and common Liar: he ſaith expreſly, that he ſcarce ever ſpake a true Word in his whole Life, but <hi>always</hi> lived in Diſſimulation. and that to <hi>all</hi> Men. He weeps hereupon; and doubts, whether he can be ſaved: but his Angel aſſures him, that if for the time to come he will leave off his Lying, he may attain to Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He that was ſo addicted to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 'tis no wonder that he has coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited alſo Viſions and Colloquies with Angels; or that to gain Credit to his Chimeras and Follies, he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd them on <hi>Hermas</hi> an Apoſtolical Man and Friend of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as others before him had laid their ſpurious Off-ſprings to the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But, 2. Some of his (Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial) Viſions contain manifeſt Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoods; particularly, he maketh his Angel to tell him, that <hi>the whole World is made up of twelve Nations, Simil.</hi> 9. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. Being a Perſon altogether ignorant of ſecular Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as appears in all his three Books, 'twas almoſt impoſſible, but that in his feigned Conferences with Angels he ſhould ſometimes make them to ſpeak divers things both falſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. 3. To add no more on this Trifler; he has been judged to be no Prophet, by the whole Catholick Church, in that his Book is not reckoned among the Canonical Books of Scripture: were it a real Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God, by the Miniſtry of Angels, as the Author pretends; and ſo eſteemed by the Catholick Church; it muſt have been put among the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Books. It is true, when it firſt appeared, it impoſed on ſome Churches, by the Boldneſs of its Pretence; and therefore was read in thoſe Churches, as other genuine Parts of Scripture were: but even then, very many of the more Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rejected it; and as the Church began to fill with learned and able<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53124:6"/>Perſons, it was not only every where laid aſide, but cenſured as both falſe and fooliſh. Of ſo many of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients as condemned it, we need on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take notice of <hi>Euſebius;</hi> who, ſpeaking of the Books uſed by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, whether privately or in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, ſays;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Some Books are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>by common Conſent of all;</hi> others are <hi>of queſtioned and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority;</hi> and finally others are ſuppoſititious and counterfeit, of which laſt kind (ſaith he) are the Acts of <hi>Paul,</hi> the Revelation of
<hi>Peter, the Shepherd of</hi> Hermas, and the pretended Epiſtle of
<hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s third Author is <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi> but neither is this Writer a whit better or honeſter, than the <hi>pretended Barnabas,</hi> or the <hi>counterfeit Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</hi> I do not mean to deny, that we have ſtill the Epiſtles that are quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Antients (<hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi>) under the Name of <hi>Ignatius:</hi> but this I affirm, that they were forged under <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Name, about the time that ſo many other Impoſtures were publiſhed under the Names of Apoſiles, and of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Men; of which, the Learned know, there were almoſt an infinite Number.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee, firſt, what the Criticks of the contrary Perſwaſion, have to alledg for the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius;</hi> we may hear Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> for them all, becauſe he has written laſt, and more largely than any other. He obſerves that St. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> being thereto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by the Philippians, ſent them the Epiſtles of
<hi>Ignatius;</hi> to which he alſo prefixed an Epiſtle of his own, directed to the ſame Philippians. Well, we acknowledg that <hi>Polycarp,</hi> writing to the Philippians, tells them towards the Cloſe of his Epiſtle, that he had ſent them (according to their Deſire) the Epiſtles of
<hi>Ignatius,</hi> that had by any means come to his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg or Hand. He adds, that in theſe Epiſtles,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"<hi>Ignatius</hi> treats <hi>of Faith and Patience, and all other things that tend to Edification in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q> But here, two Doubts ariſe. Firſt, whether the Epiſtles that we <hi>now have,</hi> were the ſame that are intended in the Epiſtle of
<hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp,</hi> or ſo much as directed to the ſame Perſons or Churches? The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the doubt is, the Epiſtles that we now have, treat of nothing leſs than <hi>Faith and Patience,</hi> nay they treat not of Faith and Patience at all; much leſs (if it could be) are they a Collection of
<hi>all things that tend to Edification in Chriſt;</hi> they are very far from being a kind of <hi>Summary of the Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> either in Faith or Morals. They are Letters of Compliment and Reſpect, not of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction or Exhortation. The other Doubt is, of what Authority and Credit is this Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp;</hi> on which the Credit of the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius</hi> wholly depend? Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> anſwers; It is quoted by St. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus.</hi> Suppoſing now, what Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> has not proved, nor can prove; that the Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp</hi> intended by
<hi>Ireneus,</hi> is (in part) that Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp</hi> which we
<hi>now have,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53124:6"/>both the one and the other are directed to the Philippians: I ſay, ſuppoſing this; yet divers learned Criticks are of opinion, that the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Epiſtle written by the true
<hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarp,</hi> and which <hi>Ireneus</hi> intends, concludes with the
12<hi>th</hi> Chapter; where he ſolemnly gives them his <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictory Bleſſing:</hi> ſo that the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chapters which ſpeak of
<hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> his Epiſtles, and other Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, have (probably) been added by him (whoever he was) who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived Epiſtles in the Name of
<hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> No, ſays Mr. <hi>du Pin,</hi> nor can <hi>that</hi> be; for <hi>Ireneus</hi> (who praiſes that Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp</hi>) quotes alſo certain Words, which are found in the very Epiſtles of
<hi>Ignatius.</hi> But I do not know that <hi>Ireneus</hi> quotes any Epiſtle of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> or ſo much as names the Man; but only repeats a Saying of a certain Chriſtian Martyr, which Saying the Forger of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of
<hi>Ignatius</hi> thought fit to inſert into thoſe Epiſtles, which himſelf wrote in the Name and Perſon of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius.</hi> In ſhort, I ſay, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and before him <hi>Origen,</hi> owned the preſent Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> becauſe they conſidered the Matter but light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as not being any way concerned to diſprove them. And
<hi>Ireneus</hi> (ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than they) quotes an Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp</hi> to the Philippians; as alſo (elſewhere) ſome Words that are now found in an Epiſtle imputed to <hi>Ignatius:</hi> but ſuppoſing that we <hi>now have</hi> that Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> yet it ſeems likely that the Epiſtle did then conclude with the 12<hi>th</hi> Chapter, without any mention of the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius;</hi> and we cannot be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that
<hi>Ireneus</hi> quotes the Words of one of the Epiſtles of
<hi>Ignatius,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than that the Forger of thoſe Epiſtles borrowed thoſe Words from <hi>Ireneus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be ſaid; but why all this Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piciouſneſs? it will be hard to prove any Matter of Fact, of remote Ages; if ſuch cloſe and ſtrict Proofs be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. I anſwer; there is too much Cauſe to ſtart theſe Doubts and Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. For we have the Epiſtle of
<hi>Polycarp</hi> to the Philippians, as alſo the Epiſtles of
<hi>Ignatius,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdoms of <hi>Ignatius</hi> and
<hi>Polycarp,</hi> whereof the latter is contained in an Epiſtle (pretended to be written) by the Church of <hi>Smyrna;</hi> with this Advertiſement at the end of them:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"This Epiſtle (concerning the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom of
<hi>Polycarp</hi>) was tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by <hi>Cains,</hi> from the Copy of
<hi>Ireneus,</hi> who was a Diſciple of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarp.</hi> And I
<hi>Socrates</hi> tranſcribed it at <hi>Corinth,</hi> from the Copy of
<hi>Caius.</hi>—After which, I <hi>Pionius</hi> wrote it from the Copy before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, having <hi>ſearched it out by the Revelation of</hi> Polycarp, <hi>who directed me to it;</hi> having gathered <hi>theſe things</hi> together, now almoſt corrupted by Time, that Jeſus Chriſt may alſo gather me, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Elect ones.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here then is an Epiſtle; namely, the Epiſtle of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> concerning the Martyrdom of <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp;</hi> and as
<hi>the Advertiſement</hi> ſaith, <hi>other things that were almoſt corrupted<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53124:7"/>thorow Proceſs of Time;</hi> namely, a Relation of the Martyrdom of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> and ſeven Epiſtles of
<hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius:</hi> all theſe miraculouſly diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to
<hi>Pionius</hi> (the good) by <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp,</hi> after his Death. It ſhould ſeem, <hi>Polycarp</hi> could not reſt, even in Reſt; nor be bleſſed, in Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; till he had broke from the Abodes of Bliſs, and appeared to (honeſt) <hi>Pionius;</hi> to make known to him, where theſe
<hi>Golden Remains</hi> were to be found. If we ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Advertiſement ſo, as ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Epiſtle concerning
<hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp</hi>'s Martyrdom came to <hi>Pionius</hi> by Revelation; and the other Pieces and Epiſtles were collected by the proper Induſtry of
<hi>Pionius:</hi> yet thus, the whole Collection depends on the Credit of
<hi>Pionius;</hi> who with moſt, I doubt, has utterly ruined his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, as a Publiſher of antient Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by his Pretence that (at leaſt) part of them are by Revelation. The Clowns will certainly cry out, Away with Impoſtors: let <hi>Pionius</hi> take his Bandle to himſelf, both his own Collection, and <hi>Polycarp</hi>'s Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for coming from him, we muſt needs believe them to be true alike! Could not this Knave (will they ſay) be content, to perſonate <hi>firſt</hi> the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> in a moſt <hi>palpable</hi> Fiction; <hi>then</hi> the Aſſiſtants at the Martyrdom of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and finally <hi>Ignatius</hi> himſelf; but he muſt ſeek too to confirm his counterfeit Wares by Revelations from Heaven, by Viſions and Apparitions of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Saints? We demand Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities out of the Antients concerning the (pretended) Divinity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, from Writings and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are verified by <hi>ſome good humane Teſtimony;</hi> our Oppoſers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer us out of Books, which ſome of their Fraternity received by Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>by Revelations from the Dead:</hi> but if once we allow of ſuch Proofs, what end will there be of Fictions? The departed Saints were firſt called up, to bear witneſs to certain Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Books: but in the next Age, when the firſt Cheat had taken with many; they were made to witneſs to their Bones and Reliques, in order to their being <hi>inſhrined and worſhipped;</hi> this laſt ſort of Apparitions were eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whit as true, as the firſt. They will prove, they ſay, their (conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial co-eternal) Trinity, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the <hi>Antenicene</hi> Fathers; but from
<hi>the Apoſtolical Fathers,</hi> that is the Fathers that had Converſe with the very Apoſtles, and flouriſhed (ſome of them) to the Year 150: but when theſe Authors are produced, they are <hi>Barnabas</hi> the Apoſtle, the Prophet <hi>Hermas,</hi> the Martyrdoms and Epiſtles of
<hi>Polycarp</hi> and <hi>Ignatius;</hi> whereof the two former (we have ſeen) are rejected as ſpurious by the Catholick Church, the other are grounded on Viſions and Apparitions to one <hi>Pionius.</hi> But let us conſider the Contents of theſe (pretious) Pieces, the <hi>Pionian</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The Martyidom of <hi>Polycarp</hi> ſaith,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"That when the Fire began to blaze to a great height; <hi>the Flame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an Arch, like the Sail of a <pb n="13" facs="tcp:53124:7"/>Ship againſt a full Wind,</hi> incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd the Martyr's Body at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, without hurting it; while <hi>from his Body proceeded a Smell, like to Frankincenſe, or ſome other rich Spices.</hi>
                  </q> The firſt of theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles would make <hi>the Boys</hi> wonder, and ſhout; and was of no farther Uſe: the other is yet more ſuſpicious, for could not the Aſſiſtants diſtinguiſh the Smell of Frankincenſe; no not from any other of the Oriental Spices, tho both <hi>that</hi> and <hi>they</hi> were every day uſed (in thoſe times) in their Funeral Piles? <hi>But the Tale goes on;</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"When <hi>the Wicked</hi> ſaw, that the Martyr could not be hurt by the Fire, they commanded the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner to ſtick his Dagger into <hi>Polycarp,</hi> and ſo diſpatch him: which the Hangman preſently did; but behold two other Miracles, <hi>and (believe me) as credible as either of the former.</hi> For out of the Wound, which was in the Martyr's ſide, <hi>ſprang a Live-dove;</hi> and then, <hi>ſuch a Torrent of Blood</hi> (out of the Body of an old Man, upwards of 86 Years) <hi>as wholly extinguiſhed all that great Fire.</hi>
                  </q> This <hi>Text</hi> needs no Comment.</p>
               <p>The Martyrdom of <hi>Ignatius</hi> affords another
<hi>ſort</hi> of Wonders, Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Viſions. For the Night in which he ſuffered, he appeared to the Chriſtians, who had aſſiſted at his Martyrdom: to ſome, <hi>as one ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after hard Labour;</hi> to others,
<hi>ſtanding by the Lord,</hi> with much Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, and in unſpeakable Glory; but however, moſt courteouſly and lovingly <hi>imbracing them all.</hi> 'Tis <hi>a Miracle,</hi> to me, that he had not done ſweating, now that he was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at Bleſſedneſs; or do Souls (in their Etherial Vehicles) ſweat? But 'tis <hi>a greater Miracle,</hi> that appearing at Chriſt's right Hand in Heaven, he could at the ſame time imbrace (or ſeem to imbrace) thoſe upon Earth.</p>
               <p>As to the Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering by whom they are ſaid to be written, and to whom; they are more marvellous than the Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was Biſhop at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> where he was condemned to Martyrdom by the Emperor <hi>Trajan;</hi> but was ſent to
<hi>Rome,</hi> (guarded by ten Souldiers) to ſuffer there, in the Amphitheater. In the Amphithea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Condemned fought with Beaſts, Lions, Leopards, and ſuch like, till one or the other were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And for this Reaſon, they choſe out of the Priſoners of War, and the Condemned, the moſt robuſt young Men, that could make ſome Sport for the People, by the valiant Reſiſtance they made to the Beaſts. Therefore here are two things very incredible; that <hi>Ignatius, a decrepid old Man,</hi> for he had been a Biſhop above 40 Years, ſhould be condemned (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Cuſtom, and to the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe Sports) <hi>to fight the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> And next, that in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, he ſhould be ſent with ten Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers <hi>(leſt he ſhould maſter, and got away from four or five)</hi> to guard him, above
1500 Miles. To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould they be at ſo vaſi a Charge, eſpecially when it had been more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53124:8"/>and more effectual to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to execute him in his own Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of
<hi>Antioch?</hi> The (pretended) E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles however ſuppoſe all this; they are written to divers Churches, as the Old Man paſſes from
<hi>Antioch</hi> to <hi>Rome, to fight the Lions:</hi> and either theſe Epiſtles muſt be granted to be forged, or we muſt admit theſe (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant incredible) Suppoſitions. But the Epiſtles themſelves more plainly diſcover the Impoſture.</p>
               <p>That to the <hi>Romans</hi> is chiefly, and almoſt wholly imployed, in adviſing and intreating the Chriſtians of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they ſhould not reſcue him from the Execution, but permit him to undergo his Sentence. The true <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> could never write ſuch an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd thing. Was it ever heard of, that Chriſtians attempted to reſcue their Martyrs; on the contrary, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom was reckoned (in thoſe days) the very higheſt Glory of a Chriſtian: and it was the Indeavour of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans who aſſiſted at Martyrdoms, to incourage the Martyrs, by all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ways, to ſuffer couragiouſly; in ſhort, <hi>they would as little have reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Martyr, as they would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Sacrilege.</hi> Beſides, were the Number and Power of the Chriſtians at <hi>Rome,</hi> in thoſe early times, ſo conſiderable, that they might reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably attempt ſo bold an Action, as to attack the Amphitheater, and the Imperial Guards, on behalf of a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? <hi>Ignatius</hi> perfectly knew the contrary to all this; and therefore could not be Author of an Epiſtle, which ſuppoſes theſe Follies.</p>
               <p>The Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> is full of weak things. He tells them there, with equal Sillineſs and Falſhood, that the Virginity of <hi>Mary,</hi> her Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and the Death of Chriſt, the three great Myſteries <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> of the Goſpel, <hi>were kept concealed from the Devil;</hi> and done in ſecret by God. He adds, that the Star, which appeared before our Saviour's Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did <hi>exceedingly outſhine the Sun, and all other Lights of Heaven. Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> did not conſider; that if ſo, it would not have been called a Star, but <hi>another Sun:</hi> and that there would have been no Night in <hi>Judea,</hi> till this Star diſappeared.</p>
               <p>But ſee, how they have made a dying Man, a Biſhop and Saint of the firſt Age of Chriſtianity, complement with the Church of the Magneſians:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"I have been judged worthy to ſee you, by
<hi>Damus, your moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Biſhop;</hi> by your <hi>very worthy Presbyters, Baſſus</hi> and <hi>Apollonius;</hi> and by <hi>my Fellow-Servant</hi> Socio, your Deacon: In whom I rejoice, becauſe he is ſubject to his Biſhop <hi>as to the Grace of God;</hi> and to the Presbytery, <hi>as to the Law of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q> Who ſees not, that this is more like <hi>a Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> than an Apoſtolical Biſhop, and a primitive Martyr? In the ſame Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, he exhorts them not to obſerve the Sabbaths: but it is certain that the Sabbaths were obſerved, together with the Lord's Day, till after the Times of Great
<hi>Conſtantine;</hi> it is not likely, the true <hi>Ignatius</hi> would oppoſe the Cuſtom and <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53124:8"/>Practice of the Univerſal Church.</p>
               <p>To the Trallians he ſaith, that the Deacons are to be reverenced <hi>as Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> the Biſhops, <hi>as God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> the Presbytery, <hi>as the College of Apoſtles.</hi> A complicated Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my! He tells them afterwards, that their particular Biſhop is ſuch, that <hi>his very Look is inſtructive.</hi> He that writes thus of Biſhops and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, muſt needs be <hi>an approved Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor;</hi> but I dare almoſt to give them my corporal Oath, he never was a Doctor of the firſt Age.</p>
               <p>Writing to the Philippians, he forgets not (his uſual and conſtant Cuſtom) to claw their Biſhop. Your Biſhop, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> is able to do more by his Silence, than others by their Speech. There are many Biſhops ſtill of this mind; but our Saviour's Motto was, <hi>My Sheep hear my Voice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the Smyrneans he ſays;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"'Tis a good thing to be ſubject <hi>to God, and to the Biſhop.</hi>
                  </q> Then he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes <hi>their very worthy Riſhop;</hi> their <hi>venerable Presbytery;</hi> your <hi>Deacons my Fellow-Servants;</hi> the <hi>very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> Daphnus <hi>and</hi> Eutychus.</p>
               <p>The laſt Epiſtle is to <hi>Polycarp;</hi> and tho he writes to a Biſhop, not to a Church, he cannot forbear his (odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) Daubing.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"He that thinks, <hi>ſays this Pſeudo-Martyr,</hi> that he knows more than his Biſhop, is ruined: Hearken to the Biſhop, that God may hearken to you.</q> In the Concluſion of this Epiſtle, as if he were a Prophet, he ſays; <hi>my Grace be with</hi> Attalus, <hi>and with thee</hi> Polycarp. A ſtrain which, ſome will think, exceeds <hi>the Fulneſs of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Character;</hi> which this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor aſſumes in the Epiſtle to the Trallians: I ſalute you,
<hi>ſaith he to the Trallians,</hi> in the Fulneſs of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Character. In ſhort, no one can read theſe Epiſtles, with Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and impartially, but he will ſee, what was the Aim of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of them; namely, under the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Authority and Name of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> to magnify the Reverence and Reſpect belonging to Church-men. This is the Beginning, Middle, and End of all theſe Epiſtles; except on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that to the Romans; where (to cover his Deſign, and diſcover his Folly) he only adviſes the Chriſtians, <hi>not to reſcue him from the Imperial Guards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are all the Apoſtolical Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Writings, that our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers can muſter up, during the firſt 150 Years of Chriſtianity; that is, to the Times, when the Socinians (and all Proteſtants) confeſs, that the Faith began to be actually cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. I have proved, that the Monuments they have to produce, are unqueſtionably and inconteſtably counterfeit; and therefore I do not think my ſelf concerned, to examine the (few and impertinent) Paſſages, alledged out of them by Dr.
<hi>Bull:</hi> but before I proceed to his other <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Doctors,</hi>
'tis but reaſonable that I ſhould have leave, to ſearch what Authors and Books of theſe times, of which we are ſpeaking, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Unitarians; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Socinians. The Queſtion<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53124:9"/>between Dr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> and the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, is; what (genuine) Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Remains there are, of the Period which Church-Hiſtorians have called <hi>the Apoſtolical Succeſſion:</hi> that is, of the Time in which thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with the Apoſtles, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the pure Faith of the Goſpel from their very Mouths, flouriſhed? And whether thoſe Remains or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents do favour the Unitarians, or the Trinitarians; whether they teach the Doctrine of one God, or of three? We have ſeen what Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce for their (pretended) Trinity; his Apoſtle <hi>Barnabas,</hi> the Prophet <hi>Hermas;</hi> both of them rejected, as falſe and ſooliſh, by the Catholick Church: Next, the Revelations of <hi>Pionius;</hi> that is, the Martyrdoms of <hi>Polycarp</hi> and <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and their Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, all which being almoſt periſhed and worn out by Time, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to <hi>Pionius</hi> by one from the Dead. It is true, our Oppoſers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſo long Maſters, have made uſe of their Power, to deſtroy and aboliſh (as much as was poſſible) whatever Monuments of thoſe firſt Times, that (too notoriouſly) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted the Innovations in the Faith, that were made by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils of <hi>Nice, Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon:</hi> yet as there is no Battel ſo bloody and cruel, but ſome (tho it may be a very few) have the good luck to eſcape from the Maſſacre; ſo from this Perſecution of Books and Writings, ſome (illuſtrious) Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Witneſſes to the Truth, are come down even to our Times. Theſe are, the Apoſtles Creed; an unqueſtioned Epiſtle, of St. <hi>Clemens Romanus;</hi> the Accounts given (by unſuſpected Hiſtorians) of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens or Ebionites, the Mineans, and the Alogi, who all held as the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians now do, concerning God and the Perſon of our Saviour; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitions of St.
<hi>Clemens,</hi> which tho (it may be) they are not rightly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him, yet are a moſt antient Book, and ſerve to ſhow what was the current Doctrine of thoſe Times; they are cited by <hi>Origen</hi> in divers Places. by <hi>Euſebius, Aikanaſins,</hi> and others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Apoſtles Creed.</head>
               <p>COncerning the Apoſtles Creed, we muſt reſolve two Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: What it teaches; and who were the Compilers of it? To the firſt, the Creed it ſelf anſwers;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"I bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eve in <hi>one</hi> God;</q> 
                  <hi>ſo this Creed was antiently read both in the Eaſt and Weſt;</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"the Father, Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth.</q> In theſe Words the Father is character'd by theſe Names, Properties and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions; that he is <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> God,
<hi>Almighty,</hi> and <hi>Maker of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53124:9"/>Concerning the Lord Chriſt, it ſaith;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"And in Jeſus Chriſt, his <hi>only</hi> Son (Gr. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten</hi> Son) our Lord.</q> So the Characters of our Saviour, are; that he is (not the one God, but) the <hi>only begotten</hi> Son of the <hi>only</hi> (or one) God, and that he is <hi>our Lord.</hi> Our <hi>Lord</hi> he is, as he is our Saviour, Teacher, and Head of the Church both in Heaven and Earth. He is called the <hi>only begotten</hi> Son of the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (or <hi>one</hi>) God, to diſtinguiſh him from all other Sons of God; from Angels, who were (not begotten, but) <hi>created</hi> Sons; from Holy Men, who are <hi>adopted</hi> Sons; and from <hi>Adam,</hi> who is called the Son of God, not becauſe he was generated or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten,</hi> but <hi>made</hi> or formed by God himſelf immediately. Well, but it may be this only-begotten Son of God, is an only-begotten Son in ſome higher Senſe; and namely, by eternal Generation, from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Eſſence of God; whereby he is God, no leſs than the Father is God. But the Compilers of this Creed knew nothing, or however have ſaid nothing, of any ſuch Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: ſo far from that, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his Generation, and his Perſon, <hi>by humane Characters,</hi> and <hi>by ſuch only.</hi> Every thing that they ſay here, either of his Perſon or Generation, is not only humane; but <hi>inconſiſtent with Divinity.</hi> He was conceived (ſay they) of the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> was crucified, dead, and buried; he aroſe again from the Dead, aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; ſitteth on the right Hand of God, <hi>i. e. is next in Dignity to God.</hi> Our very. Oppoſers confeſs, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe is a Deſcription of a mere humane Perſon, and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: even <hi>they</hi> acknowledg, that God cannot be conceived, be born, die, aſcend; and leaſt of all, be at God's right Hand, or <hi>next to God:</hi> to be <hi>God</hi> and <hi>next to God,</hi> are wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent.</p>
               <p>There is no anſwering here; that the (before-mentioned) are intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, only as the Characters of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Humane Nature. For a Creed being an Inſtitution (or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction) what we are to believe in the main and ſundamental Articles of Religion; eſpecially concerning the Perſons of the Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit: if the firſt is deſcribed as the one (or <hi>only</hi>) God; and the Son, only by Characters that ſpeak him a mere Man, and are utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with Divinity; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, that the Compilers of the Creed, really intended, that we ſhould believe the Father is the one God; and the Son a <hi>mere</hi> Man, tho not <hi>a common</hi> Man, becauſe conceived (not of Man but) of the Holy Spirit, which is the Power and Energy of God. If they had meant, or but known, that the Son and Spirit are
<hi>eternal and divine Perſons,</hi> no leſs than the Father; they have done to both of them the greateſt (poſſible) Wrong: becauſe in the ſame Creed in which they declare, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Father is the
<hi>one</hi> God, Almighty, and Maker of Heaven and<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53124:10"/>Earth; they believe the Son was conceived, born, died, deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, aſcended into Heaven, is <hi>next to God,</hi> that is, they believe he is
<hi>a mere Man;</hi> and concerning the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they believe no higher thing, than of the Church, we believe <hi>in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Spirit and <hi>in the Holy</hi> Catholick Church. It is evident then, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſtable by any fair and ſincere Conſiderer; that whoever made this Creed, either they did not know that any other Perſon but the Father is <hi>God,</hi> or
<hi>Almighty,</hi> or <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth:</hi> or they have negligently or wickedly concealed it. The Latter is a Suppoſition, that none will make; therefore the other is the Truth of the Matter: and it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains only, that we enquire, who were the Framers of this Creed?</p>
               <p>The Creed that bears the Name of the Apoſtles Creed, was always reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned both by Fathers and Moderns, to be really compoſed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; for a Rule of Uniformity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves in their Preaching, and of Faith to all the Converts: till about the middle of this preſent Age,
<hi>G. J. Voſſius</hi> publiſhed a Book, wherein he denies, that either the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, or the 120 Diſciples (who are mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. and who aſſiſted and voted with the Apoſtles in publick Matters) were Authors of this Creed. He thinketh, it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Creed of the particular Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that the Original of it was this. Becauſe it was the Cuſtom to interrogate Perſons that were to be baptized, whether they believed in God the Father, in the Lord Chriſt the Son of God, and in the Holy Ghoſt; in whoſe Names Baptiſm is adminiſtred: therefore in proceſs of Time it became a Form of Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for Perſons who were admitted to Baptiſm, to ſay; I believe in God the Father, in Jeſus Chriſt his only-begotten Son, and in the Holy Ghoſt. Afterwards, ſome few more Words were added to theſe, as a fuller De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription both of the Father and Son: and as Hereſies grew up, new Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were added to the Creed, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to them; and to diſtinguiſh Catholicks from Hereticks. Againſt all Hereticks and Schiſmaticks in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, this Article was made;
<hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Holy Catholick Church:</hi> againſt the Sects of the Gnoſticks, this Article, <hi>I believe the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body.</hi> This is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of <hi>Voſſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe it was ſo evident, that this Creed makes only the Father to be God; and that it ſpeaks of the Son, by only <hi>humane Characters,</hi> and ſays not the leaſt Word of the Divinity of the Holy Spirit: therefore this Book of <hi>Voſſius</hi> was received with a mighty Applauſe, among all the Denomian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Trinitarians; Papiſts, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, Calviniſts, and all others. They ſaw themſelves delivered by this Book, from ſuch an Allegation and Aughority againſt the Doctrine of the Trinity; as was more than equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, to all their (pretended) Proofs from the Fathers, or from the Holy Scriptures, For what are all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if indeed they were all of their<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53124:10"/>ſide; when oppoſed by the College of Apoſtles? And what are ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental and very dubious Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of ſome particular Writer of Holy Scripture; againſt a Creed, compoſed by the Concurrence and Conſent of all the Apoſtles, and of their Senate (or Council) the CXX? A Creed, in which they, not inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally (in which caſe, Men often ſpeak looſly and incorrectly) but
<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly</hi> and <hi>deſignedly</hi> declare, what is the true Faith to be believed by all Chriſtians concerning the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. I ſay, for this Reaſon 'tis not to be much wondred, that
<hi>Voſſius</hi> his Book was ſo kindly received; or that the Trinitarians, of whatſoever Perſwaſion, have (gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally) ever ſince followed the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of <hi>Voſſius.</hi> If now and then <hi>a learned Man</hi> has diſſented from the new Opinion; he has always been laugh'd out of Countenance by the Croud of <hi>Pretenders to Learning. Voſſius</hi> ſays;</p>
               <p n="1">1. St. <hi>Luke,</hi> in his <hi>Acts</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, would never have omitted ſo memorable a Tranſaction; as the compiling a Creed by all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for a Rule of <hi>Doctrine</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Succeſſors in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral Office, and of
<hi>Faith</hi> to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts. He has ſet down many leſſer Matters, the Election of <hi>Matthias</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Apoſtolate of <hi>Judas;</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Apoſtles and Elders, aſſembled in Council, concerning the Ritual and Judicial Parts of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaick Law; and even divers petty Matters, relating only to <hi>private</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: and is it credible, that he ſhould not ſay a Word of <hi>the Rule of Faith;</hi> of
<hi>a Creed,</hi> made by the joint Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all the Apoſtles, and intended for the general and perpetual Uſe of both Paſtors and People? But beſides that this Creed is never ſpoke of, in the <hi>Acts;</hi> none of the Apoſtles men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſo much as allude, or refer to it, in any of their Epiſtles: it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, not to ſay impoſſible, that there ſhould not be ſo much as <hi>a hint</hi> given of this Creed, in all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Writings; if indeed it had been compoſed by the Apoſtles, as their Joint Work, for the Uſe of the whole Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>There are abundance of falſe Steps made, in this reaſoning of <hi>Voſſius.</hi> (1) It is evident enough, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers moſt important Matters were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, by <hi>the joint Council and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the Apoſtles and the CXX, which yet St. <hi>Luke</hi> did not think ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be inſerted, into his <hi>Hiſtory of the Preaching, Travels, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of the Apoſtles.</hi> The Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Lord's Day, inſtead of (or with) the Sabbath (or ſeventh Day) appointed by God himſelf in the 4<hi>th</hi> Commandment; the Form of Church-Government, whether you will ſay by Biſhops, or by a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or in the Independent Way; the ſolemn manner of ordaining the Church-Paſtors, by Impoſition of Hands, and Prayer made for them; the Love-Feaſts, the Holy Kiſs: all theſe, every one will confeſs, are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, not of one Apoſtle, but of the College of Apoſtles and their<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53124:11"/>Council the CXX; and yet St. <hi>Luke</hi> has not told us, either <hi>when</hi> or by
<hi>whom</hi> they were ordained, but is as ſilent of their Inſtitution by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as of their compoſing the Creed. (2) 'Tis not hard to gueſs at the Reaſon, why none of theſe (great) Matters, or the compiling the Creed, are particularly recorded in the Acts of the Apoſtles; namely, becauſe they are not bare <hi>Memoirs,</hi> or tranſient things; but ſuch as were to be <hi>kept up, and perpetuated, by Example and Practice.</hi> Every one ſees, that the Lord's Day, the Form of Church-Polity or Government, the Ordination of Church-Paſtors, the Love-Feaſts, and the Holy Kiſs, are Inſtitutions that needed not to be recorded: becauſe the conſtant and univerſal Practice of them, by the Apoſtles and the whole Church, was more effectual to preſerve them, than any Regiſter or Hiſtory would be. The like is as evident, of the Creed; it was to be <hi>orally taught</hi> to every Convert, in every Place, as <hi>the Mark of their Chriſtianity:</hi> therefore being committed to ſo many Witneſſes and Memories, it was conſidered, not as a tranſient thing (of which there was Danger that it might go into Oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if not recorded) but as laid up ſafely in the Minds and Memories of all the Faithful. Farther, 'tis an Obſervation made by all Church-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, that the Antients (of a long time) <hi>purpoſely forbore</hi> to commit the Creed to Writing; partly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not expoſe the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Religion, to the Contempt, Raileries and Oppoſition of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: partly, to oblige their own People, to be more careful to learn it exactly. To this purpoſe, they cite, among divers others, the Teſtimony of St. <hi>Jerom, Epiſt. ad Pam.</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"In the Creed, <hi>ſays St.</hi> Jerom
<hi>there,</hi> which is <hi>not written with Ink and Paper;</hi> but on the (fleſhly) Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Heart.</q> (3) It is not true, what
<hi>Voſſius</hi> adds, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles do not ſeem to allude or refer to this Creed, in any of their Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Ye have obeyed (from the Heart) the Form of ſound Doctrine, which was delivered to you.</hi> The
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Exemplar</hi> (or Form)
<hi>of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> (here) cannot be better inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, than of the common Creed.</p>
               <p>It ſeems alſo to be meant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Let him that propheſieth</hi> (or, preacheth) <hi>preach,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>according to the Analogy</hi> (or, the Rule) <hi>of Faith.</hi> The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the New Teſtament not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet written, the Chriſtian's <hi>Rule of Faith</hi> could be no other but the Creed; which (accordingly) by the moſt antient Fathers is expreſly called <hi>Regula fidei, the Rule of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Tim. 6.20. <hi>O</hi> Timothy, <hi>keep,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> (or, the thing committed to thy Truſt) <hi>and turn not aſide.</hi> The
<hi>Depoſitum</hi> or <hi>Truſt,</hi> from which <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> might not turn aſide, is (ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally and very reaſonably) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by Interpreters, to be the true Doctrine or <hi>Faith</hi> of the Goſpel: but if ſo, 'tis very probable, that the<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53124:11"/>Apoſtle intended more particularly <hi>the Rule of Faith,</hi> the Creed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by all the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Hold faſt <hi>the Form of ſound Words;</hi> which thou didſt hear of me; <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ye ought (for the time) to have been Teachers; ye have need, that one teach you again <hi>the firſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> of the Doctrines (not, <hi>the Oracles</hi>) of God;
<hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. Leaving <hi>the Principles of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt,</hi> let us go on to Perfection.</q> Here <hi>the Form of ſound Words,</hi> and <hi>the firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and again <hi>the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſo (moſt properly) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the Creed; that it was too much Boldneſs (or Inadvertence) in
<hi>Voſſius,</hi> to affirm directly, that there is no Alluſion to the Creed in all the Apoſtolick Writings: one may ſay, they not only allude, but even point to it.</p>
               <p>And what does St. <hi>Jude</hi> (ſo likely) mean, in theſe Words; <hi>Jude</hi> 3.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Earneſtly contend for <hi>the Faith, once delivered to the Saints:</hi> for there are certain Men crope in,—denying
<hi>the only God; and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q> It is highly credible, that by <hi>the Faith delivered to the Saints,</hi> he means the Creed that was given out by the Apoſtles, to all their Churches. And does he not refer to the two firſt Articles of it, in theſe Words; for certain Men are crope in, <hi>who deny the only</hi> (or one) <hi>God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Voſſius</hi> his next Argument is yet more weak; nay, perfectly ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. If this Creed, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> had been made (and ſo thought to be) by the Apoſtles; the Church would never have preſumed, to add any thing to it; and much leſs, to take ought from it.</p>
               <p>I know not what he means, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ought from it; it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that any thing has been taken from it: it is ſtill the ſame, for all that I know, or have ever read, as at firſt. But they would not have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; by this he means the Creeds of <hi>Nice,</hi> of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon:</hi> by making of which Creeds,
'tis manifeſt that divers things were added to the firſt Creed, namely the Creed of the Apoſtles. I anſwer, (1) The Fathers in theſe Councils excuſed themſelves, by pretending, their Creeds were only <hi>Explications of the antient Faith, or Creed.</hi> They profeſſed, to keep cloſe to the Old Faith; without adding any thing to it: becauſe they added not any <hi>new Articles;</hi> but only more largely and fully explained the old ones. In ſhort, they came off from this Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Voſſius;</hi> as they thought; by calling their Additions, by the Name of Explications and Declarations, not of Additions. But (2) If they had directly ſaid; that they thought fit to inlarge the Creed made by the Apoſtles, by ſome other Doctrines taken from the New Teſtament: I do not think, that this is the worſt thing, of the kind, that Mother <hi>Church</hi> ever did. 'Tis known to all<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53124:12"/>the World, that ſhe has added to, and taken away, from the Sacraments and the Scriptures: therefore 'tis, no ſuch great wonder, if alſo ſhe turned her own Doctrines into Creeds; and mingled her Articles, with the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>From the Sacrament of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſhe hath taken away the Cup; and in the ſame Sacrament has changed unleavened Bread into lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened. The Sacrament of Baptiſm ſhe hath wholly changed, turning it into the mimical Rite of <hi>ſprinkling;</hi> and alſo <hi>added</hi> the Croſs, to that (falſe) Baptiſm which ſhe admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
               <p>As for the Scriptures, all learned Criticks (even of the Trinitarian Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion) agree, that abundance of Words, and ſome whole Texts have been added. 'Tis unconteſtable, that they have added; <hi>there are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the WORD, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi> It was expreſly denied at the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice</hi> it ſelf, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs, GOD was manifeſted in the Fleſh;</hi> but, <hi>which</hi> (which My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery) was manifeſted,
<hi>by</hi> Fleſh; namely, by the Lord Chriſt, and the Apoſtles. And to omit many other (certain and yielded) Depravations of Scripture, both by adding and omitting: there are ſhrewd Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that to the Inſtitution of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, by our Saviour, in the Goſpel of St. <hi>Matthew;</hi> theſe Words have been added, <hi>In the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> It appears in the Acts, and Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles never baptized in that Form of Words, but only
<hi>in the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> But we need no more but the Teſtimony of one of their own Hiſtorians, St. <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> concerning the Fidelity of <hi>the Church</hi> (as the prevailing Party always calls it ſelf) in preſerving pure and intire the Oracles of God.
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> owns in direct terms, that the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox put out of their Bibles ſome Paſſages of Scripture, which they liked not: and the Bibles of his time, that had not been ſo uſed, this good Father (roundly) calls them, <hi>the Bibles that have not been rectified.</hi> Ancor. n. 31.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Voſſius</hi> ſaith farther, that none of the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtorians, tho they have ſet down the Creeds made in Councils, have recorded the Creed of the Apoſtles: thus <hi>Socrates</hi> and others regiſter not only the Creeds made in legitimate Councils, but even thoſe by the Arian Councils; but they have not a Word of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed. To this, I ſay, 1. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> and the Hiſtorians that follow him, begin their Hiſtories (at ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) no higher, than the Converſion of Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to the Chriſtian Faith. Therefore 'tis no wonder, that tho they record the Creeds in order, as they were compoſed by the Councils that aſſembled under Great
<hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and his Succeſſors: yet they ſay nothing of the Apoſtles Creed, which belonged to a Period<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53124:12"/>300 Years older than the times of which thoſe Hiſtorians write. 2. <hi>Voſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> has not asked; why <hi>Euſebius,</hi> the oldeſt of the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and who begins his Hiſtory from the very firſt, has not mentioned or recited the Apoſtles Creed; becauſe he foreſaw, it would be anſwered; that <hi>Euſebius</hi> was a thorow-paced Arian, a great Oppoſer of <hi>Marcellus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ancyra</hi> (againſt whom alſo he particularly wrote) who held the Doctrine that the Socinians now do; therefore perceiving that the Apoſtles Creed was as much againſt the Arians as the Homo-ouſians, and that it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favoured <hi>Marcellus,</hi> he forbore to take notice of it in his Hiſtory. I ſhall grant, that
<hi>Euſebius</hi> was a moſt learned Hiſtorian, and that we are extremely in his debt, for the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of antient Monuments and Memoirs he has left to us: but I could give, and hereafter ſhall give, divers Inſtances, of his deſigned ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing whatſoever of Antiquity, that favoured the Nazarene and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean (or as we now ſpeak, the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian) Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The laſt Argument of <hi>Voſſius,</hi> is propounded by (the preſent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous) Monſieur <hi>du Pin</hi> (in his
<hi>Eccl. Hiſt. c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 9.) in more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Terms and Manner than by <hi>Voſſius:</hi> I will therefore examine it, as Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> has offer'd it. He ſays, that 'tis an Opinion eſtabliſh'd on ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Grounds, that this Creed was made by the Apoſtles: but that they wrote, or dictated it, <hi>word for word, juſt as we now have it;</hi> he thinks is very improbable. He choſe to propound his Opinion, after this fallacious manner, that he might not be talk'd of (it may be, be cenſured by his Superiours) for maintaining <hi>in terminis</hi> an Opinion, which might be judged to be heretical. For in very deed, Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> does not only
<hi>not believe,</hi> that the Apoſtles wrote this Creed <hi>word for word,</hi> as we now have it; but he thinks, they were not Authors of it at all, in any Senſe; according to him, the Apoſtles nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made, nor deſigned to make a Creed. He ſaith indeed, that 'tis an Opinion eſtabliſh'd on very good Grounds, that the Apoſtles made this Creed; and the Propoſition he undertakes to prove, is only this, that <hi>the Apoſtles did not write this Creed word for word, juſt as we now have it:</hi> but his Arguments (which are the ſame with thoſe of <hi>Voſſius</hi>) aim at this; that the Apoſtles neither wrote, nor intended to write any Creed at all. I have already conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all his Arguments, but only the laſt; which both he and <hi>Voſſius</hi> (ſeem to) ſuppoſe, to be the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt: in truth, it is the weakeſt, as being made up of Accounts that are (too notoriouſly) falſe; it is this.</p>
               <p>If the Apoſtles had made a Creed, ſaith Mr. <hi>du Pin,</hi> it would have been found <hi>the ſame</hi> in all Churches, of all Ages: all Chriſtians would have learnt it by Heart; all Churches, and all Writers, would have repreated it, in the ſame manner and in the ſame terms. But the contrary is evident, for not only in the 2<hi>d</hi> and 3<hi>d</hi> Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53124:13"/>but in the 4<hi>th</hi> alſo there were many Creeds; and all, tho the ſame as to Doctrine, yet different in the Expreſſion. In the 2<hi>d</hi> and 3<hi>d</hi> Ages we find as many Creeds as Authors: which ſhows that there was not then any Creed that was reputed to be the Apoſtles; or even any regulated or eſtabliſh'd Form of Faith. For
<hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> exhibits one Creed, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and another, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> makes uſe of
<hi>three</hi> ſeveral Creeds, in his Books <hi>de Praeſcriptione, contra Praxeam,</hi> and <hi>de Virgin. velandis.</hi> See alſo <hi>Origen peri Archon, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Dial. contr. Marc. Ruffinus</hi> in the
4<hi>th</hi> Age, compares <hi>three</hi> antient Creeds, of <hi>Aquileia, Rome,</hi> and the Orient; none of which agree per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly with the common one, nor with one another: as will appear (ſaith he) by the Table, containing the
4 Creeds, at the End of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (in his Catechetick Lectures) gives us a particular Creed, uſed by the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when this Father wrote. The Authors alſo that have explained the Creed, as St. <hi>Auſtin, Serm.</hi>
119. St. <hi>Maximus, Chryſolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, Fortunatus,</hi> omit ſome Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are found in the Apoſtles Creed <hi>as we now have it;</hi> as <hi>the Life everlaſting:</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſays, that the Apoſtles Creed concludes with <hi>the Reſurrection of the Body;</hi> but now it concludes with the <hi>Life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi> Laſtly, he ſaith, that <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is the firſt, and only Perſon of the 5<hi>th</hi> Century, who aſſerts that the Creed was compoſed by the Apoſtles; and he propoſes his Opinion, only as a Matter that depended
<hi>on popular Tradition:</hi> the other Authors that are of this Opinion,
<hi>he ſaith,</hi> took it up on the Credit of <hi>Ruffinus;</hi> and are too late in time, to be admitted as Witneſſes in this Queſtion, about the Authors of the Creed called the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Never was there leſs Truth, in ſo many Words; I ſhall therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs very particularly, all that he hath ſaid. He ſaith; (1) If the Apoſtles had made a Creed, all <hi>Churches</hi> and all
<hi>Writers</hi> would have repeated it, in the ſame Manner and Terms. That all <hi>Churches</hi> repeated it in the ſame Terms and Manner, we affirm; nor will Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> ever prove the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. That all
<hi>Writers</hi> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it in the ſame Manner and Terms, is a childiſh Suppoſition: for ſometimes they have occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat but
<hi>part of it;</hi> ſometimes they repeat it <hi>Paraphraſtically,</hi> thereby to put on it their own Interpretation. Therefore 'tis but weakly urged by Mr. <hi>du Pin,</hi> that <hi>Ireneus</hi> gives us <hi>two</hi> Creeds,
<hi>Tertullian three, Origen</hi> yet <hi>another:</hi> for of theſe Writers,
<hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian (de Virgin. veland.)</hi> deſigned to repeat but only a part of the Creed; the ſame <hi>Tertullian (de Praeſcript. &amp; contr. Prax.)</hi> as alſo <hi>Ireneus</hi> and <hi>Origen</hi> repeat the Creed Paraphraſtically or Exegetically, that their Reader might take it in their Senſe. 'Tis to no purpoſe, that Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> urges the Creed in St.
<hi>Cyrill,</hi> uſed in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for no Body denies that after the<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53124:13"/>Council of <hi>Nice</hi> (that is, after the Year 325.) the Nicene Creed, and the Creeds made in imitation of
<hi>that,</hi> were explained in many Places to the Youth and Catechumens, inſtead of the Apoſtles Creed; that People might be infected betimes, with that Inſidelity which the Nicene Council had eſtabliſh'd and publiſh'd.</p>
               <p>But whereas he has given us a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of 4 Creeds; namely, the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, the Aquileian, that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that of the Orient: We ought to thank him, for (implicitly) gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up the Queſtion to us. The Reader is to know, that by <hi>the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> (in the Age of <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> from whom Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> takes the Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leian, Roman and Oriental Creeds) was meant the <hi>Eaſtern Part</hi> of the Roman Empire; namely, all the Provinces, that ſpoke the Greek Tongue; which is to ſay, all
<hi>Illyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> and <hi>Grecia,</hi> the Kingdoms and Provinces of
<hi>Aſia,</hi> the Provinces and Kingdoms of <hi>Syria,</hi> as far as the
<hi>Euphrates</hi> and <hi>Tigris, Egypt,</hi> the Iſlands in the
<hi>Archipelago, Adriatick</hi> and <hi>Ionian</hi> Seas; all theſe (being the better Moiety of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire) were called <hi>the Orient.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> tho ſhe was not (as ſhe now calls her ſelf)
<hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs;</hi> yet being the Patriarchal Chair of all <hi>the Weſt,</hi> ſhe was <hi>the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of the Churches of the Weſt Part of the Empire. I affirm now, that theſe two Creeds, as alſo that of
<hi>Aquileia,</hi> perfectly agree with the Vulgar; by which he means the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creed as we now have it. Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi>'s Table, which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to be exact enough, will ſhow us no Difference, but what will confirm every intelligent Reader, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out peradventure they are all but one Creed, made by the ſame Author or Joint-Authors. There is more Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as recited by <hi>Moſes</hi> at
<hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and as repeated again by the ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> at
<hi>Deut.</hi> 5. than between theſe Creeds: Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> will ſooner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a prudent Reader that the 10 Commandments in
<hi>Deuteronomy</hi> were not the Commandments ſpoke on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and recorded <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. than that the 4 Creeds in his Table are not the ſame, or came not from the ſame Hands.</p>
               <p>The whole Difference of the 4 Creeds conſiſts in theſe (unſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant) Words and Expreſſions. The Oriental Creed ſaid, I believe in <hi>one</hi> God, the Father, Almighty, <hi>Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Impaſſible.</hi> The Roman, I believe in God the Father Almighty: and the Aquileian ſaid; I believe in <hi>one</hi> God, the Father, Almighty: the preſent (or Vulgar) Creed adds, <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Roman, and Aquileian, and Preſent, ſay; And in Jeſus Chriſt his only Son our Lord: the Oriental tranſpoſes the word
<hi>only,</hi> thus; and in our <hi>only</hi> Lord Jeſus Chriſt, his Son.</p>
               <p>The Oriental, Roman and Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leian ſaid; who was born of the Holy Ghoſt and of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> the Preſent, by way of Explication; who was <hi>conceived</hi> of the Holy<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53124:14"/>Ghoſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Oriental and Roman ſaid; was crucified under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> and was buried: the Aquileian, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> buried, <hi>deſcended into Hell:</hi> the Preſent, crucified under <hi>Pontius Pilate, dead,</hi> buried, deſcended into Hell. But
<hi>deſcendit ad inferos, he deſcended to thoſe below,</hi> or as we render it <hi>into Hell,</hi> is confeſs'd on all Hands to be an accidental Addition in the Creed of <hi>Aquileia;</hi> and from that Creed was taken into the Preſent Creed, on this Occaſion. In ſome Churches it was ſaid,
<hi>was buried;</hi> in others, <hi>went to thoſe below;</hi> which (every one ſees) are equivalent Expreſſions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſignify the ſame thing: but the Church of <hi>Aquileia</hi> deſiring that her Creed ſhould be moſt full and compleat, took in both the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; tho at the ſame time (as <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who was of <hi>Aquileia,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges) ſhe meant no more by both, than other Churches by the ſingle word <hi>buried.</hi> And hence it was, that the other Churches and Copies of the Creed, which ſaid <hi>deſcended into Hell</hi> (or deſcended <hi>to thoſe below</hi>) did omit <hi>buried:</hi> and ſo, at this day, doth the Athanaſian Creed. But it was not long before this Variety of expreſſing the ſame thing, begat Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes: for by occaſion of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<hi>deſcended to thoſe below,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers began to imagine a local Deſcent of Chriſt into Hell. Some of them ſaid, to triumph over the Devil; others ſaid, to releaſe thoſe Damned who believed and repented at the ſight of him; others had ſtill other (as ungrounded) Conceits. But the Diſputes about <hi>the Reaſons</hi> of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Deſcent <hi>to thoſe below,</hi> made the Article (taken in general) to be believed; and therefore it was added at laſt to the Roman Creed, which with this and ſome other Alterations, makes the Vulgar or <hi>Preſent</hi> Creed.</p>
               <p>All the Creeds ſay; the third Day he aroſe again from the Dead.</p>
               <p>The Oriental, Roman and Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leian ſaid; he aſcended into Heaven, ſitteth on the right Hand of God, the Father: the <hi>preſent,</hi> to the word Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, adds the word <hi>Almighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They all ſaid; from thence he ſhall come, to judg the quick and the dead. The Oriental, Roman and Aquilean ſaid; And in the Holy Ghoſt: the Preſent, more explicitly, <hi>I believe</hi> in the Holy Ghoſt. The Oriental, Roman and Aquileian ſaid; I believe the Holy Church, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints: the Preſent to the word <hi>Church,</hi> adds the word
<hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> or Univerſal.</p>
               <p>All the Creeds ſaid; the Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sins.</p>
               <p>In like manner, they all ſaid; the Reſurrection of the Body; ſaving that the Aquileian ſaid, of <hi>this</hi> Body.</p>
               <p>The Preſent concludes with <hi>the Life everlaſting:</hi> the other <hi>three</hi> mention not the Life everlaſting; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſuppoſed and included in the foregoing Article, <hi>the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay now, let any one read the ten Commandments at
<hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and compare them with the ſame ten<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53124:14"/>Commandments at <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. and he will perceive, that he may better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them to be the ſame Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than that theſe four
<hi>various Copies</hi> are Copies of the ſame Creed. The Variations of the 4 Copies are ſo inconſiderable, the Cauſes of that Variation ſo obvious and evident, that he that will call them, not <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Readings</hi> of the ſame Creed, but 4 ſeveral Creeds proceeding from ſo many ſeveral Compilers, in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ought (if obſtinate in his Error) to take Phyſick. But if theſe are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>various Readings of the ſame Creed,</hi> without doubt we have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Point, that the Apoſtles were the Authors of it. For I deſire to know, how it was (morally) poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt;</hi> which is to ſay, all the Churches of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> ſhould in all Kingdoms, Provinces and Epiſcopates, happen to have the very ſame Creed, both for <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of Articles, and <hi>Manner of Expreſſion;</hi> if they did not receive it from the very ſame Perſons, from whom they received the Goſpel and the Scriptures, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Apoſtles and other firſt Miſſionaries and Preachers of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Doctrine? It is granted to us, that there had been no General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, when this Creed (as we have made it appear) was the <hi>common</hi> and <hi>only</hi> Creed both of the Weſt and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: therefore when all the Fathers (without excepting any) <hi>that ſpeak of this Creed,</hi> tell us, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>ex traditione Majorum (by Tradition of their Predeceſſors)</hi> that this Creed was made by the Apoſtles; they give us ſuch an Account as juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and proves its own Truth; for no other Cauſe can be thought of, how it ſhould become
<hi>the common and only Creed</hi> of Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="2">(2) Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> ſaith; <hi>Ruffinus</hi> (in the
5<hi>th</hi> Century) is the firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who aſſerts that this Creed was compoſed by the Apoſtles; and that too <hi>from popular Tradition:</hi> indeed a great many other Fathers ſay the ſame thing; but they all had it from <hi>Ruffinus.</hi> Firſt, Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> reckons <hi>Ruffinus</hi> to the 5<hi>th</hi> Century; only to leſſen his Authority and Credit in this Queſtion: for it is certain, (and acknowledged by Dr. <hi>Cave,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi>) that <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> flouriſh'd at
<hi>Aquileia</hi> in the Year 360. at which Time and Place he had a great Friendſhip and Intimacy with St. <hi>Jerom.</hi> It is true, becauſe he lived to be old, he ſaw the Year of Chriſt 410 or 411. and from hence Mr.
<hi>du Pin</hi> has taken occaſion, to call him a Father of the 5<hi>th</hi> Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury. <hi>Ruffinus</hi> being the firſt of the Fathers, that ever wrote an Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Creed; I mean, the firſt <hi>of thoſe now extant:</hi> 'tis no wonder that he is alſo the firſt that expreſly informs us, who were the Authors of it; tho if he had not told us, who were the Compilers, the Univerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Antiquity of it, are alone ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to declare the Authors and Compilers. Nor does he ſay, that he had learned who were the Framers of the Creed, <hi>by popular Report;</hi> but <hi>tradunt rajores noſtri,</hi> our Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53124:15"/>(in the ſacred Function) have ſo delivered to us. Which is not to be underſtood neither, of bare <hi>oral Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> by the preceding Biſhops and Presbyters; but of the antient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters who had commented on the Creed, who (be ſaith) were very many. None of them are come down to our Times; but of the Number was <hi>Photinus,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Sirmium</hi> and Metropolitan of <hi>Illy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum,</hi> who held as the Socinians now do, that the Lord Chriſt was a Prophet, not God. Whereas Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> adds, that all the other Fathers (whom he confeſſes to be very many, he ſhould have ſaid,
<hi>All that mention this Creed</hi>) took it on the Credit of
<hi>Ruffinus,</hi> that the Apoſtles were the Compilers of it: it is raſhly ſaid, None of them quote <hi>Ruffinus</hi> for their Author; and divers of them (parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) alledg (as <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> does) Tradition for their Ground; which, as I ſaid before, was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> but <hi>the Tradition of the antient Commentators.</hi> And when this Critick urges, in the laſt Place, that St. <hi>Auſtin, Maximus,</hi> and ſome others, who have expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Creed after
<hi>Ruffinus,</hi> omit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Words, nay and Expreſſions, that are found in the Creed <hi>as we now</hi> have it; why has he concealed, that the Words or Expreſſions omitted by theſe Expoſitors, are only ſuch, as they ſuppoſed to be included in other equivalent Expreſſions of the Creed? Tho it might alſo ſometimes happen, that they did not intend, to explain
<hi>the whole</hi> Creed. <hi>verbatim,</hi> but only the principal Words and Articles; namely, ſuch as either were contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by Hereticks, particularly by the Ghoſticks and Manichees, or were miſunderſtood by Heretical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. His Inſtance of <hi>the Life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> omitted by Expoſitors, will do him no Service: for 'tis not <hi>an Article</hi> (no more than <hi>dead,</hi> or <hi>gone to thoſe below</hi> are Articles) but only an Illuſtration or fuller Explication of the Article foregoing, <hi>the Reſurrection of the Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the Arguments of theſe two very learned Criticks (I willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledg them to be ſuch) <hi>Voſſius</hi> and Monſieur
<hi>du Pin,</hi> againſt the Apoſtles Creed: I have (I think) not only fully ſatisfied them; but at the ſame time defended our Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for it, againſt their Evaſions. For whereas to our Argument, from the Teſtimony of <hi>all the Fathers who have ever ſpoke of this Creed;</hi> and eſpecially of <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> a moſt learned and judicious Father, equalled by Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> to St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> they reply, that
<hi>Ruffinus</hi> was but of the 5<hi>th</hi> Age, and ſpoke only from popular Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and that all the other Fathers took it from him: I have ſhown, that theſe are partly untrue, partly raſh and ungrounded Affirmations. And whereas to what we alledg from the (confeſs'd) Antiquity, and the Univerſality of this Creed; they anſwer, the Creeds of the
<hi>Orient</hi> and Weſt were different: I have evinced, that the (pretended) Differences are apparently only <hi>the various Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of one and the ſame Creed;<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53124:15"/>the very Commandments are (much) more differently related by <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, than the Apoſtolick Creed by the Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of St. <hi>Clemens.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF the Monuments and Remains of the Apoſtolick Age, next to the Apoſtles Creed, is the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians. This is that <hi>Clemens,</hi> of whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes reſpectful Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. He has written an Epiſtle, in the Name and by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Church of
<hi>Corinth.</hi> All the Criticks on the Fathers, when they ſpeak of this Epiſtle, without an Eye to the Trinitarian Controverſies, own, not only that 'tis unqueſtionably genuine, but that 'tis a moſt pious, moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and an elegant Compoſition: Mr. <hi>du Pin</hi> very truly adds;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"One may diſcern in this Writer, a great deal of Energy and Vigor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with much Prudence, Gentleneſs, Zeal and Charity.</q> But when they conſider the Doctrine of it, with regard to the Trinity, and the Perſon of our Saviour, the ableſt and antienteſt (and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great <hi>Photius,</hi> the moſt judicious Cenſor of the Fathers, and himſelf a Father) cannot mention it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tears in their Eyes. Beſides <hi>Photius, Petavius</hi> and <hi>Huetius</hi> (fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous modern Criticks) ſigh it out, that <hi>Clemens was an undoubted <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian;</hi> and the occaſion of this Judgment is, becauſe of the low and merely humane Characters, which (throughout this Epiſtle, even where he affects to ſpeak of our Saviour in the higheſt manner) he gives of our Saviour's Perſon and Dignity. But I ſhall be more particular, than they have been, in referring to the Paſſages of this Epiſtle; which have ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Trinitarian Criticks.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he always diſtinguiſhes the Lord Chriſt from God; and often <hi>ſo</hi> diſtinguiſhes him, that it amounts to a flat and direct Denial, that he is God.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> ch. 42. have preached to us, from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and the Lord Chriſt from God. The Lord Chriſt then, according to St. <hi>Clement,</hi> was not himſelf God; but
<hi>one that has preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us from God, as the Apoſtles preached from Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>chap.</hi> 58. he hath theſe (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding) Words;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"God the Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of all things, the Father of Spirits, the Lord of all Fleſh; <hi>who hath choſen our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and us by him;</hi> grant to you Peace, Long-ſuffering, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, through <hi>our High Prieſt and Protector</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>by whom</hi> be Glory, and Honour, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty unto God, now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</q> What a Socinian Account<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53124:16"/>is here, of our Saviour? He is, ſaith St. <hi>Clement, the choſen of God, as we alſo are;</hi> our <hi>High Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,</hi> by his effectual Prayers and Interceſſion for us: and let Honour, Glory and Majeſty, be
<hi>given to God, by him,</hi> now and for ever. Did he think the Perſon, of whom he ſo ſpeaks, was himſelf God?</p>
               <p>But when he intends to ſay a very high thing, of our Saviour; he calls him (at <hi>ch.</hi> 16.) <hi>the Scepter of the Majeſty of God.</hi> He alludes here to the Scepter of King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> which he ſtretched out to Queen <hi>Eſther,</hi> in token of his Acceptance and Favour. The Lord Chriſt therefore, in the Doctrine of this Father, differs juſt ſo from God; as the Enſigns and Marks of Power and Majeſty, differ from that Majeſty and Power of which they are only the Marks and Signs.</p>
               <p>But beſides theſe diminutive Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and abſolutely inconſiſtent with our Saviour's being God; I obſerve, that when he endeavours moſt of all (at <hi>ch.</hi> 36.) to extol the real Greatneſs of our Saviour, he minds the Corinthians, that by him our Hearts and Underſtandings are inlightned and opened; meaning, <hi>by his Doctrine and Goſpel;</hi> and that <hi>he is exalted above the Angels:</hi> to which purpoſe he cites divers Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> But tho he there goes over that whole Chapter, for the higheſt Epithets he might give to our Saviour, he omits the
8<hi>th,</hi> 9<hi>th,</hi> 10<hi>th,</hi> 11<hi>th</hi> and 12<hi>th</hi> Verſes; in which the Title <hi>God</hi> is beſtowed on him, and <hi>the Creation of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Earth</hi> is (thought at leaſt to be) aſcribed to him. This makes me doubt, that thoſe Verſes were not originally in that Epiſtle; but have been ſince added. St. <hi>Clement</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours there, to aſcribe to our Saviour all the moſt glorious Prerogatives and Pre-eminencies, that (with Truth) he could; he himſelf ſaith divers magnificent things of him: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins alſo at the firſt Verſes of that firſt Chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> goes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole Chapter, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with the laſt Verſes of it; and yet neither calls him <hi>God,</hi> nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes to him <hi>the Creation of Heaven and Earth;</hi> nay, of that whole Chapter he omits only thoſe five Verſes which ſo ſpeak of him, tho they were moſt of all to <hi>Clement</hi>'s Deſign and Aim. It is true, that in thoſe Verſes our Saviour is called
<hi>God</hi> in no other Senſe, than <hi>Solomon</hi> was ſo called; for the Author uſes the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Words that the Pſalmiſt had uſed of
<hi>Solomon;</hi> and the Heavens and Earth there meant, are only <hi>the New Heavens and Earth</hi> foretold by the Prophets, even the Goſpel-Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and State: yet theſe Characters of our Saviour are ſo noble, were ſo highly to <hi>Clement</hi>'s Purpoſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and it was ſo impoſſible for him (who went thorow the whole Chapter) to overlook them, that I cannot believe theſe Verſes were <hi>then</hi> a part of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> but (as many other Paſſages, both in the Goſpels and Epiſtles) have been fraudulently added. Or it may
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53124:16"/>be, they were at firſt a marginal Note, by ſome Copier; and being taken by ſucceeding Copiers as Words that had been overſeen, and not as a Note or Annotation, were by them put into the Text it ſelf of the Epiſtle. This Corruption might the more eaſily happen, without being oppoſed by any; becauſe it was a long time (near, if not full 400 Years) before this Epiſtle was owned as a genuine part of Scripture, any where in the Weſt, or in many Churches of the Orient. That which makes this Conjecture (that theſe Verſes have been added to the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the
<hi>Hebrews</hi>) ſtill more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is, that thoſe Antients who owned this Epiſtle as written by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaid, it was originally wrote by him in the Hebrew Tongue, and tranſlated into Greek (as we now have it) by St. <hi>Clement, Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Theophylact. Com. in C.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt. ad Hebr.</hi> But if ſo; how can we think, that
<hi>Clement</hi> ſhould omit what was moſt for his Deſign, in an Epiſtle which himſelf had tranſlated, and therefore was perfectly acquainted with it; and in a Chapter too, out of which he had cited ſo many Paſſages, that were much leſs to his purpoſe? The ſhort is, St.
<hi>Clement</hi> deſcribes our Saviour, as the High Prieſt of the Prieſts of the New Teſtament: and when he had the fitteſt Occaſion, and the greateſt Opportunity, from an Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which himſelf had tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Greek, to call our Saviour <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Creator,</hi> he calls him nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but only our High Prieſt, as St.
<hi>Paul</hi> does throughout that Epiſtle. From whence, I ſay, we have theſe 2 (very probable) Conſectaries; that neither did St. <hi>Clement</hi> think our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to be <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Creator,</hi> in any Senſe of thoſe Words; nor were thoſe 5 Verſes of that Epiſtle of St.
<hi>Paul,</hi> wherein Chriſt is ſo ſtiled, originally in that Epiſtle, but have been ſince added.</p>
               <p>And hitherto of the Judgment of St. <hi>Clement.</hi> For tho ſomething might be added out of a ſecond Epiſtle, which alſo bears the Name of St. <hi>Clement,</hi> I ſhall omit it; partly, becauſe the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is rejected as counterfeit, by the moſt Learned of the Antients,
<hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> and <hi>Photius:</hi> partly becauſe the Meanneſs of the Stile, the Drineſs and Flatneſs of the Thoughts, and the Inelegance of the Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, moſt plainly diſcover, that it was none of St. <hi>Clement</hi>'s. <hi>Euſebius</hi> adds, that the Antients never alledg or cite the (pretended) ſecond Epiſtle of
<hi>Clement. Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</p>
               <p>As to what Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> quotes out of the firſt Epiſtle, and indeavours to improve by paraphraſing (that is, <hi>by wreſting</hi>) it; 'tis ſo trivial, as well as ſo remote, that I ſhall truſt the Judgment of any (the meaneſt) Reader with it: but out of the
2<hi>d</hi> (counterfeit) Epiſtle, he has abuſed his Reader with a broken Citation, which may ſeem to his purpoſe, when indeed it is not. The Words are theſe, being the very firſt Words of the Epiſtle;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"We ought (Brethren) to think of Chriſt, as of God.</q> It was knaviſhly done, to omit <hi>the next</hi> 
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53124:17"/>Words, which were deſigned by the Author, to explain theſe:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"We ought, <hi>ſays this Pſeudo-Clemens,</hi> to think of Chriſt as of God; as the Judg both of the Dead and Living.</q> His Meaning therefore was; We ought (Brethren) to think of Chriſt, as we do of God; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he alſo is our Judg. He himſelf has taught us, that <hi>God hath committed to him all Judgment,</hi> John 5.22. And why; becauſe he is God? No, but becauſe he is Man: for ſo himſelf adds in that very Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text; <hi>God hath given to him to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Judgment, becauſe he is the Son of Man,</hi> John 5.27.</p>
               <p>Out of the 9<hi>th</hi> Chapter of the ſame Impoſture, Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> alledges; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt being firſt a Spirit, was made Fleſh.</hi> He ſhould not have left out the following Words; <hi>ſo alſo ſhall we, in the Fleſh, receive our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> In both the Expreſſions he ſeems to deſign, that the Souls of Men being firſt created, are afterwards infuſed into Bodies. They are not <hi>the Harmony of the Body,</hi> nor <hi>derived ex traduce;</hi> but firſt really made and exiſtent, and then incarnated by the Divine Power. But it is Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi>'s conſtant Method, to omit what goes before or after; by which his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Intention may be cleared: or to feign (by occaſion of ſome ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous preceding Paſſage) an Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was never in the Author's Mind; and by ſuch (pretended) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to interpret the Places, either alledged by him, or objected to him. In ſhort, his Reader can never rely upon his Quotations; but then leaſt of all, when he falls to explaining or paraphraſing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Nazarens, Ebionites, Mineans.</head>
               <p>LET us now proceed to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens, Mineans, Ebionites, and Alogians: concerning the former of which, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> grants, that if the Nazarens (or Mineans) were indeed Unitarians, if theſe held that the Lord Chriſt was a Man only; the Queſtion is at an end. He yields, that the Nazarens being the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judea,</hi> who were converted by the Lord Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and flouriſhed there under a Succeſſion of 15 Biſhops, whereof the firſt was St.
<hi>James</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord: if theſe believed, that Chriſt was a Man only, it will certainly follow, that the Article con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Saviour's Divinity can be no longer defended. <hi>Judic. Eccl. p.</hi> 42.</p>
               <p>I do not thank him, for this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; for who ſees not, that if the Churches of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judea,</hi> planted by the Apoſtles, and which indured in a moſt flouriſhing Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (under 15 ſucceſſive Hebrew Biſhops) to the times of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<hi>Adrian,</hi> were Unitarians; then<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53124:17"/>is the Unitarian Belief concerning our Saviour, inconteſtably true, and the certain Doctrine of the Apoſtles? But before I argue this Point, it will not be unprofitable to the Reader, who is not verſed much in theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, if I give a ſhort Account of the Occaſion and Reaſon of theſe Names, <hi>Nazaren, Minean, Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The followers of the Doctrine of Jeſus, were firſt called
<hi>Chriſtians</hi> at <hi>Antioch;</hi> a City of <hi>Syria,</hi> out of the Bounds of <hi>Judea:</hi> but in <hi>Judea</hi> it ſelf, they were (from the firſt) called <hi>Nazarens</hi> and <hi>Mineans. Nazarens,</hi> from
<hi>Nazareth,</hi> the Place of our Saviour's Education: <hi>Mineans,</hi> from an Hebrew Word which ſignifies <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks. Tertullus,</hi> when he accuſed <hi>Paul</hi> before <hi>Felix,</hi> makes this to be his Fault; that he was <hi>a Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazarens,</hi> Acts 24.5. To the other Name <hi>Minean</hi> or Heretick, St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf refers, in his Defence againſt the ſame <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus;</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"This I confeſs, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> that after the way which they call <hi>Hereſy,</hi> ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers:</q> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14. Theſe two Names, <hi>Nazaren</hi> and
<hi>Minean,</hi> are indifferently uſed by the Fathers in the following Ages, that is, they were applied to the ſame Perſons and Sect: ſo we learn from St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> writing to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in theſe Words;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"There is to this day over <hi>all the Orient,</hi> a Jewiſh Sect, who are called <hi>Mineans;</hi> and by the Vulgar, <hi>Nazarens;</hi> who believe in Chriſt, the Son of God.</q> St.
<hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in the Account he gives of this Sect, ſays, <hi>the Nazarens and Cerinthians began at the ſame time,</hi> and that <hi>all Chriſtians were at firſt called Nazarens. Epiph. Haereſ. Naz. c.</hi> 1. What he ſays farther of them, ſhall be alledged in its proper Place: in the mean time, theſe Teſtimonies (which no Man controverts) are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſhow, what was the Cauſe of this Name, and how antient it is; and that the Sect thereby intended, not only indured, but overſpread <hi>the Orient,</hi> at what time St. <hi>Jerom</hi> wrote to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which was about the Year 416. What is meant by <hi>the Orient,</hi> was declared before, when I treated of the Creed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ebionites</hi> is another Name of the antient Unitarians, and firſt (genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine) Chriſtians; tho not without a Mixture [if their Adverſaries (after having deſtroyed all their Writings and Defences) may be accepted as Witneſſes againſt them] of very bad People among them. It is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, whether they have been thus named from one <hi>Ebion,</hi> a particular Man; or from <hi>the poor</hi> and low O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion they had of our Saviour's Perſon, owning him indeed to be the Chriſt, but <hi>the Son of</hi> Joſeph <hi>and</hi> Mary: Some of the Antients affirm the one, ſome the other of theſe. Nor is the Matter worth diſputing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are (by all) granted to have been Contemporaries with the Apoſtles; and that they held the Lord Chriſt was a Man only, the Chriſt, the Son of
<hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by Generation,</hi> the Son of God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53124:18"/>
                  <hi>by Holineſs, Adoption and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Queſtion now, between Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> and us, is, not concerning the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> for he and all others grant, that the Ebionites held concerning our Saviour, that he was a mere Man; but concerning the Nazarens and Mineans; namely, whether the Nazarens and Mineans ſuppoſed, the Lord Chriſt was a Divine Perſon, and God; or only a Man, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the true <hi>Meſſias</hi> or Chriſt, the Son of God (not only by Holineſs, Adoption and Exaltation, as the other Ebionites ſaid) but by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Generation (in the Womb of <hi>Mary</hi>) by the Spirit or Power of God? We affirm the latter of theſe; but not altogether confounding the Mineans and Nazarens, with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionites. For tho they were both of them Jews, or Proſelytes of the Jews, yet there was this Difference between the Ebionites and the Nazarens; that the former believed the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> by Nature, the Son of God by Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Exaltation and Holineſs; but the Nazarens ſaid, he was the Son of God alſo by his miraculous Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being conceived by the Spirit or Power of God, and born of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> who had never known any Man. But this alſo is to be noted, that tho the Nazarens held our Saviour's mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Conception, by the Spirit of God; and the Ebionites contended, that he was the Son of only <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary:</hi> yet becauſe they both agreed in theſe two main Points, that Jeſus Chriſt was a Man only, and that the Law (by <hi>Moſes</hi>) ought to be obſerved by all Jewiſh Chriſtians (not by the Gentile Chriſtians) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Goſpel; therefore the Vulgar, and even thoſe Learned Writers (of the Catholick Party) who conſider'd them only in what they agreed, namely, that the Lord Chriſt is not God, but Man only, called both of them Ebionites; as we ſhall preſently ſee.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is a very litigious Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; it will therefore be expedient, for the prevention of a great many Eluſions and Subtleties, to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in the firſt place, what he grants to us concerning the propoſed Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>What the Nazarens held con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Saviour's Perſon?</hi> What Authorities has he owned; and how far has he yielded this Queſtion: in the yielding of which, he profeſſes, that the Socinians have carried this whole Controverſy concerning the Quality of our Saviour's Perſon? for it can be diſputed no longer, he ſaith, whether our Saviour was a Man only, if the Nazaren Chriſtians were of that Belief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He grants,</hi> that <hi>Origen</hi> aſſures us,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"That the Jews who believe in Chriſt, obſerve the Moſaick Law together with the Goſpel: and that <hi>all Jews who own Jeſus to be the Chriſt, are called Ebionites.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Orig. contr. Celſ. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 56. I wiſh, inſtead of his wondring at this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given by <hi>Origen,</hi> he had been ſo ſincere, as to let the Reader know, that <hi>Origen</hi> having lived long in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:53124:18"/>nay in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> which is to ſay, in the very midſt of the Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren or Jewiſh Churches, could not but know their true State and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He ſaith, <hi>all the Jews that are Chriſtians, are called Ebionites:</hi> and does not he (and with him, all the Antients) every where tell us, that the Ebionites were all of them Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; nay were called Ebionites, from their <hi>poor</hi> and low Opinion of our Saviour, that he was a Man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not God? Let Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> produce any of the Fathers, who have ever named the Ebionites, who do not alſo (explicitly) confeſs, that they believed our Saviour to be a Man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. In ſhort, the Nazarens are grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all (and by Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar) to be thoſe Chriſtian Jews, that were gathered into Churches in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> and
<hi>Paleſtine,</hi> by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Apoſtles themſelves:
<hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> (who lived among them) wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that all Jews who were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, were named <hi>Ebionites</hi> or <hi>the poor ones,</hi> partly from the <hi>poor Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> they had of our Saviour's Perſon, partly becauſe they adhered ſtill to the <hi>beggarly Principles</hi> and Rites of the Moſaick Law: it unavoidably fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that the Nazarens were Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites in this Senſe; that they held the Lord Chriſt was a Man only, and obſerved the Law together with the Goſpel. I ſaid, Ebionites <hi>in this Senſe;</hi> becauſe, as was noted before, the Ebionites, more
<hi>ſtrictly ſo called,</hi> believed our Saviour was the Son of
<hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary:</hi> but the Nazarens, tho they believed he was a Man only, yet they held he was miraculouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Womb of
<hi>Mary,</hi> by the ſole Power and Energy of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Concurrence of any Man.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Origen</hi> makes no Diſtinction of the Ebionites, into Ebionites and Nazarens; becauſe of their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the main Points, that
<hi>the Lord Chriſt was a Man only,</hi> and that <hi>the Moſaick Law muſt be obſerved by all Jewiſh Chriſtians:</hi> no more does
<hi>Euſebius,</hi> who contents himſelf to obſerve, that <hi>ſome Ebionites hold the miraculous Conception;</hi> others of them ſay, <hi>he was the Son of</hi> Joſeph <hi>and</hi> Mary. <hi>Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 3.
<hi>c.</hi> 27. But neither he nor <hi>Origen</hi> charge ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, as
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> in after Ages (from no Author) does; that they owned of the Old Teſtament, only the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> not the Prophets: or that they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniated St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and rejected his Epiſtles; publiſhing alſo certain <hi>Acts of St.</hi> Paul, wherein they charge him as an Apoſtate from the Law, only becauſe he could not obtain for his Wiſe a Prieſt's Daughter. <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> imputes this, not to the Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren-Ebionites, but to thoſe Ebionites who held our Saviour was the Son of only <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary:</hi> but as I ſaid, he quotes no Author; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this ſeems to be one of the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Tales which contending Sects and Parties frequently raiſe upon one another. So in after-times, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigenſes, Waldenſes, and Wiclevites, were charged with monſtrous Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, which they not only abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but are refuted by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53124:19"/>Hiſtorians, out of the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms, Sermons, and other Books of thoſe early Reformers. They were charged with teaching, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is above God; that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was Chriſt's Concubine, and taken with him in Adultery; with other more horrid and fooliſh things, not fit to be named: but the Proteſtant Hiſtorians have evinced, to the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction even of all learned and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Papiſts, out of the Books and Catechiſms of thoſe pious Men; that theſe are diabolical Calumnies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by their Perſecutors the Friars.</p>
               <p>Farther, <hi>Dr.</hi> Bull <hi>grants,</hi> that
<hi>Theodoret</hi> (<hi>Haeret. Fab. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.) affirms expreſly, that <hi>the Nazarens honour the Lord Chriſt, only as a holy Man,</hi> not as God or a Divine Perſon. Becauſe this Father alſo lived in <hi>Syria,</hi> was a moſt learned and inquiſitive Perſon, and writeth in that Work (before-quoted) of all Hereticks and their Opinions; we may (ſurely) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the Account he gives. 'Twas impoſſible that
<hi>Theodoret,</hi> whoſe Biſhoprick was <hi>in Syriâ cavâ,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts the Nazarens and Mineans then moſt abounded; and whoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Deſign it was (in that Book which we alledg) to ſet down the peculiar Opinions of all the Diſtinctions and Denominations of Chriſtians: I ſay, 'tis impoſſible he ſhould not certainly know the Doctrine of the Nazarens, the moſt famous as well as moſt anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of all thoſe Denominations which diſſented from <hi>the Church</hi> (or
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Party</hi>) of thoſe Times. And whereas Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> excepts, that <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> is a later Father than ſome he quotes; 'tis a mere and a wretched Subterfuge. Firſt, becauſe St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> (before cited) witneſſes, that <hi>then</hi> the Nazarens flouriſh'd over all the Orient; and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> that they abounded chiefly in
<hi>Paleſtine</hi> and <hi>Syriâ cavâ.</hi> Secondly, becauſe in very Deed <hi>Theodoret</hi> was contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary with <hi>Sulpitius Severus,</hi> who is (as we ſhall ſee) Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s only Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, the only Father who ever miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took the Nazaren Doctrine concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Saviour: and the Occaſion of his Miſtake was, that he lived ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from them; they in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, he in the Weſt, that is to ſay, at about
2000 Miles diſtance. <hi>Sulpitius</hi> began to write (at ſooneſt) about the Year 401. <hi>Theodoret</hi> was made Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in 420. ſo
<hi>Theodoret</hi> might be the older Man. But however that be, one lived in
<hi>Syria</hi> among the Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Churches; the other in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt Parts of <hi>Gaul,</hi> diſtant from the Nazarens the whole length of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire, when in its greateſt Extent; and therefore 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if he miſtook the Nazaren Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He grants,</hi> again; that <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> (<hi>Haereſ.</hi> 30. <hi>c.</hi> 2.) informs us, <hi>Cerinthianis &amp; Nazaraeis fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Cerinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Nazarens had like Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> and (<hi>Haereſ.</hi> 30. <hi>c.</hi> 2.)
<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaraeos &amp; Ebionaeos capita ſimul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuliſſe, ſuamque nequitiam invicem communicaſſe, i. e.</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Nazarens and Ebionites laid Heads together, and communicated their Impiety</q>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:53124:19"/>(by which
<hi>Epiphanius,</hi> without doubt, means their <hi>Hereſy</hi>)
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"one with another.</q> Laſtly, that
<hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> doubts only of this; whether in this the Nazarens agreed with the Cerinthians, that the Lord Chriſt was <hi>a common and ordinary Man,</hi> or was miraculouſly generated by the Holy Spirit (or Power of God) in the Womb of <hi>Mary.</hi> Let us put this together; <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſays, the Nazarens and Cerinthians had like Opinions: but did the former be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (as the other did) that the Lord Chriſt was <hi>a common Man,</hi> born (as all other Men are) of a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Father and Mother; or did they grant, that he was a Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but <hi>miraculouſly conceived</hi> by the Divine Power, in the Womb of a Virgin? <hi>Epiphanius</hi> profeſſes, that he cannot, upon his own Knowledg, charge the Nazarens with the former of theſe Opinions. Farther, he owns, that the Ebionites and Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens were extremely gratious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, and communicated in the ſame Impiety; that is, Hereſy.</p>
               <p>Theſe Teſtimonies do ſtagger Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> ſo that at laſt (<hi>Judic. Eccl. p.</hi> 56, 57.) he is willing to grant, that at length <hi>ſome Nazarens</hi> were infected with the Ebionite Hereſy, that the Lord Chriſt is a Man only: and of theſe Nazarens (whom he calls <hi>the latter Nazarens,</hi> tho the Antients never make any ſuch Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as the former and latter Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens) he thinks, <hi>Origen</hi> is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtood, when he ſays, as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoted, that <hi>the Jewiſh Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Nazarens) <hi>are Ebio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nites.</hi> There never was a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious Paragraph, unleſs the Man wilfully prevaricates. For firſt, why doth he ſay, <hi>ſome Nazarens</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Ebionite Hereſy, when <hi>Origen</hi> (who is his Author) expreſly ſays, <hi>all the Jewiſh Chriſtians are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionites?</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſays <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; i. e. <hi>the Jews, that own Jeſus to be the Chriſt, are Ebionites. Contr. Celſ. l.</hi> 2.
<hi>p.</hi> 56. Secondly, I deſire to know of Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> how
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> could more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually declare the Doctrine of the Nazarens concerning the Quality of our Saviour's Perſon, than by ſaying,
<hi>they hold as the Cerinthians do;</hi> and they <hi>mutually communicate their He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy with the Ebionites.</hi> For was it ever made a Queſtion, or dares he queſtion it, that the Cerinthians and Ebionites held, the Lord Chriſt was a Man only? 'Tis a ridiculous Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge, when he pretends, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens might at firſt hold the Divinity of our Saviour, but afterwards (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what before <hi>Origen</hi>'s time) ſell off to the Cerinthian and Ebionite Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. For I requeſt him, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce but the leaſt Intimation from any Father or Hiſtorian, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens changed their Opinion, by falling off from the Trinitarians to the Unitarians, as he pretends they did:
'tis a mere ſhift, to which he was forced, by the Clearneſs of the Teſtimonies given by <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:53124:20"/>But I ſhall mind him of other Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, that the Nazarens were Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians; or held but one Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that our Saviour was a Man only. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> (<hi>Haereſ. Naz. c.</hi> 7.) ſays; <hi>Nazaraei à Judaeis nullâ in re diſſentiunt, niſi quod in Chriſtum cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt: i. e.</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Jews and Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens differ in nothing, ſaving that the latter believe in Chriſt.</q> But if the Nazaren Chriſtians had held <hi>more than one Divine Perſon,</hi> or that <hi>the Meſſias or Chriſt was to be God;</hi> they had differed from the Jews, in two the higheſt Points of all: for all Men know and own, that the Jews believed but one Divine Perſon; and Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> himſelf has largely proved, (out of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>) that the Jews expected, that the Meſſias (or Chriſt) ſhould be a Man only, not God. To the Teſtimony of <hi>Juſtin,</hi> he might have added <hi>Origen contr. Celſ. l.</hi> 2.
<hi>p.</hi> 79. &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 162.</p>
               <p>Farthermore, when <hi>Epiphanius</hi> (in the Chapter before-quoted) makes doubt, whether the Nazarens held that the Lord Chriſt was <hi>the Son of</hi> Joſeph <hi>and</hi> Mary, or was miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly
<hi>generated by the Holy Spirit in the Womb of</hi> Mary: who ſees not, that he took it for granted and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that they denied he was God or a Divine Perſon; if he had not firſt ſuppoſed <hi>that,</hi> he could never have made it a Queſtion, whether they did not think he was the Son of only
<hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary?</hi> Becauſe he know, that the Nazarens believed the Lord Chriſt was only a Man; therefore he queſtions, and otherwiſe could not queſtion; whether they held, he was the Son of
<hi>Mary</hi> by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> or of <hi>Mary</hi> by the Holy Spirit?</p>
               <p>To add now no more, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> (<hi>contr. Creſc. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 31.) ſays; <hi>Et nunc ſunt quidam Haeretici, qui ſe Nazaraeos vocant; à nonnullis tamen Symmachiani appellantur,</hi> i. e.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"There are now certain Hereticks, by themſelves called Nazarens; but by divers they are named Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians.</q> To know therefore what the Nazarens held, we need only to inquire, what
<hi>Symmachus</hi> held. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> will anſwer; <hi>Symmachus</hi> was an Ebionite, and maintained Chriſt to be the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and
<hi>Mary. Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 17. But here we are to note two things. Firſt, the Nazarens did not hold, that the Lord Chriſt was the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> but the Son of God, by miraculous Conception in the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> But <hi>divers</hi> (as St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> has cautiouſly worded it) were not ſo critical, or ſo well verſed in the Knowledg of Sects, as to mind or underſtand the ſeveral Subdiviſions of them: therefore becauſe the Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens were ſo far Ebionites and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machians, that they held the Lord Chriſt was <hi>a Man only,</hi> tho generated not by <hi>Joſeph</hi> but by the Power of God in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> they called them Ebionites and Symmachians, tho both theſe (the Symmachians and Ebionites) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed that Chriſt was <hi>but a Man,</hi> but that he was the Son of
<hi>Joſeph</hi> by <hi>his Wife</hi> Mary, not of God <hi>by the Virgin</hi> Mary. Secondly, <hi>Symmachus</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:53124:20"/>and the Ebionites, as they held our Saviour to be the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> ſo they contended, that the firſt Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel was added by the Greek Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator. St. <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in Hebrew; when it was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Greek, the Tranſlator pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced it with a Genealogy, and a Narration that our Saviour was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Holy Spirit of God, and was not the Son of <hi>Joſeph:</hi> but this Genealogy and Narration, ſaid <hi>Symmachus</hi> and the Ebionites, is not in the Hebrew Goſpel of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> nay is the mere Invention of the Tranſlator. As for the other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels, the Ebionites and <hi>Symmachus</hi> did not receive the Goſpel of St. <hi>Luke:</hi> and for that of St.
<hi>John,</hi> they ſaid it was indeed written by <hi>Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus,</hi> to confirm his (Platonick) Conceits about the <hi>Logos</hi> or <hi>WORD;</hi> which he ſuppoſed to be <hi>the Chriſt,</hi> or Spirit of God that reſted on, and inhabited the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us now, for the Eaſe of the Reader, ſum up this whole Evidence concerning the Nazarens, in ſhort Paragraphs. All grant, they were the Jewiſh Chriſtians, whoſe firſt Churches were gathered by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles themſelves in <hi>Judea, Jeruſalem, Paleſtine, Syria, Arabia,</hi> and the whole Orient. The Queſtion is, what they held concerning Almighty God, and the Perſon of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: whether they ſaid, there is but one Divine Perſon, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is a Man only; or whether they held a Trinity of Divine Perſons, and that our Saviour is God moſt High? We affirm the former of theſe, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> the latter. We alledg that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſays, in expreſs Terms; the Nazarens honour the Lord Chriſt, not as God, but <hi>only as a holy Man.</hi> We obſerve, that <hi>Theodoret</hi> lived where (<hi>Epiphanius</hi> informs us) the Nazaren Churches then moſt abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>in Syriâ cavâ:</hi> and that in the Work by us quoted, it is the very Deſign of
<hi>Theodoret,</hi> to tell us the particular Opinions of the ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations and Sects of Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>We alledg again, that the moſt learned <hi>Origen,</hi> who alſo lived a long time in <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine</hi> it ſelf, ſays; that all Jewiſh Chriſtians were Ebionites. And <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that all Ebionites hold the Lord Chriſt is a Man only; but they are divided (ſays he) into two Sects: for the Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians and ſuch like Ebionites believe, Chriſt is <hi>a Man, the Son of</hi> Joſeph <hi>and</hi> Mary; others of them ſay, he is <hi>a Man (miraculouſly) generated by the Holy Spirit,</hi> or Divine Power, in the Womb of a Virgin.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, the Nazarens are Symmachians. But he means only, they are <hi>thus far</hi> Symmachians, that they think Chriſt is only a Man, not God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſays, <hi>the Nazarens communicated in their Hereſy with the Ebionites;</hi> and that they <hi>held as the Cerinthians do:</hi> both which belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that our Saviour was a mere Man. He ſays, <hi>they agreed in all Points with the Jews;</hi> concerning whom, 'tis certain and granted;<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53124:21"/>that they never belleved more than one Divine Perſon; and Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> himſelf has proved, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the Meſſias (or Chriſt) ſhould be a Man, not God. Again,
<hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> makes it appear, that he took it for yielded, that the Nazarens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the Lord Chriſt to be a Man only; in that he doubts, whether they did not alſo hold, that he is <hi>the Son of only</hi> Joſeph
<hi>and</hi> Mary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Objections concerning the Nazarens.</head>
               <p>AS to what Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> objects, I ſhall now evince, how frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and impertinent it is. He ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects firſt, the Authority of
<hi>Sulpitius Severus,</hi> who began to write about the Year 401.
<hi>Sulpitius</hi> ſays,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Emperor <hi>Adrian</hi> drove <hi>all Jews</hi> out of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> but this tended to the Advantage of the Chriſtian Religion; for at that time <hi>almoſt all</hi> of them believed
<hi>in Chriſt God.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Hiſt. ſacr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 31. This Expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all Jews, from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> hapned about the Year of Chriſt 135. The Words <hi>almoſt all</hi> are intended to ſignify, that as the Jews were the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority of the Inhabitants and Citizens of
<hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> ſo the moſt (the far greater Number) of them were Chriſtians. But when he adds, they believed <hi>in Chriſt-God;</hi> I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it to be a Miſtake, by the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thoſe Fathers who lived among the Jewiſh Chriſtians, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Origen</hi> and
<hi>Theodoret;</hi> and of other Fathers who were much nearer to them than
<hi>Sulpitius,</hi> even <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtin. Epiphanius</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantia</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> an Iſland juſt by <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> and he himſelf was a Native, and had his Education in <hi>Paleſtine:</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> from
<hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> informed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the State of the Syrian and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine Churches, not only by Letters <hi>to</hi> and
<hi>from</hi> the Learned Men of thoſe Churches and Provinces; but alſo by ſome of his Clergy, whom he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Holy Land, only for Intelligence and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. On the contrary,
<hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitius</hi> lived in <hi>Aquitain,</hi> a Province of <hi>Gaul,</hi> in the (remoteſt) weſtern Parts of the Roman Empire; at the Diſtance of above 2000 Miles from <hi>Paleſtine</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> where the Jewiſh Chriſtians had their Churches; or as their Enemies (particularly St.
<hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi>) ſpoke, their <hi>Synagogues.</hi> We cannot much wonder, that at ſo great a Diſtance from the Jewiſh Chriſtians,
<hi>Sulpitius</hi> miſtook their Doctrine, concerning the Quality of our Saviour's Perſon, or whether he were God or Man: nor will any Man of Prudence think, that one <hi>Sulpitius,</hi> at ſuch a Remotion from them, is to be believed, againſt ſo many moſt learned Fathers, who dwelt partly among the Nazarens, partly very<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53124:21"/>near to them. Beſide,
<hi>Sulpitius</hi> was not a Divine, but a Lawyer; bred a Heathen, and went over to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion after he had long pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed (as they ſpeak) at the Bar: 'tis eaſily conceived, that a New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to Chriſtianity, might not be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry skilful in the Knowledg and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Sects. Therefore Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>du Pin</hi> obſerves concerning
<hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitius,</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"That tho his Abridgment of the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory is the beſt we have of the Antients, yet it is not very exact: He commits di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Faults againſt the Truth of Hiſtory, eſpecially the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</q> 
                  <hi>Eccl. Hiſt. cent.</hi> 5.
<hi>p.</hi> 112.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> cites alſo <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. l.</hi> 4.
<hi>c.</hi> 5. where that Hiſtorian ſays; that the firſt 15 Biſhops of
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſat but a very ſhort time; but that he finds in the Writings of the Antients, that <hi>thoſe Biſhops received and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the true Knowledg of Chriſt.</hi> I believe, there is no learned Man will doubt, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> his Author for <hi>this,</hi> was <hi>Hegeſippus;</hi> who was the firſt that wrote an Eccleſiaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which he publiſhed about the Year of Chriſt 170, a Work now loſt, to the great Regret of learned Men. But when <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> ſays, the Biſhops of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> profeſſed <hi>the true Knowledg of Chriſt,</hi> did he mean, as Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſuppoſes, that Chriſt is God moſt High? No, he meant, that they profeſſed (in oppoſition to the <hi>Docetae</hi> and others, who held the Pre-exiſtence of our Saviour, and that he was not a Man) <hi>he was a true and very Man, and a Man only:</hi> Of this I am perſwaded by theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> was himſelf a Jewiſh Chriſtian, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> (<hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.) witneſſes: but all Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Chriſtians, ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi> (who lived and flouriſh'd above 100 Years before <hi>Euſebius</hi>) were Ebionites, that is, denied the Divinity of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The ſame <hi>Euſebius (ibid)</hi> ſays, that
<hi>Hegeſippus made uſe of St.</hi> Matthew<hi>'s Hebrew Goſpel;</hi> which was uſed only by the Ebiouites, and Unitarian Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, When <hi>Hegeſippus (apud Euſeb. ibid.)</hi> reckons up the Hereſies and Hereticks of the Jewiſh Nation, that were (ſaith he) againſt the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and againſt Chriſt; he names the Samaritans, Phariſees, Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, Eſſeans, Masbotheans, Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans, Hemerobaptiſts: but if the Denial of our Saviour's Divinity had been a Jewiſh Hereſy, if the Ebionites or Cerinthians had been Hereticks, in the Judgment of <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> they muſt have come into the Catalogue of <hi>Hereticks that were againſt Chriſt,</hi> for 'tis certain (and yielded on all hands) that both theſe Sects denied the Divinity of our Saviour. If it be ſaid, <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> might not reckon the Ebionites and Cerinthians among the Jewiſh Hereticks; becauſe tho they were Jews by Nation, they were Chriſtians by Religion: yet at leaſt he would have put them into the Liſt of Chriſtian Hereticks, which he does not. The Chriſtian Hereſies, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> are the Hereſy of the Simomans, Menandrians, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionites,<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53124:22"/>Carpocratians, Valentinians, Baſilidiaus, Saturninians; but not a word of the Ebionite, Cerinthian, Alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, or Monarchian Hereticks, who were all Unitarians. But the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der muſt here take care, that he is not impoſed on by
<hi>Valeſius</hi> his Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of <hi>Euſebius:</hi> for the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after the Enumeration of the before-named Hereſies and Hereticks, adds <hi>(alii<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>) and others,</hi> as if ſome were omitted; but the Greek Text of <hi>Euſebius</hi> has no ſuch Words. In ſhort, I ſay, <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> gives a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the Hereſies of the Jews and Gentiles, but does not account ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Cerinthians or Ebionites among the Hereticks; which he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly would, if he himſelf had held the Pre-exiſtence and Divinity of our Saviour.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I have before cited <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> owning and profeſſing, that the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory of <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> was loſt by the Antients: becauſe (like the Hypotypoſes of St.
<hi>Clemens</hi>) it was obſerved to agree with the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians. If it be ſaid, But did not <hi>Euſebius</hi> know <hi>this;</hi> and yet he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſpeaks reſpectfully of <hi>Hegeſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put:</hi> I anſwer, without doubt he knew it; but durſt not take notice of it: it was not for <hi>Euſebius,</hi> to find fault with an Apoſtolical Father; he could only diſſemble his Knowledg of what the Unitarians (and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly his Antagoniſt
<hi>Marcellus</hi>) would not fail to make Advantage; and this alſo is the Reaſon, as I hinted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, why this crafty Arian will take no notice of the Apoſtolick Creed, <hi>as compoſed by them,</hi> tho he <hi>recites paraphraſtically</hi> (that ſo he may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on his Reader) the Heads of it. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> (Unitarian <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſippus</hi>) was the Author whom <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> follows, in the Account he gives of the firſt 15 Biſhops of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> that <hi>they profeſſed the true Knowledg of Chriſt;</hi> which will not be queſtioned by any that are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> or have obſerved that he profeſſes (<hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8, &amp; 22.) to follow
<hi>Hegeſippus</hi> concerning the Apoſtolick and following times: we have alſo gained another very great Point; namely, this. That not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Jewiſh Chriſtians, but thoſe of <hi>Rome</hi> and all the great Churches to which <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> had reſorted, to know their Doctrine and Diſcipline, were alſo Unitarians; that is, held (with
<hi>Hegeſippus</hi>) that the Lord Chriſt is a Man only. For he ſaith (<hi>apud Euſeb. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.)
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"That he travelled to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he lived under the Popes <hi>Anicetus, Soter</hi> and <hi>Eleutherus,</hi> ſucceſſively Popes of <hi>Rome;</hi> but both here, and in all other Epiſcopates, they keep the Doctrines taught by the Law and the Prophets, and by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</q> Briefly, he owns, that he found the Churches every where to be Orthodox and uniform: of which, if he was an Unitarian, as (I think) I have proved, the Meaning can be only this; that they believed, as the Jewiſh Chriſtians do, <hi>the Lord Chriſt is a Man, the Prophet and Meſſenger of God, on whom the</hi> Logos <hi>or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53124:22"/>WORD reſted.</hi> This perfectly agrees with the Account that the old Unitarians (in <hi>Euſebius</hi>) give; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>they had kept the Doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd by the Apoſtles, and which was profeſſed every where, till the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition made to it, by the Popes</hi> Victor <hi>and</hi> Zepherin, who ſucceeded to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leutherus,</hi> as he to <hi>Soter,</hi> and
<hi>Soter</hi> to <hi>Anicetus,</hi> with which Orthodox Popes
<hi>Hegeſippus</hi> had converſed. The ſhort is; We grant that
<hi>Euſebius</hi> ſays, the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Biſhops
<hi>profeſſed the true Knowledg of Chriſt:</hi> We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he borrowed this from <hi>Hege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſippus,</hi> whom he took for his Author, eſpecially in what concerned the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Times, and the Times that followed, to the taking of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Emperor <hi>Adrian</hi> in the Year 135, that is, while the 15 Biſhops (concerning whom our preſent Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and Debate is) governed the Churches of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judea.</hi> But <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> being himſelf a Jewiſh Chriſtian, that is, one that believed our Saviour to be a Man only, when he ſaid, the
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Biſhops pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed <hi>the true Knowledg of Chriſt,</hi> he undoubtedly meant, that our Lord was a true and mere Man; againſt the <hi>Docetae</hi> and other platonizing Chriſtians, who held his Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, and denied that he was a Man.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is not aſhamed to infer, from St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Saying, that <hi>the Nazarens confeſs Chriſt is the Son of God;</hi> that they held he is ſo the Son of God, that <hi>he was born of God from all Eternity.</hi> I ſay, he is <hi>not aſhamed</hi> of this Inference, tho he knows that all Ebionites believed Chriſt was a Man only; and yet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius</hi> ſays of them, divers times, as St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> does of the Nazarens, that <hi>they own the Lord Chriſt is the Son of God.</hi> For tho the Ebionites did not believe the miraculous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, yet they ſaid the Lord Chriſt is the Son of God,
<hi>progreſſione Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; quatenus ad ſublimia coeleſtia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> provectus eſt, i. e.</hi> by Holineſs, and by his Exaltation to the right Hand of God, <hi>Epiphan. Haereſ. Ebion. c.</hi> 13. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3.
<hi>c.</hi> 30. But let us recite the very Words of St. <hi>Auſtin, de Haereſ. c.</hi> 9, 10.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"The <hi>Nazarens,</hi> as they confeſs Chriſt is the Son of God, ſo they obſerve the whole Law; the which, Chriſtians have been taught that 'tis to be underſtood and taken ſpiritually, not carnally. The Ebionites <hi>alſo</hi> ſay, that Chriſt is a Man only, and obſerve the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Precepts of the Law.</q> Theſe Words, <hi>the Ebionites alſo ſay, that Chriſt is a Man only,</hi> would be Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe; if the Nazarens, of whom he ſpeaks <hi>immediately before,</hi> had not likewiſe ſo held.</p>
               <p>In like manner he would put a falſe Meaning on theſe Words of St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom;</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Nazarens believe in Chriſt the Son of God, who was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> the ſame, ſay they, who ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> and roſe again from the Dead; in whom alſo <hi>WE</hi> (i. e. <hi>we of the Church</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</q> One would have thought, that when the Nazarens ſay here; <pb n="44" facs="tcp:53124:23"/>We believe in the Son of God <hi>that was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>was put to Death under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>and roſe again from the Dead:</hi> they had ſufficiently declared, that the Son of God in whom they believed was <hi>the Man</hi> Chriſt Jeſus; not a Son of God that could not be born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or die, or riſe again. But becauſe St.
<hi>Jerom</hi> ſays, <hi>in whom alſo we believe;</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> cries out, Look here, the Nazarens believed in that Son of God, in whom the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox believed. <hi>We</hi> think ſo too, Doctor; becauſe both Parties believed in the Son of God, <hi>who was generated and born of</hi> Mary,
<hi>died, and roſe again:</hi> tho the Orthodox (ſo called) invented alſo another Son of God; a Son that could not be generated and born of
<hi>Mary,</hi> a Son that could not die, a Son <hi>as old as his Father,</hi> a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Almighty, another Creator, firſt made known by the Council of
<hi>Nice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> produces as Paſſage out of
<hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> to prove that there were ſome Chriſtians who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Moſaick Law, and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in ſuch a Chriſt, <hi>who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Luciſer <hi>and the Moon:</hi> and who could theſe be, but the Nazarens? I anſwer; whoever they were, they were not the Nazarens: moſt of the Gnoſtick Sects, who alſo obſerved the Moſaick Law, beld the Pre-exiſtence of our Saviour. What hinders, but that they might be the Cerinthians? Beſides, it is uncertain, whether <hi>Juſtin</hi> meant to ſay, that there were ſome Chriſtians who keep the Law of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> and yet believe that Chriſt was <hi>before</hi> Lucifer
<hi>and the Moon:</hi> to make out this Senſe, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is forced to add theſe Words to the Words of <hi>Juſtin, ſuch a Chriſt as you before deſcribed. Judic. Eccl. p.</hi> 52. which Addition ſeems alſo contrary to the Context, where 'tis inſerted by Dr. <hi>Bull;</hi> for Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> contends for a Chriſt (in that Context) who was <hi>before</hi> Lucifer
<hi>and the Moon;</hi> and the Context deſcribes <hi>a Chriſt that was crucified, and to whom GOD has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Judgment of the Dead and Living, and has given to him a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that ſhall have no end.</hi> This ſeems to be a mere Ebionite or Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian-Chriſt; a Man, not God.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he quotes the Title of the 12<hi>th</hi> Chapter of the 6<hi>th</hi> Book of <hi>the Conſtitutions</hi> of St. <hi>Clement,</hi> that is, as Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> himſelf confeſſes, falſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled to Sr. <hi>Clement.</hi> The Words are theſe, <hi>Of thoſe who confeſs, but yet live after the manner of the Jews:</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> would have it thought, that this Title ſpeaks of thoſe <hi>who confeſs that Chriſt is the moſt High and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God.</hi> Theſe, Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> thinks, could be no other but the Nazarens. But to come at that Concluſion, Mr.
<hi>Bull</hi> muſt firſt prove; not only that the Nazarens believed the Lord Chriſt is <hi>God the WORD:</hi> but that there were no other Denominations of Chriſtians, who obſerved the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaick Law. and alſo believed that Chriſt is <hi>God the WORD.</hi> But he knows, that the Cerinthians, and moſt of the Gnoſtick Sects, did Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daize and alſo believe the Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53124:23"/>of our Saviour, and that he is
<hi>God the WORD.</hi> But let us grant to Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> whatever he contends for, from this Citation; and ſee how it will advantage his main Cauſe. The Queſtion is concerning the Nazarens, whether they held, as the Church now does, that there is more than one <hi>Divine</hi> and
<hi>Eternal</hi> Perſon; are there two, or three ſuch Perſons, is the Lord Chriſt <hi>the eternal God?</hi> Yes, ſays Dr. <hi>Bull;</hi> for
<hi>the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> (chap. 11.) have a Confeſſion to that purpoſe; and the 12<hi>th</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is <hi>concerning thoſe that confeſs</hi> (that is, ſo confeſs) <hi>and yet live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the Jews,</hi> that is, obſerve the Moſaick Law: and theſe, moſt certainly, were the Nazarens. But if the Nazarens <hi>confeſſed</hi> in the
<hi>Form</hi> there mentioned; they were far from believing as Dr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> and the Church, now believe. Let us hear the Confeſſion at
<hi>chap.</hi> 11. to which the Title urged by Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> does refer. It ſaith,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"We teach but one God, the Father of Chriſt; not a ſecond, not a third, not a manifold God; but one eternal God.</q> One would think, this were <hi>Socinus,</hi> or <hi>J. Crellius de uno Deo Patre:</hi> but towards the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, the Author (or Authors) ſhow, that he held the ſame Doctrine with <hi>Arius;</hi> for tho he had ſaid, there is but one God <hi>who is Eternal</hi> or from Eternity, yet he owns that Chriſt is <hi>not a mere Man,</hi> but is alſo <hi>God the WORD.</hi> That is, there is but one <hi>true,</hi> one <hi>eternal</hi> God, yet the Son or WORD is alſo God in an inferiour Senſe: namely, a God that was generated in time, and is ſet over the Works of the Creation. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>du Pin</hi> deals ingenuouſly, when he owns, that the Author of <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions</hi> ſeems to have been an Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: he rightly adds, that
<hi>the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, as we now have them,</hi> were forged after the times of St. <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius;</hi> for that Father quotes them far otherways than, nay contrary to, what they now are. <hi>Eccl. Hiſt. Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi>
29, 30.</p>
               <p>If the Reader compares this Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with what I have alledged in the foregoing, he will perceive, that 'tis with the greateſt Juſtice and Truth in the World, that the preſent Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians claim the Nazarens (or firſt Jewiſh Churches and Chriſtians) as of our Party.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Alogi, or Alogians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the Nazarens, that is, the <hi>Jewiſh Chriſtians,</hi> I go on to the <hi>Alogi</hi> or <hi>Alogians,</hi> who were the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<hi>Gentile Chriſtians.</hi> They were called <hi>Alogian,</hi> or
<hi>Alogi,</hi> becauſe they denied the <hi>Logos</hi> or WORD, of which St.
<hi>John</hi> ſpeaks in his Goſpel, Epiſtles and Revelation: they ſaid, that all thoſe Pieces were written by <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> under the Name of St.<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53124:24"/>
                  <hi>John;</hi> to confirm <hi>Cerinthus</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits about the <hi>Logos,</hi> and the <hi>Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> or thouſand Years Reign of Chriſt here upon Earth. For tho the <hi>Alogi</hi> held, that the Lord Chriſt is a Man only; as alſo did <hi>Cerinthus;</hi> yet
<hi>Cerinthus</hi> (of the antient Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians) had theſe two things, peculiar to himſelf. 1. That the World was made, not immediately by God; but
<hi>by God, by the Miniſtry of his Angels.</hi> 2. That the Lord Chriſt was a Man only, the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> but <hi>there reſted on him the Logos or Divine WORD,</hi> which he alſo called <hi>the Chriſt,</hi> by which <hi>Cerinthus</hi> intended the Spirit, Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy or Power of God, that Power by which he created Original Matter, and made the World: but as the Chriſt or WORD deſcended on Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus at his Baptiſm, ſo it left him at his Crucifixion. The Alogians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved none of theſe things: they ſaid, they had only received from the Apoſiles; that the Lord Chriſt was the great Prophet promiſed by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Law, and the Meſſias (or Chriſt) intended in the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> and who (in the Fulneſs of Time) was ſent by God to unite both Jews and Gentiles under one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Inſtitution, or Law of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is the firſt, who gave to them the Name of
<hi>Alogi:</hi> before him, that is before the Year 368, they were ſimply called Chriſtians; without any other Name, that might ſignify them to be a particular Sect. They were thoſe Chriſtians of the Gentiles, who retained the ſincere Apoſtolick Doctrine concerning the Unity of God, and the Perſon of our Saviour, without corrupting it (more or leſs) with Platonick Notions, or Gnoſtick Novelties: they were very antient, co-eval with the Apoſtles; and flouriſhed (as the prevailing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) in the Period called
<hi>the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Succeſſion,</hi> or to about the Year 140.
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> all along ſpeaks of them, as the antient Unitarians of the Gentiles: He ſays alſo expreſly, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus adjunxit ſe Haereſi Alogorum;</hi> Theodotus <hi>joined himſelf to the Sect and Churches of the Alogians. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> appeared about the Year 190; by joining himſelf to the Alogian Sect, we learn, that before he was of the Number of the (new) Platonick Chriſtians; who held the Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of our Saviour. <hi>Euſebius</hi> is ſtrangely out, or prevaricates too no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly, when he ſays, <hi>Hiſt. Eccl. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28. that this <hi>Theodotus</hi> was the firſt, who held that our Saviour was
<hi>a mere Man:</hi> for not only the Alogians ſo held, but ſo alſo did both ſorts of Ebionites, and that by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Euſebius</hi> himſelf elſewhere, particularly <hi>H. Eccl. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 27. But
<hi>Euſebius</hi> takes all Occaſions, tho ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fraudulently, to depreſs the Unitarians, whom he had undertaken to confute in the Perſon of
<hi>Marcellus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ancyra.</hi> We may take notice too, that the <hi>Excerpta</hi> at the End of <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> his Books of <hi>Stromata,</hi> which bear the Title of <hi>the Oriental Doctrine of Theodotus,</hi> were not Particulars of the Doctrine of <hi>Theodotus</hi> the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53124:24"/>for the Doctrine of <hi>Theodotus</hi> was diametrically oppoſite to the Contents of thoſe <hi>Excerpta:</hi> but the
<hi>Excerpta</hi> are nothing elſe but a Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Hypotypoſes of St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> himſelf; which alſo is obſerved by the learned
<hi>Valeſius,</hi> in his firſt Note on <hi>Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 5.
<hi>c.</hi> 11. and again on <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 14. In few Words; that the Alogi held our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was a Man only, is not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by any: that they belonged at leaſt to <hi>the Apoſtolick Succeſſion</hi> is proved; becauſe 'tis confeſſed by the Trinitarian Hiſtorians, that the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotians (who appeared about the Year 190) joined themſelves to the Alogian Churches; and becauſe <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> ſpeaks of them (throughout) as flouriſhing in that Period. We have therefore deſervedly here reckoned them, among the antient and firſt Witneſſes of the true Doctrine. As to the Reaſons which they gave, <hi>and which I affirm not,</hi> againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and other Works, which we now account to St.
<hi>John,</hi> I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready (briefly) intimated them, in <hi>the Conſiderations</hi> on the 4 Sermons of his Grace the Archbiſhop of
<hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> It was 400 Years before the Epiſtle to the
<hi>Hebrews</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as Canonical, any where in the Weſt, and but in few Places of the Orient; and other Books of the New Teſtament, eſpecially St. <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Revelation,</hi> were not preſently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Catholick Church: it ought not therefore to ſeem ſtrange, that the modern Unitarians allow of the Goſpel and other Pieces of St.
<hi>John;</hi> tho they are aware that many of the Antients, and particularly ſome Unitarians ſuſpected, and (too haſtily) rejected them. As it often happens, that Time detects Frauds and Falſhoods, ſo alſo (not unfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) it diſcovers and vindicates oppreſſed Truths.</p>
               <p>The laſt Monument or Remain of <hi>the Apoſtolick Succeſſion,</hi> which agrees with the Socinian Doctrine concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Saviour, are <hi>the Recognitions,</hi> imputed to <hi>Clemens Romanus.</hi> They ſeem to be falſly reckoned to St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens:</hi> but they are very antient, publiſhed (probably) in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the 2<hi>d</hi> Century, or the ſecond Century being but little advanced; when ſo many other ſpurious Pieces were ſet forth, under the Names of Apoſtles, or of Apoſtolical Men. The Recognitions are quoted (divers times) by
<hi>Origen,</hi> who began to flouriſh about the Year 210. But they are much antienter than <hi>Origen,</hi> for in a Fragment of <hi>Bardeſanes</hi> (<hi>apud Euſeb. Praep. Evang. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 10.) who flouriſhed about the Year 170, there is a Paſſage taken word for word out of the
9<hi>th</hi> Book of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitions. Whereas Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, that <hi>Bardeſanes</hi> was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Recognitions;</hi> his Gueſs is nothing probable, nay a manifeſt Miſtake; becauſe the Author of the <hi>Recognitions</hi> was an Ebionite; but <hi>Bardeſanes</hi> a Valentinian, that is, held the Pre-exiſtence of our Saviour, and that he was not (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>made of a Woman,</hi> but brought his Fleſh from Heaven. It<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53124:25"/>remains therefore, that the
<hi>Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are antienter, not only than <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen,</hi> but than
<hi>Bardeſanes:</hi> how much antienter we cannot determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately ſay; but probably publiſhed when the 2<hi>d</hi> Century was but little advanced, when ſo many affected to countenance their own Productions, with the authoritative Names of the Apoſiles and Apoſtolical Men. But tho the
<hi>Recogaitions</hi> are not the Work of <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> yet they ſerve to let us know, what Doctrines and Rites were current or in uſe in thoſe times: and to this purpoſe they are quoted by the ſeverely Criticks, of all Parties and Perſwaſions. I ſhall not need to cite particular Paſſages out of theſe Books: for 'tis conſeſſed by the Trinitarian Criticks, and by Monſieur <hi>du Pin,</hi> who hath written laſt on the Fathers, that the Author of the Recognitions was a manifeſt Ebionite. <hi>Eccl. Hiſt. cent.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>But hitherto of <hi>the Apoſtolick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and the Writings and Remains of <hi>the Apoſtolick Succeſſion.</hi> I have proved, I think, that hitherto we have no certain or probable notice, that there were yet any who publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſed to hold the Pre-exiſtence of our Saviour; or that he was <hi>God,</hi> in any Senſe of that Word. But on the contrary, the Apoſtles Creed. the true (and by all confeſſed) St.
<hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Romanus,</hi> the Nazaren, Minean or Ebionite (that is, the Jewiſh) Churches, the Alogians (or Gentile Churches) <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> the Father of Ecclefiaſtical Hiſtory, the moſt antient Author of the
<hi>Recognitions,</hi> were all of them Unitarians; that is, held there is but one Divine Perſon, and the Lord Chriſt was a Man only.</p>
               <p>It ſhould ſeem then, that very thing hapned to the Chriſtian Church, which had formerly come to paſs in the Church of the Jews. For as the Author of the Book of <hi>Judges</hi> (Judg. 2.7.) ſays;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"The People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſerved the Lord, all the Days of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and of <hi>the Elders</hi> that outlived <hi>Joſhua;</hi>—but when all that Generation was gathered to their Fathers, there aroſe another after them, which knew not the Lord: ſo the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did Evil in the ſight of the Lord, and ſerved <hi>Baalim,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Gods.</hi>
                  </q> In like manner, while the Apoſtles lived, and thoſe <hi>Elders</hi> who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with the Apoſtles, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church kept her ſelf to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment and Worſhip of the one true God; and preſerved the true Doctrine and Faith concerning the Perſon of the Lord Chriſt, that he was a holy Man, the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Meſſias, promiſed in the Law and other Book, of the Old Teſtament. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſiles themſelves, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Succuſſion, were gathered to their Fathers, then
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to prevail apace:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied a pre-exiſtent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, God's Miniſter and Inſtrument in the creating of all things, and but little leſs than his Father. <hi>A Son,</hi> ſaid they, who being (tho but <hi>the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental,</hi> yet) <hi>the immediate</hi> Creator of all things, is to be worſhipped by<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53124:25"/>us his Creatures. <hi>A Son,</hi> who, tho with reſpect to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as they ſtill ſpoke) <hi>the true and very God</hi> the Father, is but a Miniſter and Subject; yet with reſpect to us (his Creatures) is a God.
<hi>A Son,</hi> who muſt be called
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a God:</hi> tho on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Father may be called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the God;</hi> that is, God <hi>by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence</hi> and true Propriety. In a word, after the Apoſtles, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Elders or Paſtors, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to reſt, the next Generation, like the Jewiſh Church, <hi>did Evil in the Sight of the Lord, and ſerved Baalim:</hi> that is, the half-Gods of their own deviſing. <hi>Nemo repente fit turpiſſimus,</hi> therefore here they ſtop a conſiderable time; namely, from about the Year 140 and
150, to the Nicene Council, or the Year 325. at what time, as we ſhall ſee hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Superſtition and Impiety made a ſudden and wonderful Advance.</p>
               <p>The firſt Defender and publick Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of the Apoſtacy, mentioned in the foregoing Paragraph, was <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> about the Year 150. Our Oppoſers can quote no Father (or genuine Monument) older than
<hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr,</hi> for the Pre-exiſtence of our Saviour; or that he ought to be called a God, in ſo much as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained inſeriour Senſe, before ſaid. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> indeed pretends to prove the contrary, from (the counterſeit) <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> the falſe
<hi>Ignatius,</hi> aliàs <hi>Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> and the Impoſtor
<hi>Hermas:</hi> how injudiciouſly, I think, hath been competently ſhown in theſe preſent Papers; but I will yet oppoſe to him one Authority, which (I doubt not) will convince the indifferent unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that capital Antagoniſt of the Nazaren and Alogian Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and who ſearched with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Diligence, into the remoteſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, for whatſoever might ſeem to make againſt them, quotes (<hi>H. E. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28.) a very antient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, whom (in his foregoing Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) he reckons among the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Writers that <hi>deſerve</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to be eſteemed for their laudable Zeal and Induſtry.</hi> This laudable Man, you muſt know, wrote a Book againſt the Theodotians and Artemonites, who were Branches of the Alogians: what <hi>Euſebius</hi> there cites out of him, is as follows:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Unitarians pretend, that <hi>the Apoſtles</hi> and all <hi>the Antients</hi> held the very Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, concerning the Perſon of our Saviour, that is now main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Unitarians: and that it is but only ſince the Times of the Popes
<hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Zepherin,</hi> that the Truth has been adultera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſcountenanced. This would be credible, if (firſt) the Unitarian Doctrine were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Holy Scripture; and if divers before <hi>Victor</hi> and
<hi>Zepherin</hi> had not contended for the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Lord Chriſt, namely, <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Miltiades, Tatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Clemens</hi> of
<hi>Alexandria, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus, Melito.</hi> To whom we may add the antient Hymns or Pſalms, <hi>wrote from the beginning by the Brethren;</hi> which ſpeak of Chriſt,<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53124:26"/>as <hi>the WORD of God,</hi> and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to him
<hi>Divinity.</hi>
                  </q> I will omit now, that all theſe, but only
<hi>Juſtin,</hi> were <hi>but Contemporaries</hi> to <hi>Victor</hi> and
<hi>Zepherin;</hi> or after them: for it is home to my purpoſe, that <hi>the firſt</hi> whom our Oppoſers (of thoſe early times) could quote, was
<hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> who ſaith himſelf, in his firſt Apology, that he preſented his Apology in the Year 150. The Epiſtles of <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and the Prophecies and Viſions of <hi>Hermas,</hi> were not (it ſhould ſeem) yet come out of the Mint; or were ſo well known to be Impoſtures, that no Body durſt to alledg them, in theſe Controverſies. The Queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> and the preſent Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians is, concerning the Fathers and Monuments of <hi>the Apoſtolick Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion:</hi> whether theſe held our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Pre-exiſtence and Divinity? <hi>Euſebius</hi> anſwers us, out of <hi>a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Author;</hi> that <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed our Doctrine, that is, he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth up to us the whole <hi>Apoſtolick Succeſſion;</hi> which is as much as the Socinians ever claimed. As to the Hymns or Pſalms of <hi>the Brethren,</hi> which (he ſaith) ſpoke of Chriſt as the WORD of God, and attributed to him Divinity; 'tis plain, that he ſpoke raſhly and at adventures, when he added, <hi>they were compoſed by the Brethren from the very firſt:</hi> for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Authors</hi> of them were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known; ſo alſo of neceſſity muſt <hi>their Date.</hi> Is doubt not, theſe are <hi>the Pſalms in Honour of Chriſt,</hi> which were put down in the Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> under this Cenſure, that in very deed they were
<hi>novel Compoſitions, by later Men, and containing ſome dangerous Strains.</hi> As we learn from a Letter of the Council at <hi>Anticch, apud Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>Having ſaid what was neceſſary, concerning <hi>the Apoſtolick Fathers,</hi> I might now proceed immediately to <hi>the Primitive Fathers,</hi> ſo called, to diſtinguiſh them from the Fathers that lived after the Nicene Council, or the Year 325, who are ſimply called
<hi>Fathers.</hi> But becauſe I would have nothing elſe to do, in the
2<hi>d</hi> and 3<hi>d</hi> Parts of this Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> but only to examine and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs his (impertinent and moſt frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent) Citations out of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and to oppoſe to them (the certain and clear) Teſtimonies of the ſame (and other) Fathers: therefore here I will conſider the two Paſſages in Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s <hi>Defence of the Nicene Council,</hi> which (in my opinion) are the only Parts of his Book that needed to be at all remarked on by the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians. The firſt is, concerning
<hi>the Grounds</hi> on which <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and the following Fathers built their new Doctrine of our Saviour's Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence; and that he was (tho a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial and Subordinate,</hi> yet) an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the Creation of all things. The other is; whether the Explication of the Trinity (or how <hi>three</hi> Divine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eternal co-equal <hi>Perſons</hi> and
<hi>Spirits,</hi> can be but <hi>one</hi> God) given by Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> as out of the Fathers, be not an unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable unavoidable Tritheiſm?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:53124:26"/>
               <head>Of the Grounds on which <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and the following Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, built their Doctrine of our Saviour's Pre-exiſtence; and that he is a (Miniſterial) Creator.</head>
               <p>AFter Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> had quoted ſome Paſſages of the Fathers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſay, it was the Divine WORD who appeared ſo often to the Patriarchs, as to <hi>Adam, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Jacob, Moſes:</hi> He takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice alſo that ſome learned Men of the Moderns (at <hi>p.</hi> 20. he calls them
<hi>viri quidam doctriſſimi</hi>) deride theſe Citations, as mere Dreams of the good Fathers; and hold it for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth, that it was only an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel who appeared ſo often, and on ſo many Occaſions, to the Patriarchs: but the Angel, ſay they, is called Jehovah and God, <hi>becauſe on thoſe Occaſions he repreſented the Perſon and Authority of God.</hi> He notes again, that others may object here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; if the Fathers were miſtaken in the Ground on which they did build their Suppoſition of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Pre-exiſtence, 'tis but too probable, that they have erred alſo in the Suppoſition it ſelf, namely, that the Lord Chriſt did pre-exiſt, or had a Being before he was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> He anſwers to the ſeveral Arguments of the <hi>viri quidam doctiſſimi;</hi> and I intend here to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his Anſwers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They argue; that indeed it is ſaid (at <hi>Exod.</hi>
3.4.) <hi>God called to</hi> Moſes <hi>out of the midſt of the Buſh:</hi> but it is owned in the (preceding) 2<hi>d</hi> Verſe, that it was indeed
<hi>an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord that appeared to</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>in a Flame of Fire, in the midſt of the Buſh;</hi> and St. <hi>Stephen</hi> alſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, (<hi>Acts</hi> 7.30.) <hi>There appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to</hi> Moſes
<hi>an Angel of the Lord, in a Flame of Fire, in the midſt of a Buſh.</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> replies; 1<hi>ſt.</hi> The Divine WORD, who is the true God, might be called here an Angel; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he appeared in ſuch manner as Angels were wont to appear. 2<hi>dly.</hi> Some of the Fathers ſaid, that it was an Angel that appeared in the Buſh; but the Divine WORD was <hi>in</hi> the Angel; and it was God <hi>in</hi> the Angel, that ſpoke to
<hi>Moſes</hi> theſe Words, <hi>I am the God of thy Fathers.</hi>
3<hi>dly.</hi> 'Tis an abſurd, nay horrible Opinion, to think or maintain, that the Angels ever (as it were) <hi>acted the Perſon, and part of God,</hi> by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming his incommunicable Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or his Perſon, Authority and Attributes. He ſaith, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of, that an Ambaſſador (in delivering the Meſſage or Commands of his Maſter) took on him the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Stile of his Maſter; but all Ambaſſadors ſay only, <hi>thus ſaith my Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53124:27"/>Now in anſwer to theſe Eluſions; firſt, Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> has but imperfectly reported the Argument of thoſe learned Men, to whom he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to anſwer. For they not only alledg, that the Perſon who is called <hi>Jehovah</hi> at <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.4. is declared at <hi>ver.</hi> 2. of the ſame Chapter, and by St. <hi>Stephen</hi> at
<hi>Acts</hi> 7.30. to be only <hi>an Angel;</hi> therefore called
<hi>Jehovah</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> becauſe he repreſented the Perſon and Authority of God: but they prove this by Examples, and by very cogent Reaſons. <hi>Moſes</hi> tells the Iſraelites from God, <hi>Exod.</hi>
23.20.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"I ſend <hi>an Angel</hi> before thee in the way, to bring thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Place that I have prepared: Beware of him, obey his Voice, provoke him not; for he will not pardon your Tranſgreſſions, for <hi>my Name is in him.</hi>
                  </q> Who ſees not here, that the Meaning is, the Angel being to repreſent my Perſon, and to exerciſe my Authority, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>my Name is in him;</hi> or therefore he is called by my Name, even Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, or <hi>the LORD:</hi> which is the Name by which this Angel is all along called in the following Hiſtory, ſet down in the ſubſequent Chapters and Books of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Again, when it is ſaid at
<hi>Gen.</hi> 7.16. that <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons, and the Creatures that were to be preſerved, being entred into the Ark, the LORD (Heb.
<hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi>) ſhut them in; and when the Angel that wreſtled with
<hi>Jacob</hi> is called (<hi>Gen.</hi> 32.30.) <hi>God:</hi> is there not an abſolute neceſſity of ſaying, that theſe Angels had the Names
<hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovah</hi> and <hi>God</hi> given to them, on the account that they were heavenly Meſſengers, that repreſented the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God? For is it congruous to ſay, <hi>God ſhut the Door;</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> wreſtling with <hi>Jacob, prevailed not againſt him?</hi> In a word, the <hi>viri doctiſſimi</hi> ſhow, firſt, that 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid concerning a mere Angel, that <hi>the Name of God was in him:</hi> And next, that very often the Nature and Quality of the Action, that is imputed to the Perſon who bears the Names <hi>Jehovah</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> evinces, that the Perſon ſpoken of, is Jehovah and God, only by Repreſentation. But let us now weigh Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, firſt, the Divine WORD, who is true God, might be called an Angel, when he appeared to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Buſh;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Becauſe God appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>in ſuch manner,</hi> as Angels are wont to appear.</q> But <hi>we</hi> cannot grant, that if God appears in <hi>ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manner</hi> as Angels are wont to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, God may therefore be called an Angel: tho Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> deſires us, that
<hi>of all Love</hi> we would <hi>grant it;</hi> for he only ſays it, and offers no manner of Proof, of ſo abſurd and (in very deed) impoſſible a Suppoſition. And we give this (inconteſtable) Reaſon, why the Perſon who appeared in the Buſh to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and is called ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<hi>Angel,</hi> ſometimes <hi>God,</hi> was only an Angel who was called God on the Account that he repreſented God; becauſe if he were God, and therefore ſpoke theſe Words, <hi>I am the God of thy Fathers,</hi> in his own<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53124:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>Name, not in the Name of another, or as repreſenting another: He ſhould have been called <hi>God</hi> only; and not
<hi>Angel, which is to ſay Meſſenger.</hi> Nor do I know, why Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends here, God is called an Angel in this Place,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Becauſe he appeared <hi>in ſuch manner</hi> as Angels are wont to appear:</q> there was no Cauſe at all, why he ſhould ſay ſo; at leaſt there is nothing in the Text or Context, to countenance his ſo ſaying. But <hi>our</hi> Argument is extremely probable, while we ſay; if it was indeed (not an Angel, but) God himſelf that ſpake theſe Words, <hi>I am the God of thy Fathers,</hi> he could be only called
<hi>God,</hi> and he was not at all <hi>an Angel,</hi> that is <hi>a Meſſenger.</hi> Briefly, 'tis (ſay I) a Chimera, founded on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, what Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> here ſays, that the true God is called an Angel in this Context, becauſe he appeared <hi>in ſuch manner as Angels are wont to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear:</hi> for the <hi>manner of appearing</hi> here was wholly
<hi>unuſual;</hi> there never was any ſuch Appearance, whether by God or Angel, either before or ſince. But <hi>we</hi> argue ſolidly and concluding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when we alledg; if it be not an Angel that ſpeaks here, in the Name and Perſon of God; but God himſelf, and in his own Name: 'tis againſt all Propriety and Grammar, that he is called (both by
<hi>Moſes</hi> and St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi>) the Angel (or
<hi>Meſſenger</hi>) <hi>of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has a 2<hi>d</hi> Evaſion:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Several Fathers ſaid, an Angel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed appeared in the Buſh; but God was <hi>in</hi> the Angel: and it was not the Angel that ſpoke, but God in the Angel.</q> 
                  <hi>This is a Whimſy,</hi> tho he ſhould quote an hundred <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> for it. For if God himſelf was in the Fire, and the Voice was from God, not from the Angel, what need was there, that an Angel ſhould be there at all?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> he ſays, 'tis an impious Opinion, that Angels ever (as it were) <hi>acted the Perſon and Part of God;</hi> by aſſuming <hi>the incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Name</hi> Jehovah, and the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Attributes of God. No Ambaſſador, he ſaith, ever took on him the Name and Stile of his Prince; but the Ambaſſador ſays only, <hi>thus ſaith my Maſter.</hi> He is a bold Man, to charge even Angels themſelves; and ſo many Writers of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>as ridiculous and impious;</hi> for giving the Name <hi>God</hi> to thoſe that repreſent God. Has not our Saviour himſelf told us, that <hi>they</hi> alſo are called <hi>Gods,</hi> to whom the Word of God comes, that is, <hi>the Magiſtracy,</hi> as all confeſs. And for the Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> calls the Incommunicable Name; I ask, how comes <hi>Jehovah</hi> to be a greater Name, or more incommunicable, than <hi>God?</hi> And why has he ſaid nothing to ſo many Inſtances as the Socinians, and his own <hi>viri quidam doctiſſimi,</hi> give of Perſons, and even of Places; on which the Name
<hi>Jehovah</hi> is beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the Hiſtorical Books of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? What he ſays of Ambaſſadors ſerves only to ſhow, that he has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got ſome part of his Academical Learning, and is but little acquainted
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53124:28"/>with the World. There is no Freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridg,</hi> but will inform him, out of <hi>the Roman Antiquities;</hi> that Publick Meſſengers were wont to aſſurne the Name and whole Stile of the Perſons whom they repreſented. The <hi>Fecialis</hi> or <hi>Herald at Arms</hi> denounced War, in theſe Terms;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"I the King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rome</hi> denounce and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim Hoſtility and War, againſt the King and People of
<hi>N.</hi>
                  </q> At this preſent time, in the Chriſtian Countries, Ambaſſadors in ſome Caſes, take on them the Name and Stile of their Prince; as in all Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and ſome other Caſes: but they
<hi>always</hi> retain the Majeſty and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Prince or State from whom they come; they always ſpeak with the Hat on; and their Perſons are
<hi>ſacroſanct,</hi> that is, they cannot be arreſted, confined or puniſhed, they can only be required to depart out of the Kingdom. This whole Defence therefore of Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is either <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> or directly <hi>falſe.</hi> For if it had been God who ſpoke to
<hi>Moſes,</hi> out of the Buſh, he being <hi>preſent,</hi> and ſpeaking <hi>in his own Name</hi> theſe Words, <hi>I am the God of thy Fathers:</hi> he could not have at all been called an <hi>Angel,</hi> that is
<hi>Meſſenger.</hi> And if God himſelf, as Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> pretends, was in the Fire, there was no Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that an Angel alſo ſhould be there. And 'tis utterly falſe, that publick Meſſengers do not aſſume the Name, or the Stile, or Dignity of the Sovereigns that ſend them, and whom they repreſent. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thank Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> for giving up his Cauſe to the Socinians. For if it was the WORD (or Son) as he ſays, that appeared (in the Buſh) to <hi>Moſes;</hi> it follows, that the WORD is not God, but the Angel (or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger) of God: for he can never elude our Argument, that if the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſpoke theſe Words, <hi>I am the God of thy Fathers,</hi> had been God himſelf ſpeaking <hi>in his own Perſon,</hi> and <hi>there preſent,</hi> he could not have been called
<hi>a Meſſenger</hi> of the Lord either by <hi>Moſes</hi> or St.
<hi>Stephen.</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> muſt of neceſſity grant, either that the WORD did not appear in the Buſh; which is to yield that his Fathers miſtook, in the chief Ground on which they built our Saviour's Pre-exiſtence: or that the WORD is but <hi>a Meſſenger,</hi> not God; which is to yield his Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is argued again, againſt Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Fathers, by the <hi>viri quidam doctiſſimi,</hi> that indeed it is ſaid at Exod. 20.1. <hi>God ſpake all theſe Words,</hi> namely the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but other Texts inform us, that God is ſaid to have ſpoke the Commandments, and given the Law; becauſe <hi>it</hi> and <hi>they</hi> were given and ſpoke by an Angel (attended or accompanied by other Angels) in the Perſon and Name of God, or <hi>as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting God;</hi> Acts 7.53.
<hi>They received the Law, by the Diſpoſition of Angels.</hi> Gal. 3.19.
<hi>It was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Angels, in the Hand of a Mediator; i. e.</hi> it was commanded or ſpoken by Angels; yet not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to the People, but <hi>by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:53124:28"/>(that is, the Intervention) of
<hi>Moſes:</hi> the Angels ſpake it to <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the Mount; he to the People: <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2,3.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"If <hi>the Word ſpoke by Angels</hi> was ſtedfaſt;—how ſhall <hi>we</hi> eſcape, if we neglect ſo great Salvation, which at firſt began to be ſpoke by the Lord [Jeſus,] and was confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us, by them that heard him?</q> None ever doubted, that all theſe Texts ſpeak of <hi>the Law;</hi> and (the firſt and ſecond) of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments more eſpecially: but we ſee 'tis here ſaid, they were <hi>received from</hi> Angels, were <hi>ordained by</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, were
<hi>ſpoke by</hi> Angels; of which the Meaning can only be, that the Angels ſpoke, ordained, and gave the Law, <hi>in the Perſon of God,</hi> or <hi>as ſuſtaining the Name and Perſon of God;</hi> we can no otherways reconcile theſe Texts, to thoſe other which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the giving and ſpeaking the Law to God himſelf.</p>
               <p>Whereas Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> replies; the Law indeed is ſometimes ſaid to be given by Angels, and ſpoke by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, becauſe they were preſent and attended when God gave the Law: Almighty God came, he ſaith, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on by his Angels, to manifeſt his Greatneſs and Majeſty. I ask; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> God was <hi>perſonally</hi> preſent, nay it was he that ſpoke the Commandments and the Law: how could the Holy Scriptures ſay of the Angels, who aſſiſted only <hi>at Attendants and Servants</hi> in the Train of the Celeſtial King, that they
<hi>gave,</hi> they <hi>ordained,</hi> they <hi>ſpoke</hi> the Law? If his Majeſty ſhould come to Parliament in his Robes, and other Marks of Sovereign and Legiſlative Power; but withal waited on by the Gentlemen of his Chamber, or others whom he thinks fit to call to him: will any one be ſo abſurd as to ſay, that <hi>theſe Gentlemen made a moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Speech to the two Houſes?</hi> The Scriptures often tell us, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Law were <hi>ſpoke,</hi> were <hi>ordained,</hi> were <hi>given</hi> by Angels: True, ſays Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> out of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for the Angels were preſent, they waited on God when he gave, ordained, and ſpoke the Law. Who ſees not, that at this rate of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and arguing, he may alſo impute the Acts of our Kings and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to their Mace-bearers and Door-keepers?</p>
               <p>Whereas he refers us to <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.2. and
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.17. as Texts that will prove to us, that God himſelf was with the Angels at <hi>Sinai,</hi> where the Commandments and Law were delivered: it had been but civil, if he had repeated the very Words of thoſe Texts. Readers (commonly) take it very unkindly, when (lazy) Authors ſend them of an Errand; and generally to a wrong Place too. It may be, I am reading below Stairs in my Parlor; my Bible is on the Stool, by my Bed-ſide, two Stories higher: is it good Manners in an Author, to oblige me to clamber up, with gouty Knees and Hands, into my Bed-chamber, to ſearch for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Words which he himſelf durſt not recite, for fear I ſhould laugh at
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53124:29"/>him? Well, but I have look'd into the Texts, which Mr.
<hi>Bull</hi> was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to relate: and I will aſſure our common Reader, that they do not at all ſay, that God was any more with the Angels in
<hi>Sinai,</hi> than he is in all other Places; which is not ſuch a ſort of Preſence as will anſwer Mr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Purpoſe. We doubt not, God was at <hi>Sinai</hi> in the midſt of the Angels; in ſuch Senſe, as it is ſaid by <hi>David,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.25.)
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"It is well ſeen my God and King, how <hi>thou goeſt into the Sanctuary;</hi> the Minſtrels go <hi>before,</hi> the Singers <hi>follow,</hi> in <hi>the midſt</hi> are Damſels playing with Timbrels.</q> Or as he is in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Congregations of ſuch as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble to hear or pray. But <hi>we</hi> ſay, ſuch (general) Omnipreſence not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding; it is the Miniſter, not God, that (immediately) exhorts the Congregation: and at <hi>Sinai</hi> the Angels, not God, immediately gave and ſpoke the Law; that is, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Perſon of God, and by his eſpecial Mandate, Orders and Directions, they gave the Law and the Commandments.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Again, they object to Mr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Fathers,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1,2.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"God, who at ſundry times, and in divers manners, [as by Viſions, Dreams, Apparitions of his Angels] ſpake in times paſt by the Prophets to the Fathers, hath <hi>in theſe laſt Days</hi> ſpoken to <hi>us by his Son.</hi>
                  </q> Here now are Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Fathers and St. <hi>Paul</hi> at utter Variance. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, God
<hi>in times paſt</hi> ſpoke to the Patriarchs and the Jewiſh Church by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, in divers manners; by Dreams, Apparitions of Angels, Viſions, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Inſpirations: but at length, <hi>in theſe laſt Days,</hi> in the Goſpel-Age with which the World ſhall conclude, he has ſpoke to us by his Son. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Fathers, on the contrary, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that God ſpake all along in the Old Teſtament-times, not by a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Angel, but by his Son the eternal WORD. The Socinians are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely of opinion, that
<hi>one</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> is to be preferred, to <hi>all</hi> the Fathers: and tho on this Account they are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned grand Hereticks, yet they are content to be reproached for their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to Scripture.</p>
               <p>But what ſays Dr. <hi>Bull?</hi> He is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at a loſs, he anſwers. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 'tis but <hi>in theſe laſt Days,</hi> or in the Goſpel-Age, that the Son of God hath ſpoken to M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Meaning is, he did not before
<hi>ſpeak immediately</hi> to Men. How ſo; why not <hi>immediately,</hi> if he appeared <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> was heard <hi>audibly,</hi> and directed his Speech <hi>immediately to the Perſon</hi> (or Perſons) to whom he appeared? No, all this is not <hi>immediate ſpeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſays.
'Tis a hard Caſe truly; but when the Scriptures ſay farther, that God (that is, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel who repreſented God) <hi>ſpake to</hi> Moſes <hi>face to face, as a Man to his Friend;</hi> ſhall not this neither be <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate ſpeaking?</hi> Doubtleſs, it muſt not; for if it be, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has loſt his Cauſe; which is the only Reaſon, why, ſpeaking audibly, viſibly, face to face, and as a Man to his Friend, is not <hi>immediate ſpeaking.</hi> But when<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53124:29"/>the Apoſtle ſays; 'tis but
<hi>in theſe laſt Days,</hi> in the Goſpel-Age, that God hath ſpoke to Men by his Son: who gave Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> (or Friend <hi>L. de Tena</hi>) Authority to add to his Words <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately,</hi> or <hi>immediatione ſuppoſiti?</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks <hi>in unlimited Terms;</hi> it is, ſaith he, but only <hi>in this Goſpel-Age</hi> that God hath ſpoke to Men by his Son: fair and ſoftly, cries Dr. <hi>Bull;</hi> it muſt be underſtood <hi>cum grano ſalis,</hi> or good <hi>Paul</hi> is quite out; for when all is done, God ſpoke to Men by his Son, nay <hi>by none but him,</hi> from the very firſt. For the Son ſpoke to Men from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in the Likeneſs of an Angel; <hi>not indeed immediately,</hi> but viſibly, audibly, as a Friend to his Friend; and directing alſo his Speech
<hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, to the Perſon,</hi> and to no other, to whom he at that time appeared. And this they call, interpreting of Scripture; their Cauſe indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſuch Interpreters.</p>
               <p>But to prove, that the Lord Chriſt did indeed pre-exiſt; and was <hi>that</hi> Angel who led the Iſraelites thorow the Wilderneſs, Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> alledges 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.9.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"And let us not <hi>tempt Chriſt,</hi> as ſome of them alſo tempted, and were deſtroyed of Serpents.</q> The Iſraelites then were deſtroyed of Serpents, for their tempting (that is, provoking) the Lord Chriſt with their Sins, while (in the Appearance of an Angel) he led them thorow the Wilderneſs. To this Text <hi>Grotius</hi> anſwers, that without doubt, <hi>Let us not tempt Chriſt</hi> is a falſe Reading: and that we ought to read with <hi>the Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian Copy,</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Let us not tempt <hi>God,</hi> as ſome of them tempted, and were deſtroyed of Serpents.</q> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> replies, the Authority of <hi>the Alexandrian Copy</hi> cannot be oppoſed to the Syriac, Latin and Arabick Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St.
<hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> and <hi>Theophylact.</hi> Yes, <hi>the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrian Copy</hi> is much antienter than any of thoſe Verſions or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: the Latin (which is the firſt) was made by St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> above 100 Years after the Alexandrian Copy. But why has Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſuppreſſed it, that one of his own Hiſtorians (St. <hi>Epiphanius</hi>) has expreſly informed us, who was the particular Man that corrupted this Text: the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<hi>Marcion,</hi> inſtead of <hi>let us not tempt the Lord,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>God,</hi> publiſhed in his Copies, <hi>let us not tempt Chriſt: Epiphan. l.</hi> 1. <hi>T.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 358. <hi>Edit. Petav.</hi> This Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is very antient, for <hi>Marcion</hi> (one of the firſt that defended our Saviour's Pre-exiſtence; and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that Doctrine, corrupted this Text) flouriſhed about the Year 150. But after the Nicene Council, 'tis no wonder that many Trinitarians fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed (in this Text) the Copies of <hi>Marcion,</hi> as being then near 200 Years old; and it was after the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Council, that all the Verſions and Fathers to whom Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals concerning this Text, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>But to confirm farther the Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of the WORD, or Son of God, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> dares pretend that 'tis<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53124:30"/>a part of the Jewiſh <hi>Cabbala,</hi> or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Knowledg, which that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion derived from <hi>Moſes,</hi> he from God. Hereupon he cites ſome Words of the (Apocryphal) <hi>Wiſdom of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> which (according to him) is a very autient Book; alſo ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>Philo Judaeus,</hi> ſuppoſed to be a Jew by Religion as well as by Nation. He appeals alſo to the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee Paraphraſes (or Tranſlations of the Old Teſtament by
<hi>Onkelos</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi>) as if theſe ſpake of the WORD, as a Perſon, and the great Meſſenger of God, under the Old Teſtament: And finally, he ſays, <hi>Maſius</hi> (on <hi>Joſhua</hi>) has quoted a certain Rabbi, and an old Jewiſh Book called <hi>Tanchumam,</hi> which ſpeak of the WORD much after the manner as doth the Author of the
<hi>Wiſdom of</hi> Solomon.</p>
               <p>He ſaith firſt, that the Pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of the WORD, as a Divine Almighty Perſon, and as the Son of God, is a part of the Jewiſh
<hi>Cabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> or traditional Knowledg: Then, to prove this, he cites Paſſages out of <hi>Philo,</hi> the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Paraphraſes of <hi>Onkelos</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> a certain Rabbi, and the Book <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumam.</hi> He thinks, it ſhould ſeem, that theſe Jewiſh Writers had their Notion of the WORD, from the Jewiſh
<hi>Cabbala.</hi> I cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I coufeſs, that a Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſhould believe the Jewiſh <hi>Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bala;</hi> or think that the Jews had <hi>a traditional Knowledg</hi> or Inſtitution, concerning God and Religion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets. I had thought, that all Proteſtants, nay all Chriſtians, were agreed, that the <hi>Cabbala</hi> is the Invention of the Phariſees and Maſters of the Phariſaical Sect, not a Trudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Moſes.</hi> If the
<hi>Cabala</hi> had come from <hi>Moſes;</hi> or had it been acknowledged by the Prophets and antient Jewiſh Church, as of Divine Revelation and Inſtitution: it would have been often mentioned, appeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and alluded to, in the Books of the Old Teſtament; and there is no queſtion that <hi>Ezra</hi> (when he made the Collection of Canonical Books and Monuments, immediately after the Return from the Babyloniſh Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity) would have had an eſpecial Care of the Divine <hi>Cabala,</hi> or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Knowledg. He would have committed it to Writing, leſt it ſhould be loſt or corrupted: He would have added it to the Canon of Scripture, when he collected all other Pieces that had been written by the Prophets, or other holy Men; He that has left to us the Proverbs of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> his Book of Love, nay the Story of
<hi>Ruth,</hi> would not have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the Divine <hi>Cabala.</hi> But I ſhall put this Dilemma to Dr. <hi>Bull;</hi> let him take it by which Horn he likes beſt. Either the <hi>Cabala</hi> of the Jews is of <hi>humane Invention,</hi> or of <hi>divine Appointment and Revelation.</hi> If the former, why has he quoted (in ſo great a Queſtion as this now before us) a ſpurious Work, an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, an impious (Phariſaical) Addition to the Holy Scripture: will ſuch fraudulent Arts as theſe, help or
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53124:30"/>credit his Cauſe? If the other, if the <hi>Cabala</hi> is a Tradition of Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and Inſtitution; 'tis of equal Authority with the Writings of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets; and Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ought to bind it up, with the other two Parts of Holy Scripture, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Old and New Teſtaments. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> may do as he pleaſes; but the Socinians acquieſce in that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which our Saviour himſelf has made of the <hi>Cabala,</hi> at <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.6,9. where he calls this Traditional Law, <hi>the Commandments of Men,</hi> a mere humane (Phariſaical) Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; he adds there, that by this Tradition of theirs they contradicted and <hi>made void</hi> the true and genuine <hi>Commandments of God.</hi> It is in vain therefore that Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> tells us of a <hi>Cabala</hi> of the Jews; of which he (precariouſly, and without having read it, or ſo much as knowing what it is) ſuppoſes, that it not only ſpeaks of the WORD, but ſpeaks of it as <hi>a Perſon</hi> and <hi>the Son of God:</hi> and afterwards, falls to citing ſome Jewiſh Authors; who from this <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bala</hi> (as he again untruly ſuppoſes) diſcourſe of the WORD<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent Perſon, the Son of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and God's Meſſenger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſter during the times of the Old Teſtament. I ſay, this Pretence of Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is vain, becauſe ſuppoſing the <hi>Cabala</hi> did ſpeak of the WORD, as a Perſon and the Son of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent to the Creation it ſelf; and ſuppoſing again, that the Jewiſh Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors (whom he cites) had taken their Doctrine from the <hi>Cabala:</hi> yet what will all this avail, when the
<hi>Cabala</hi> it ſelf is (ſo certainly) not a Tradition from
<hi>Moſes</hi> or God; but a (mad) Collection of Follies and Chimeras, the ſickly Dreams of the (Fanatical) Phariſees.</p>
               <p>The Jewiſh <hi>Cabala</hi> is ſo far from owning a Trinity, that this very Doctrine of (Apoſtate) Chriſtians, is the chief Offence that the Jews take at the Chriſtian Religion: it is the great thing that their learned Men (in all Books and Conferences) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to us, that we have departed from the firſt Commandment, and have advanced a ſecond and a third God. Farther, they as little believe the WORD, when taken (in the Platonick Senſe, namely) for a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; or that God has a Son, who was his Miniſter in the Creation of all things, and his Meſſenger or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel to the Patriarchs. In ſhort, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now nor formerly have the Jews believed, that the WORD is the Son of God, but only his Power, Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and Virtue. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> will never produce any thing of the <hi>Cabala,</hi> that but looks this way. And ſee here, what <hi>Origen,</hi> who flouriſhed about the Year 270 fays of the Jews;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"I have diſputed often, <hi>ſays this moſt Learned Father,</hi> with the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Rabbins that were of moſt Eſteem; but I could never meet with any of them, who approve this Doctrine, that
<hi>the WORD is the Son of God:</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Contr. Celſum, l.</hi> 2.
<hi>p.</hi> 79. Again, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 162. he is more expreſs in the caſe;
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"<hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> is ignorant that the Jews do
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53124:31"/>not believe, that the Meſſias (or Chriſt) whom they ſtill expect as to come, is not God, nor the <hi>Son of God.</hi>
                  </q> But Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> himſelf, tho here (to ſerve the preſent turn) he contends that the Jewiſh <hi>Cabala</hi> ſpeaks of the WORD as a Perſon and the Son of God, elſewhere (<hi>Judic. Eccl. p.</hi> 170.) owns and proves, that
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"the Jews do not expect any Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as or Chriſt, promiſed to them by their Prophets, but who ſhall be <hi>a mere Man.</hi>
                  </q> And he cites <hi>Tripho</hi> the Jew, ſaying,
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"We Jews expect a Chriſt, who is a Man, born of Men.</q> But if this was the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Jews concerning Chriſt, that he ſhall be a Man only; why does Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> pretend in this Place, that the <hi>Cabala</hi> (or Traditional Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Jews) which by them is ſuppoſed to be of Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, teaches the contrary, namely that the Chriſt is to be a Divine Perſon, the eternal Son of God, and himſelf alſo God? He will never reconcile theſe Contradictions to himſelf. But let us now examine, of what Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity his Quotations, out of ſome Jewiſh Books, are.</p>
               <p>His firſt Citation is out of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal Book of Wiſdom;
<hi>Wiſd.</hi> 18.15,16.
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"Thy Almighty WORD leap'd down from Heaven, out of his Royal Throne; as a fierce Man of War, into a Land deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Deſtruction. He brought thine unfeigned Commandment, as a ſharp Sword; and ſtanding up, filled all things with Death: he touched the Heaven, tho he ſtood upon the Earth.</q> In ſober Sadneſs, this was a terrible WORD: his Feet ſtood on plain Ground, and yet his Head touched (not the Clouds or the Aether, but) Heaven it ſelf; and with his Death-dealing Fauchion, he even depopulated the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in a few Minutes. 'Tis ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent however, I ſuppoſe, to ſober People, if we ſay hereupon, that this ſame was only a Chimerical, not a real <hi>Almanzor;</hi> and that there is no Body but Dr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> that will ever be afraid of his Puiſſance. But Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> objects, that however this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſerves to ſhow, that the Author of the Book of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> who was a Jew, believed the WORD. Right, but then he ſhould have obſerved too, that the Book as we now have it, muſt be as much reckoned to the Tranſlator who was a Chriſtian, as to the firſt Writer of it, who (it may be) was a Jew. Let us hear
<hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> in his Preface to his Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on this Book:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Book of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> was written by a Jew, who lived after the times of <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra:</hi> but ſome Chriſtian or other (who was a Greek) hapning on it, he hath given it us in the Greek Tongue, but with divers Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to it, taken from the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion.</q> Of this kind, no Man will doubt it, is this Deſcription of the WORD, which is wholly Chriſtian, as Chriſtianity began to be taught about the middle of the ſecond Age: the Jews, as we have heard from <hi>Origen,</hi> never believed ſuch a kind of WORD; namely, <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53124:31"/>that is a Perſon, the Son of God, or God.</p>
               <p>His next Allegation is from the Paraphraſes of
<hi>Onkelos</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> Jews that tranſlated the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into Syro-Chaldaick, after a Paraphraſtical way. But I cannot perceive, that any of his Citations out of theſe Paraphraſes ſpeak of the WORD in the Platonick Senſe; namely, as a Perſon, or as a God: but only in the Jewiſh and Socinian Senſe; namely, as the Energy and Power of God, or God's <hi>powerful effectual Mandate.</hi> As to his laſt Quotation, from a Paraphraſe of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> on the Pſalms; which has ſome Appearance of being to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for which Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> alledged it: whereas
<hi>Jonathan</hi> ſeems to read, <hi>the Lord ſaid to his WORD, Sit on my right Hand; Jonathan</hi>'s Words may better be rendred thus, <hi>the Lord ſaid by his WORD,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> his Mandate or Decree) <hi>Sit on my right Hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Philo</hi> ſpeaks home; he (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly) calls the WORD <hi>the Son of God,</hi> his <hi>firſt-begotten Son:</hi> to whoſe Care (ſaith he farther) as to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius and Deputy of God, the whole Creation is committed; and by whom it was originally made. But I ſhall never believe, that a Jew by Religion, wrote thoſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the WORD, that we ſee in <hi>Philo</hi>'s Works. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſuſpects,
<hi>Photius</hi> directly affirms, that <hi>Philo</hi> was a Chriſtian. This laſt adds, that by occaſion of ſome Diſpleaſure ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<hi>Philo</hi> departed from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. I believe, with
<hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> and <hi>Photius,</hi> that <hi>Philo</hi> was a Chriſtian: but I make no queſtion, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> is miſtaken in thinking, that this is the <hi>Philo</hi> who was ſent on an Ambaſſage to the Emperor <hi>C. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula;</hi> but a <hi>Philo</hi> of the ſecond Age, toward the expiring of it, or of the 2<hi>d</hi> Age juſt expiring. For he deſcribes the <hi>Therapeutae,</hi> that is the Chriſtians, both in their Diſcipline, their Studies, and their manner of interpreting Holy Scripture; not as they lived or were in the Apoſtolick Times, but in the Cloſe of the ſecond (and Beginning of the third) Age.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as to the (obſcure) Rabbi cited by
<hi>Maſius,</hi> and the (unknown) Book <hi>Tankumam,</hi> enough has been ſaid to evince that if they ſpeak of the WORD as the Son of God, they may be written perhaps in Rabbinical Hebrew, and by Jews by Nation, but ſuch Jews as were come over to the Chriſtian Religion; there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more certain than that the Jews never owned a Son of God in any other Senſe but of Adoption, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Exaltation, and ſuch like; nor do I think, that Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> himſelf will again inſiſt on Jewiſh Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whether they be theſe or any other. He ſhould make himſelf ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to all learned Men, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering in ſuch a notorious Miſtake as this; that the Jews either now, or in any time paſt, believed the WORD as a Perſon, or that God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat a Son, who was pre-exiſtent to the World, and was (together with God) the Creator of it: 'tis for this very Doctrine, that the Jews have<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53124:32"/>pretended ever ſince the Council of
<hi>Nice,</hi> and at this <hi>day</hi> do pretend, that Chriſtianity is a Revolt to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm and Paganiſm.</p>
               <p>There remains now but one thing more in Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s
<hi>Defence of the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Faith,</hi> that I intend to conſider in this
<hi>firſt Part</hi> of my Anſwer to him; his Explication of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: or how three Divine Perſons and Spirits, each of which has all Divine Perfections, and is ſingly and by <hi>himſelf</hi> God, nay
<hi>perfect</hi> God, are (for all that) but one God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>On the Explication of the Trinity, according to the Fathers and Dr. <hi>Bull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THAT <hi>three</hi> Divine Spirits and Perſons, each of which has all poſſible (real) Perfections, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is (ſingly and by himſelf, as the Athanaſian Creed ſpeaks) a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect God, are but one God, is ſo monſtrous a Paradox; that we might juſtly wonder, ſuch a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory and impoſſible Doctrine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (unhappily) got abroad, was not immediately hiſſed again, into the Hole, from whence the
<hi>Chimera</hi> firſt ſallied; did we not know, that the Propagation and Conſervation of this Affront to common Senſe, and to all the Principles of Knowledg and Silence, was the Work and Effect of ſuch <hi>penal Laws,</hi> as would equally have reſtored the whole Body and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of Paganiſm. While the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion about the Trinity was diſputed, only <hi>by Argument</hi> and
<hi>Authorities of Holy Scripture;</hi> the Proverb was, <hi>all the World is againſt</hi> Athanaſius, <hi>and</hi> Athanaſius <hi>is againſt all the World.</hi> And in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> it ſelf, the then capital City of the whole Roman Empire, the Trinitarian <hi>Conventicle</hi> was ſo thin, that it had more Benches than Men to fit on them: and their Preacher was forced to comfort his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt empty Fold with ſuch Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Unitaries, <hi>ſays he,</hi> have the Churches, but we <hi>(we Trinitarians)</hi> are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of God; they have the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but the Angels are with us: my Flock indeed is little, I eaſily tell all my Sheep; but they hear my Voice, they follow me, and will not follow Strangers.</q> 
                  <hi>Greg. Nazianz.</hi> Serm. 35. againſt the Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But the Empire falling at length to a Prince, who was a bigotted Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarian; he applied the Imperial Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and the Awe of his Armies, which comfilied (for the moſt part) of Souldiers and Officers who had been born (bred and continued) Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, to eſtabliſh Trinitarianiſm by Terrors and Force. He ('twas <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi>) and his Succeſſors began with taking the Churches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in all Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,
<hi>by military Force:</hi> then they were prohibited to hold their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, Conventicles they were now <pb n="63" facs="tcp:53124:32"/>called, within the Preciucts of Cities or Towns. Next, he called general Councils, but admitted none to Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Vote but Trinitarians: to whoſe Creeds and Canons, all that ſtood for any (the very leaſt) Church-Preferment, muſt ſubſcribe, before they were admitted to their Places. Afterwards, all Diſputes againſt the Deciſions of theſe Councils were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to all without Exception: to Churchmen and military Officers, on pain of Depoſition; to Lay-men, if they were free, under the Penalty of Baniſhment; to Servants, under pain of corporal Chaſtiſement, and that too (ſaith the Law)
<hi>after the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt manner.</hi> They proceeded far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they required all Perſons, to deliver up all Heretical Books, that they might be publickly burnt; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing horrible Puniſhments to ſuch as ſhould preſume to hide or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal any ſuch Books. While the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power acted his Part in this (out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious) manner, the Eccleſiaſticks were as induſtrious another way: the Underlings of them ſought the Favour of their Superiours, by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Informers againſt the Hereticks and their Aſſemblies; others (that could read and write) took upon them the corrupting, or as they then ſpoke, <hi>the correcting</hi> the Bibles; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and leaving out as themſelves pleaſed. Nor would they have left to us, any Remain of genuine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; or ſuffer'd a ſingle Unitarian to eſcape their Barbarities: but that their Diviſions concerning their own Doctrine, their own Diſputes <hi>de Aſini umbrâ,</hi> diverted often their Rage and Treachery, from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the Unitaries, to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their own Party and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Dares Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> or any other, deny any thing of this? when they do, this (and much more) ſhall be proved upon them, from the moſt allowed of their own Hiſtorians, and from <hi>the Codes</hi> which contain the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>We may ſay then, that Trinitaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm is not ſo much a Religion, as the Law of the <hi>Bizantine</hi> (or
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitan</hi>) Emperors; it was firſt introduced by military Force, then confirmed by Edicts of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Emperors of
<hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Well, but when Folly and Impiety are once eſtabliſh'd by Law, and are the only way to Preferment, there will never want a great Number, who will court the Favour of the Government, by endeavouring to repreſent the current Doctrine of the Times, as poſſible, nay as reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and agreeable to Scripture: and from hence came the Explications of the Trinity, by <hi>the Paraſites</hi> of thoſe times; whom now, in regard of their Antiquity, we call <hi>the Fathers,</hi> Theſe Explications were various, and contrary to one another; Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has made choice of the moſt tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and paſſable Accounts given by the Fathers: and tho he has patched up one Hypotheſis (or Explication) out of many and divers, I will be content to take it, as he gives it. He repreſents it, as the ordinary Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of all the Fathers; as well
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53124:33"/>the Ante-nicene as Poſt-nicene: let us ſee what it is, and then make our Reflections upon it.</p>
               <p>They ſaid, there are <hi>three</hi> infinite Perſons, known by the Names of Father, Son, and Holy Spirit; each of which has all Divine Perfections, and in their <hi>higheſt</hi> Degree. They are ſo many
<hi>diſtinct,</hi> tho not <hi>divided</hi> or ſeparated Subſtances and Eſſences: they are as much three Spirits, as they are three Subſtances and Perſons; each has his own proper and perſonal di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Underſtanding, Will, and (Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty) Energy. It is true, that they ſaid alſo, that the three Divine Perſons are conſubſtantial, or have <hi>the ſame</hi> Subſtance: but they did not mean thereby <hi>the ſelf-ſame</hi> Subſtance, or the ſame Subſtance <hi>in Number,</hi> but the ſame for Kind and Properties; that is, their Subſtances are (alike) Divine, Immortal, and Unchangable. They are conſubſtantial to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Stars are conſubſtantial to Stars; that is, their Subſtances, tho divers in Number, have the ſame Properties and Qualities. In ſhort, the Father, Son and Spirit, are <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> (intellectual) Subſtances; and are conſubſtantial (or of <hi>the ſame</hi> Subſtance) as their Subſtances or Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences are alike infinite, immutable and immortal: they are alſo (and therefore) diſtinct <hi>Beings;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are intellectual and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, they are three <hi>Minds</hi> and three
<hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> as much as they are three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Subſtances. Laſtly, becauſe each has all poſſible (real) Perfections, therefore each of them is <hi>true God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dare to affirm before-hand, that Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is ſo well ſatisfied, that this is the Notion that the Fathers had of the Trinity, that he will own it for theirs and his, and will not (diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly) deny that he intended this Explication or Account of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the ſeveral Chapters of his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Nicene Faith,</hi> where he ſpeaks (either deſignedly or inciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally) of this Point. And his Book has given him ſuch a Reputation all over <hi>Europe,</hi> even in the Catholick Countries; and his Citations out of the Fathers, ſo plainly evince, that this was their Senſe; that (I believe) no Trinitarian will be ſo raſh or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to call him Heretick, or to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack or write againſt him as ſuch; tho others (of leſs Eſteem) are now loudly challenged of Hereſy, for this very Explication. In very deed, it is the Doctrine of the (Poſt-nicene) Fathers, and of all the <hi>real</hi> Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians: and ſince the Revival of theſe Controverſies, divers learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (by Name Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Mr. <hi>How,</hi> and others) imbrace this Notion of the Trinity. 'Tis not unlikely, that (by degrees) it will exclude the (Sabellian Nominal) Trinity of the Schools; and not only exclude it, but be the Occaſion that it ſhall be declared
<hi>Heretical.</hi> 'Tis true, that more commonly in Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, they go the way of the Schools; but the ſcholaſtick Trinity implies ſo many Follies, and is ſo certainly nothing elſe but a diſguiſed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53124:33"/>Sabellianiſm: that <hi>the real</hi> Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians may probably enough carry their Point againſt the Nominals; if the Difference between them, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out into a Contention, ſhall fall into the Hands of able Managers.</p>
               <p>We have ſeen how the Fathers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Trinity; but the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty is ſtill behind: how did they make out the Unity of God? For if there are three ſpiritual intellectual <hi>Subſtances,</hi> three infinite <hi>Spirits,</hi> three (eternal, all-knowing and all-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful)
<hi>Minds,</hi> Three, each of which is a <hi>perfect God:</hi> do we not loſe the Unity of God, the principal Article of revealed Religion, and the grand Deſign of both the Teſtaments, while we believe and affirm three ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> here offers his Hand, at a dead lift; he tells us, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eaſily came off from this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or Doubt, by ſaying,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Son and Spirit had their Original, their Being, and Godhead, from the Father: therefore having proceeded from him as their Principle and Fountain, they are not diſtinct Gods from him, but one God with him. The Fathers granted, that were not the Son and Spirit origina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Father, the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons being ſo many <hi>ſeveral Principles,</hi> would alſo be ſo many <hi>Gods:</hi> but becauſe the Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are not (as the Father) ſelf-origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated or unoriginated, but from the Father; therefore they are rightly ſaid to be one God with him.</p>
               <p>Every one ſees, that there lies this Exception, againſt this Account of the Unity of God. If to be origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from the Father, will make the Perſons ſo originated to be one God with him, or one with him and with one another; it follows, that not only the Son and Holy Spirit, but Angels alſo and Men (nay the whole Creation, the very vileſt Parts of it) ſhall be one God with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with the (pretended) Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and one with one another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are all originated from the Father. Therefore the Fathers ſaid,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Bare Origination</hi> from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will not conſtitute the Perſons ſo originated one God (or one) with him, or with one another, unleſs they <hi>have the ſame Subſtance with the Father;</hi> that is, as has been ſaid, <hi>the ſame for Kind and Properties.</hi> And this Confideration, they ſaid, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes <hi>all Creatures</hi> from being one God or one with the Father, or the bleſſed Trinity: for <hi>created</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are finite, ſubject to Change and Accidents. In a word, they are <hi>wholly unlike to the Divine Subſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They foreſaw, that it would be again objected here. If to be origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from another, who is <hi>of the ſame kind</hi> with the Perſons ſo origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from him, will make them all to be one; for Inſtance, will make the Son and Spirit to be truly one, and one God, with the Father from whom they are originated: then two Sons, or a Son and Grandſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are originated from the ſame Father, and are <hi>of the ſame kind</hi> with him, ſhall alſo be one with him; they ſhall not be three <hi>Men,</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:53124:34"/>but one <hi>Man,</hi> as Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, are not three Gods, but one God. To wind themſelves from this moſt certain and ſolid Reaſoning, the Fathers deviſed a third Eluſion, as wiſe as either of the two former: they ſaid that,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Origination of two Perſons from a firſt Perſon, tho they are all <hi>of the ſame kind,</hi> will not make them one, or one God; except (as it moſt luckily happens between the three Divine Perſons) the originated Perſons are propagated <hi>interiori pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductione:</hi> that is, are generated by an internal Production, ſo that they are (always and inſeparably) in the Perſon that produced them. And this at length is the Fathers whole Explication of a Trinity in Unity. They ſaid, in ſhort, three diſtinct Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons, Subſtances, Spirits, each of which is (ſingly and by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) a perfect God, are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding but one God; becauſe the ſecond and third Perſons <hi>are origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from the firſt,</hi> and are <hi>of the ſame Kind and Properties with him,</hi> and are generated or propagated <hi>by an internal Production,</hi> ſo that they inſeparably and always <hi>remain in the Father, and he in them.</hi> This, in effect, is to ſay; that naturally, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and truly ſpeaking, there are three Gods, or there are <hi>three Gods in Number:</hi> but in regard that God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, are <hi>of the ſame kind</hi> with God the Father, are
<hi>originated from him,</hi> and are eternally and inſeparably <hi>in him;</hi> they may (in a Catachreſtical, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper and reſpective Senſe) all be called one God.</p>
               <p>I will examine very particularly, the whole Hypotheſis of theſe Fathers, their Trinity of Subſtances, Minds and Spirits; and their Explication (now laid down) how three ſuch Perſons and (Divine) Minds can be but one God? Only for preventing (if it may be) future Cavils, I would firſt take notice, that <hi>this Explication</hi> of the Unity of God (or how
<hi>three</hi> Perſons can be but one God) by the Fathers and Dr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> evidently ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, that they held the three Divine Perſons are ſo many diſtinct Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Minds, and Spirits, as well as diſtinct Perſons.</p>
               <p>I think, 'tis ſufficient, to prove that the Fathers held the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſo many diſtinct <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Minds,</hi> in that they ſo certainly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed them to be <hi>diſtinct ſpiritual Subſtances:</hi> if the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are three diſtinct Subſtances, all Men (the very nominal Trinitarians themſelves) will grant, that they are diſtinct Minds and Spirits. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath inconteſtably proved, by a great Number of Quotations, and might have proved by a great many more; that by conſubſtantial, or <hi>of the ſame Subſtance,</hi> the Fathers meant not the ſame Subſtance <hi>in Number,</hi> but the ſame <hi>in Properties.</hi> As Stars are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial to Stars, and the Bodies of Men to the Bodies of Beaſts; becauſe they are Subſtances <hi>of the ſame kind</hi> (that is, corporeal) and <hi>of the ſame Properties,</hi> for all Stars are
<hi>lucid,</hi> and the Bodies of Men and Beaſts are <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganized,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:53124:34"/>and <hi>ſubject to Alteration:</hi> So are the three Divine Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial, being of the ſame kind, that is to ſay <hi>ſpiritual;</hi> and having the ſame Properties, namely Eternity, Immutability, Omnipreſence, and the other Divine Attributes. I will undertake for it, that none of the Nominal Trinitarians (as angry as ſome of them are) will ever attempt to confute Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s firſt Chapter of his ſecond Section; where he gives this Account of the word Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, out of the Fathers. But if the Divine Perſons are therefore Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial, becauſe they are of like kind, and have the ſame Properties; their Subſtance is not <hi>the ſame in Number,</hi> but only (as Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>the ſame in Nature.</hi> And if this be true, as inconteſtably it is, that the Fathers believed the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be ſo many <hi>diſtinct</hi> ſpiritual Subſtances in Number: it will be controverted by no Body, that they are alſo (in the Judgment of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) <hi>diſtinct</hi> Minds and Spirits.</p>
               <p>Secondly; But (as I ſaid) the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned Explications of the Unity of God, or how the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons are yet but one God, are another, and an invincible Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that they held the ſaid Perſons are three Minds, Spirits and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. If the Fathers had held, that the three Perſons are but one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (numerical) Subſtance, one infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Spirit, one omniſcient Mind and Energy; and that they are called Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, only becauſe the one (numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal) Subſtance ſubſiſts
<hi>in three Modes,</hi> that is, <hi>after three ſeveral manners:</hi> I ſay, if this had been the Opinion of the Fathers, the Queſtion would not have been, how the <hi>three</hi> Perſons can be but one God, but <hi>how they can be called Hypoſtaſes or Perſons?</hi> As at this day, no Man is ſo fooliſh, as to charge the Nominal Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with Tritheiſm, or holding three Gods; but only with <hi>Gotham</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Divinity, in calling <hi>Modes</hi> (or a Subſtance ſubſiſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter three manners) <hi>Perſons,</hi> when it is ſo obvious that Modes are not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but certain Affections and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Denominations belonging to Perſons. The Fathers would never have troubled themſelves, nor would any ever have objected it to them, or demanded it of them; how they could ſay there is but one God, if the three Perſons (by them ſo called) were but one (numerical) Subſtance ſubſiſting three manner of ways, or in three relative Modes: all the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (as I ſaid) would have been, what they meant by this Gibberiſh, <hi>ſubſiſting in three Modes or three man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ways?</hi> What Occaſion was there for the Fathers to tell us, the three Divine Perſons may be called one God; becauſe the Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are originated from the Father, are like to him in all Divine Properties, and ſubſiſt in him: what need, I ſay, was there of theſe Excuſes, or how are they poſſibly applicable to the three Divine Perſons; if the Perſons were not taken to be ſo many Spirits, Minds and Subſtances, but only a threefold manner of Subſiſtence of<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53124:35"/>the ſame (numerical) Subſtance, Mind and Spirit?</p>
               <p>I omit (for the preſent) a great deal that might be farther ſaid on this Subject; becauſe when the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Trinitarians have called, till they are hoarſe, weary and aſham'd, to Univerſities and Biſhops to eſpouſe their Cauſe, and to cenſure the real Trinitarians: after all, the very Names by which the three Divine Perſons are called (<hi>a</hi> Father, <hi>his</hi> Son, an Holy Spirit diſtinct from both) do ſo manifeſtly imply thoſe Perſons to be diſtinct Beings, Subſtances, Minds and Spirits, and not Modes or Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only of the ſelf ſame numerical Being and Spirit; that it will always be carried againſt them, by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority of conſidering Divines. All their Appeals notwithſtanding, it will not be long, e're they are told by their Superiors in the Church, that
'tis expedient for them to be quiet, left themſelves be cenſured as Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, or as we now ſpeak Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. To ſum up all, I ſay, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beld that the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are three diſtinct (ſpiritual, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual) Subſtances, three Minds, three Spirits: this appears, ſay I far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>by their Explications of the word Conſubſtantial;</hi> by their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to this Queſtion, <hi>how three ſuch Perſons can be but one God;</hi> and by the Terms which they uſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the three Perſons, <hi>a Father, his Son, a Spirit diſtinct from both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things being, I ſuppoſe, ſufficiently eſtabliſh'd, we may rely on it, that Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> will not deny that I have truly reported what the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (the Poſt-nicene Fathers ſay I, but Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſays <hi>all</hi> the Fathers) held, both concerning the three Divine Perſons, and how we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them to be but one God. Therefore now, I will examine his whole Hypotheſis; it hath theſe Parts. 1. There are three Divine Hypoſtaſes, or <hi>intellectual Subſtances,</hi> three ommſcient almighty <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> each of theſe has all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections, and is ſingly and by himſelf a moſt compleat and perfect God. 2. Yet doth not this contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict that moſt great and indiſputable Truth, viſible in the Works of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and aſcertained by Revelation of holy Scripture; that there is but one God: becauſe of the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Hypoſtaſes and Spirits before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, the ſecond and third are ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginated from the firſt; have the ſame Nature and Properties, that he has; and are propagated from him by an internal Production, ſo that they are always inſeparably in him, and he in them, by a mutual Pervaſion, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meation or Penetration.</p>
               <p>There is no neceſſity that I ſhould concern my ſelf, againſt the firſt of theſe Propoſitions; for if I diſprove the ſecond, the firſt will fall of it ſelf: if <hi>three</hi> Hypoſtaſes or Spirits cannot be one God, this ſort of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians muſt either give up their three diſtinct Subſtances, their three Minds and Spirits; or openly profeſs, that they believe three Gods. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, it will not be amiſs, or beſides our Purpoſe, if we ſhow<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53124:35"/>theſe Gentlemen, that whatever Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments militate againſt a Plurality of Gods, prove alſo (no leſs effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and directly) that there can be but one Divine (intellectual) Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but one infinite Spirit and Mind.</p>
               <p>How do Philoſophers and Divines eſtabliſh the Unity of God; or, that there neither is, nor can be more than one God? They ſay; all Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Beings of the ſame kind and ſort, is from the Imbecillity, Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Unſufficiency (in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect or other) of thoſe Beings: for if a Being be abſolutely perfect, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in all Perfections, all-ſufficient for it ſelf, and for the Beings to which it relates; there is no need, that it ſhould be multiplied, or be more than one. We ſee, ſay they, that all Nature has nothing that is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, nothing in vain; where-ever one of the ſort is ſufficient, as one <hi>Sun</hi> and ſuch like, the Individuals of that kind never proceed beyond Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But the Divine Nature, as the moſt excellent of all, will much more exclude all Multiplicity: more <hi>Infinites,</hi> more <hi>All ſufficients,</hi> would be ſuch an impertinent Repetition, ſo altogether vain and to no purpoſe, that we cannot think of it, without immediately rejecting it. This is the firſt Argument, uſed by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, to prove the Unity of God; no Body will conteſt it, that it equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proves but one infinite <hi>Spirit,</hi> one all-ſufficient <hi>Mind,</hi> one abſolutely perfect
<hi>Being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They ſay again; it implies a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, that there ſhould be more than one all-ſufficient God, Mind or Spirit; becauſe ſuch a Suppoſition pretends to make an infinite Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (of the ſame kind) to what is (already) infinite, and to increaſe All-ſufficiency.</p>
               <p>And, if there are more Gods, or more Minds and Spirits, infinite in their Perfections, either they are all of them unoriginated; or one only is unoriginated, and the reſt are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him by Generation or Creation. The Trinitarians, with whom we have now to do, anſwer; that only one, the Father, is unorigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, the other Perſons are propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated from him. But they can never anſwer, either why the Father ſhould propagate from himſelf, only two Spirits as perfect as himſelf; or why, ſeeing thoſe two are as perfect as he, <hi>they</hi> alſo ſhould not generate their like? If the two propagated Perſons and Spirits <hi>cannot</hi> generate their like; they are not ſuch perfect Beings as the Father is: and conſequently are neither Gods, nor abſolutely perfect Spirits. If it be ſaid only, they <hi>will not</hi> generate their like, becauſe three abſolutely perfect Spirits are enough; 'tis not only frivolous, but ſilly: for if <hi>three</hi> perfect Spirits are more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by one another, or more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the World than <hi>one</hi> ſuch Spirit or Mind, by an unavoidable Parity of Reaſon, ſeven or ten Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Minds, that are all-ſufficient and abſolutely perfect, muſt be more deſirable, and more requiſite to the World than Three. Again,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53124:36"/>It was <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that obſerved, and 'tis an Obſervation worthy of ſo great a Man; that the Unity of God is diſcernable in the Conſtitution and Frame of the World. For ſuch is the Uniformity and good Order of the whole; and all the Parts (both in their
<hi>Qualities</hi> and <hi>Motions</hi>) ſo manifeſtly tend to one and the ſame End, namely the Service of Man, and the Conſervation of the World it ſelf in its preſent State; moreover, theſe Parts continue in their firſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Courſe, ſo <hi>ſtedfaſtly</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variably: that it appears they were contrived, and are regulated, not by more Gods, Makers, or Almighty Spirits, but by one only Law and Mind.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, that there is an all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God; we prove beyond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, by that perpetual Wiſdom, Contrivance and good Senſe, which is ſeen in the <hi>Whole</hi> and the <hi>Parts</hi> of the World; and which muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the World and its Parts, elſe how came (blind unthinking) Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into ſuch a <hi>wiſe</hi> Order? But we have no manner of Proof, not the leaſt Intimation, that there are more ſuch Gods; as undoubtedly there would be, both in Nature and by Revelation, if indeed there were more ſuch.</p>
               <p>Theſe Reaſons have always per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded all Philoſophers and Divines, that there is but one (ſupreme and infinite) <hi>God;</hi> and they proceed as directly againſt more infinite <hi>all-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> and
<hi>creating</hi> Spirits or Minds, as againſt more Gods. In very deed, there never was any Philoſopher that made any Diſtinction, between three
<hi>Gods</hi> and three infinite <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Spirits:</hi> he would have been eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not in his right Senſes, by the Philoſophers, who ſhould talk of <hi>one</hi> God and <hi>three</hi> infinite all-perfect Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; with them, one God, and one all-perfect Spirit were convertible Terms, and uſed for each other; and indeed they ever will be, by all that conſider what they ſay.</p>
               <p>But Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> and the Fathers whom he follows, are perſwaded; that tho all Nature and Reaſon are againſt it, yet 'tis a Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there are three infinite (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual)
<hi>Subſtances,</hi> three all-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Spirits,</hi> three all-ſufficient <hi>Minds:</hi> and that they may be ſaid to be but one God, on the Accounts before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given; and which I will now exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. He, and his Fathers ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſecond and third Minds are originated from the firſt; the Son and Spirit have their Being, Life and Godhead from the Father: therefore they are one God with him. There never was a more abſurd thing ſaid by Men. They pretend to prove the Unity, or declare the Unity; by what is the firſt Cauſe of Diſtinction, Diverſity, and ſeparate Exiſtence. God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, are propagated, from God the Father; therefore they are <hi>one</hi> God with him: no Friends, no; therefore they are <hi>ſeparate</hi> Beings, and <hi>diſtinct</hi> Gods, from him; as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſeparate as Cauſe and Effect can be, which is the very <hi>firſt</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions.<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53124:36"/>and the
<hi>Ground and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of all ſubſequent Diſtinction.</p>
               <p>And what kind of God have theſe Gentlemen deviſed? A God who is, in one part of his Compoſition, in that part which they call <hi>the Father,</hi> unoriginated; but in his two other Parts, the Son and Spirit, not only originated <hi>as to his Godhead;</hi> but as <hi>to his very Being and Life.</hi> To ſay, as Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> and the Fathers do, that the Son and Spirit have their <hi>Being, Life</hi> and <hi>Godhead</hi> from the Father, or are originated in reſpect of all theſe from the Father; implies that they differ from the Father as <hi>prior</hi> and <hi>poſterior,</hi> former and latter: for the originated Spirits (or Parts of God) muſt of neceſſity be
<hi>poſterior</hi> (latter or poſtnate) to that Spirit (or part of him) from which they are origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated; the very term <hi>Origination</hi> is a Confeſſion of <hi>a natural Poſteriority,</hi> which cannot be in God. To grant to our Oppoſers that Diſtinction of theirs, <hi>prior</hi> in Nature and <hi>prior</hi> in Time; they cannot thereby ſecure their Cauſe: for if the Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are originated, as to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Being, Life and Godhead, from the Father; they are <hi>poſterior in Nature</hi> to him, and therefore can neither be God, nor eſſential Parts of him. <hi>Poſterior in Nature</hi> (or poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate) is as incompatible to God, as <hi>poſterior in Time;</hi> for it implies an <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to him, and a
<hi>Change</hi> in him. If there be ſomething in God, that is <hi>poſterior in Nature,</hi> to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in God; then the whole of God is not
<hi>connate,</hi> there has been a Change and Acceſſion in him: which becauſe our Oppoſers dare not ſay, neither ought they to ſay the other; namely, that there is ſomewhat in God, that is <hi>poſterior in Nature</hi> to ſomewhat elſe in him; and yet to give up that, they know, is to give up their Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But themſelves, that they may not ſeem ſtark Fools, take notice; that if to be originated from the Father, will make the Son and Spirit to be one God with the Father; the whole Creation, the very vileſt parts of it, ſhall be one God with him, becauſe they are originated from him; that is, they give up this firſt Solution or Explication of the Unity; and they alledg, in the next Place, after this manner;</p>
               <p n="2">2. We do not affirm, that <hi>bare</hi> Origination from God, can make the Perſons ſo originated, to be one God with him: but only when they are <hi>ſo</hi> originated from God; as to have the ſame (ſpecifick) Subſtance and Properties that he hath; that is, when the originated Perſons have, like him, immortal, unchangable Subſtances; and are omniſcient, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, and the reſt that God is. As who ſhould ſay; we make it out, that <hi>three</hi> infinite Spirits are but
<hi>one</hi> God, <hi>by increaſing their firſt Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Diverſity.</hi> They were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently three Gods, by the Origina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third,</hi> from the <hi>firſt;</hi> but we will more aſcertain them to be ſo, by the Multiplication of Subſtances and ſpecifick Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. I ask, what is it that conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53124:37"/>or eſſentiates a God; is it not this, That we ſuppoſe a ſpiritual Subſtance, that is immortal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable, and has the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Omniſcience and Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence? If ſo, then by ſuppoſing more ſuch Subſtances, with ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties belonging to them; we do not ſuppoſe one God, but three. In ſhort, I ſay; they propoſe ſuch an Explication how <hi>three</hi> infinite Minds and Spirits are but <hi>one</hi> God, as all Men of Conſideration will take to be a Declaration and Aſſertion of three Gods: for they will have <hi>three</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Minds to be <hi>one</hi> God, <hi>becauſe they have three diſtinct Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, qualified each of them with (all) diſtinct Divine Properties;</hi> when theſe Subſtances and Properties are the very Marks and Notifications of their diſtinct Divinities, or that they are diſtinct Gods.</p>
               <p>But themſelves alſo acknowledg, that if Origination from the Father, and to be (ſpecifically) conſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with him, were ſufficient to make the Son and Spirit one God with the Father: then
<hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> being originated from their Father
<hi>Peter,</hi> and conſubſtantial in all Reſpects with him, it will follow, that <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> are not three Men, but one Man; or <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> are one Man with
<hi>Peter.</hi> To get rid of this, they advance a third Bull, more ridiculous than either of the two former: it is this.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the originated and conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial (and Divine) Perſons are propagated (from the firſt Perſon) <hi>by an internal Production;</hi> ſo that they are <hi>always</hi> and <hi>inſeparably</hi> in the Perſon that produced them; they are thereby moſt truly one God with him. Here the Reader needs only to conſider, that we are arguing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning three ſuch Perſons as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd (by theſe Oppoſers) to be
<hi>three</hi> diſtinct Subſtances. Now to ſay of two of theſe Subſtances, that they are propagated <hi>by an internal Production,</hi> is a Bull; to add, that that they are <hi>inſeparably</hi> in the Perſon that produced them, is another: but 'tis worſt of all, to ſay; that by their Inexiſtence in the Father, the Son and Spirit are one God with him; this (I ſay) is a worſe Blunder, a more inexcuſable Overſight, than
<hi>internal Production,</hi> or <hi>inſeparable Subſtances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Internal Production,</hi> when ſaid of Subſtances, is a Contradiction, both in the <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Terms:</hi> 'tis as much as to ſay, <hi>a Production not produced;</hi> a Generation not generated.</p>
               <p>And a Subſtance being <hi>that which can exiſt ſeparately,</hi> or by it ſelf; and needeth not, as an Accident, to inexiſt in ſomething elſe: therefore an <hi>inſeparable Subſtance</hi> is a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance without being a Subſtance, or <hi>a Subſtance and no Subſtance.</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> will anſwer, it may be, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Son and Spirit are <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways and inſeparably</hi> in the Father; not from a natural Inhability to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt (as they are Subſtances) by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or ſeparately: but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Nature of the Divine Unity requires, that the ſecond and third Perſons of the Godhead, ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53124:37"/>inexiſt in the firſt; and he in them. But if this be the Meaning of <hi>inſeparably;</hi> it is impertinently, as well as falſly added. Impertinently, becauſe the word <hi>always</hi> had been enough; and only proper to be here uſed. Falſly, becauſe things are not
<hi>inſeparable,</hi> if only they are not <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> ſeparated, but of their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have an Hability to exiſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately. The Bull therefore remains, againſt whatſoever Excuſes: but were that which the Doctor aims to ſay never ſo true, we ſhall ſee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, it will not in the leaſt avail his Cauſe.</p>
               <p>For, as I ſaid, the greateſt Blunder and Inobſervance of all, is what Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> (and the Fathers) take to be the Strength of this Hypotheſis; namely this; that the ſecond and third Perſons being
<hi>always in the firſt,</hi> are therefore one God with him. For it is to be noted, that theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hold, not only that the Son and Spirit are in the Father, but he alſo in them: it is <hi>the mutual Inexiſtence</hi> of all the three Perſons, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Son and Spirit in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that maketh them to be one God. I ask hereupon, whether this mutual Inexiſtence, Immeation or Penetration of the three Perſons, be ſuch; that their Subſtances become <hi>continuous,</hi> as the Parts (for Inſtance) of the ſame Piece of Gold are; or only <hi>contiguous,</hi> like more Pieces of Gold that are heaped (or bagged) together? Are the Subſtances of the three Divine Perſons, I ſay, <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> as (to uſe another Inſtance) the Parts of the ſame Angel or Soul are continuous and indiſcerpible? or are the <hi>only contiguous,</hi> as God or the Divine Subſtance (which pervades all things, Spirits as well as Bodies) is contiguous to the things which it pervades and immeates?</p>
               <p>If Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſays, that the Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Minds and Spirits, or the three Divine Subſtances, have ſuch a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Inexiſtence, that they become continuous; as the (aſſignable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable) Parts of each Perſon's own Subſtance are, or as the Parts of an Angel or Soul are: He ſays <hi>thereby,</hi> and <hi>therein,</hi> that the Subſtances and Perſons are <hi>identified;</hi> which is He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, becauſe (as the Athanaſian Creed ſpeaks) it confounds the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. If the Subſtances are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and thereby identified, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties alſo of the three Subſtances, in Mr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Hypotheſis, will be identified too: for in this Hypotheſis there cannot be diſtinct Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Wills and Energies, if the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are not diſtinct, but continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and (thereby) identified. But we need not to inſiſt on this; for Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> dares not ſay, that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Divine Perſons are identified or continuous: he muſt ſay, and will ſay, that they do ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſt in one another, that <hi>they are only contiguous;</hi> there is only <hi>a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact</hi> of their Subſtances, not an Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification or Continuity. But if there be only a Contact of the three Subſtances, they are as much three <hi>Gods,</hi> and <hi>ſeparate Subſtances</hi> in the Phyſical Senſe of the word <hi>ſeparate:</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:53124:38"/>as three Men imbracing one another, are three diſtinct Men, not one Man; or as God and the Creation are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Subſtances, tho he inexiſts in (pervates or immeates) the Works he hath made, and they again exiſt in him.</p>
               <p>The Fathers that were Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, when they ſaid, the three Divine Perſons or Subſtances are <hi>in</hi> one another, meant,
<hi>by their mutual Love and Agreement:</hi> but thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were not learned, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood only the Platonick Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, which is wholly moral and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſical, and never meddles with <hi>the natural Reaſons of things;</hi> I ſay, the Fathers that were not <hi>natural Philoſophers</hi> imagined ſuch an Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of the three Perſons, that the ſaid Perſons <hi>were phyſically and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially in one another,</hi> and thereby (ſay they) one God. They knew not, that a <hi>ſubſtantial Inexiſtence</hi> muſt either be <hi>by the Continuity of the Subſtances;</hi> which confounds the Subſtances or Perſons: or only by Contiguity or <hi>Contact,</hi> which can no more make three Divine Perſons and Spirits to be one God, than three Men fitting cloſe on the ſame Bench, are thereby one Man; or than God, who is in all Spirits (whether An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels or Souls) and they in him, are the ſame Being or the ſame Subſtance, not ſeparate Subſtances.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> and theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay; the three Divine Perſons are three diſtinct ſeveral Subſtances, and do ſubſtantially immeate (or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſt in) one another: yet ſo, that they are not continuous or identified, as the Parts of the ſame (numerical) Subſtance are, but only contiguous. <hi>We</hi> ſay hereupon, that this will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make them to be one God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>mere Contact is only a juxta-Poſition, not a real <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> All Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, but only the Platoniſts who underſtand not Phyſicks, or <hi>the Nature of things,</hi> will aſſent to this Reaſoning: and I doubt not, it was one of the Cauſes, why the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (who were learned Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers) unanimouſly agreed, that three diſtinct (Divine) Subſtances are moſt certainly three Gods; and they (the Divines of the Schools) have been followed by all the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity-Chairs in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> from about the Year 1200 to this preſent time. I do not believe, there is a Chair in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> that will own more than one Divine Subſtance; or will admit that
<hi>three</hi> Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances can be <hi>one</hi> God. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> will not approve his Hypotheſis to the Chairs, or to Univerſities or Schools of Learning. I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion however, that ſo arrogant a Man as Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> will not let go his Hypotheſis; it being too the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Fathers, and of a great many learned Men who treat of theſe Queſtions as Divines, not as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: and Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> having acquired ſo great a Reputation all over <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> by his Book; the Chairs and Nominal Trinitarians will not, it may be, adventure to attack him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:53124:38"/>But if after all, Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> fearing the Numbers and Reputation of the Nominal Trinitarians, will deny his Hypotheſis; and (in hopes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with them) pretend that it differs not (or not <hi>materially</hi>) from the Doctrine of the Schools: beſides that all diſcerning and ingenuous Men will laugh at his Puſilanimity; I ſhall not deſire an eaſier Task, than to prove from his own Book, and from innumerable Quotations of the Fathers, that both they and he hold three diſtinct Divine Subſtances, and conſequently ſo many Minds and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, both which are rejected as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical (nay as Tritheiſtical) by the Schools and their Followers.</p>
               <p>I will conclude this firſt <hi>Part</hi> of my Anſwer, with obſerving, that tho Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> ſays here, that the Fathers believed the three (Divine) Perſons are one God, becauſe <hi>the ſecond and third are derived from the firſt, have like Subſtances and Properties with him, and all of them do mutually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meate one another:</hi> yet this is not the Explication of any <hi>particular</hi> Father, much leſs of <hi>all</hi> of them; but an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis that Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has pieced up, from the Writings of <hi>divers</hi> Fathers. The Fathers explained the Unity in Trinity, each of them his own way. One ſaid, the three Perſons are one God, becauſe <hi>they are in one another, by mutual Love and Agreement.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid, they are one God, becauſe of <hi>the Subordination and perfect Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the ſecond and third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to him who is the firſt God.</hi> Another, they are one God, becauſe <hi>the Son and Spirit are propagated from the Father.</hi> Another, becauſe they unanimouſly govern the World; that is, they are one God, <hi>becauſe they are one Monarchy, and thereby (as it were) one Ruler.</hi> Some of them ſaid, three Divine Perſons, and three infinite Spirits are <hi>God</hi> and the
<hi>Godhead;</hi> in ſuch Senſe <hi>as all Men are called Man or Mankind.</hi> As three golden Coins of the ſame Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror are called
<hi>Aurum,</hi> Gold, not <hi>Aura,</hi> Golds, in the Plural: So in proper ſpeaking, three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, becauſe (like three Men, or three golden Coins) they are conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial; that is, have the ſame ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Subſtances and Properties; they are (in proper ſpeaking) to be called
<hi>God,</hi> not <hi>Gods.</hi> This was a very ridiculous Reaſoning, contrary both to Grammar and Philoſophy; and yet it was the Explication of ſome of the moſt learned of the Poſt-Nicene Fathers.</p>
               <p>Briefly, theſe two things I affirm: That Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Explication of the Unity of God, is indeed taken out of ſome of the Fathers: but it was not (as 'tis laid down by him) the particular Explication given by any one of them, much leſs the agreed and common Explication of all of them; but part of it is from ſome, other Parts of it from other Fathers. Secondly, the Fathers advanced ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Explications; on which ſome of them inſiſted, more and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than on any part of Mr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s. The Ante-Nicens chiefly urged the Unity <hi>of Love,</hi> or elſe <hi>of Monarchy:</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:53124:39"/>the moſt learned (but leaſt judicious) of the Poſt-Nicens ſerved themſelves of the (pretended) Conſubſtantiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or that the three Perſons having like Subſtances and Properties, are therefore one God; as all Men or <hi>Mankind</hi> are called <hi>Homo,</hi> and as three (or more) golden Coins are called
<hi>Aurum,</hi> Gold; never <hi>Aura,</hi> Golds. But of theſe things I ſhall ſpeak fully, in the Concluſion of the third Part of this Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>I Have ſaid what I intended in this firſt Part. In the Second I will report the Doctrine of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Fathers, concerning the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and the Perſon of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in their own Words: By the following Fathers I mean thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who flouriſhed from about the Year 150, to the Nicene Council, or the Year 325. In the laſt Part I ſhall diſcover Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Frauds and Miſtakes, detect his Sophiſtries and Eluſions; and confront his Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the Fathers, with the Confeſſions and Judgment of the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, who have either publiſhed or commented on the Writings of the Fathers. Here and now it remains only, that I inform the Reader, who hath not ſeen Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Books, why I have anſwer'd ſo indifferently, and without any particular Deference to the Merit of his Learning and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for it cannot be denied, that this Gentleman is a dextrous Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; or that he has read the principal Fathers with a more than ordinary Application, Diligence and Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> has written two Books, his <hi>Defence of the Nicene Faith,</hi> and <hi>Judgment of the Catholick Church,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly and directly againſt the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians; whether they be Arians or Socinians. In the firſt of theſe he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks more particularly <hi>Chr. Sandius,</hi> a very learned Arian; and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Irenicum Irenicorum,</hi> who was Dr.
<hi>Zwicker</hi> M. D. a Socinian. Dr. <hi>Zwicker</hi> is complemented by Dr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> with ſuch Flowers as theſe; <hi>Bipedum ineptiſſimus,</hi> the greateſt Fop in Nature: <hi>Omnium odio, qui veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem &amp; candorem amant, dignus;</hi> deſerving the Hatred of all Lovers of Truth and Sincerity. Of <hi>Sandius</hi> he ſaith, <hi>He hath ſhip-wrack'd his Conſcience, as well as his Faith; a Trifler, a mere (empty) Pretender:</hi> He adds at <hi>p.</hi> 331. <hi>He hath only tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the Author of</hi> Iren. Irenico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; and in one Place, he prays for <hi>Sandius</hi> as one that is mad. This,<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53124:39"/>and ſuch as this, is Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s conſtant Language concerning theſe two very learned Men: nor doth he ever reply to them, without pretending an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and inconteſtable Victory; and caſting ſome moſt unworthy Scorn or other upon them, by occaſion of his ſuppoſed Advantage. He <hi>never</hi> calls the Arians by any other Name but <hi>Ariomanitae, the mad Arians;</hi> and Socinianiſm is <hi>always</hi> with him <hi>the Atheiſtical Hereſy,</hi> I do not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that he ever calls our Doctrine by a better Name. In ſhort, he hath expreſſed ſuch a Malevolence; and hath ſo notoriouſly and infamouſly broke <hi>the Cartel</hi> of Honour and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, that was thought to be agreed and eſtabliſh'd between Perſons of excellent Learning, or great Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when they happen to be ingaged in contrary Sides; that no Reſpect or Tenderneſs can be ſhown to him by any Unitarian. His Barbarities and Immanities towards a Perſon ſo little deſerving ſuch Uſage, and ſo much above Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> in all Regards, as <hi>Sandius</hi> was; and his Arrogance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and (hare-brain'd) Contempt of all Unitarians, whether antient or modern: I ſay, his Temerity and Extravagance in this kind, is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive, or rather is ſo outrageous, that he hath leſt to himſelf no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Right or Claims to the very leaſt Degree of Humanity or good Manners towards him.</p>
               <p>And ſee here what Judgment he makes, of the late Socinian
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>atiſes, that have been publiſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſix or ſeven Years laſt paſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> face to
<hi>the Judgment of the Catholick Church:</hi>
                  <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Divers <hi>impious Wretches,</hi> within theſe few Years, have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked the principal Article of the Faith; namely, the Divinity of our Saviour: Some of them are Arians, others Samoſatenians or Socinians; I may ſay of both, as the great <hi>H. Zanchius</hi> ſomewhere does of <hi>L. Socinus, Fr. Davidis, Blandrata,</hi> and other Founders of the Socinian Hereſy in the laſt Age. <hi>I do not read, without Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, the ſilly and mad Defences of the new Arians and Photini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: for I cannot meet in their Writings with the very leaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Wit, or good Senſe; they have nothing but the Repetition of old exploded Follies, or new Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of their own.</hi> But leſt they ſhould think that they have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Victory; or ſhould miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead the Weak, ſome pious and learned Men have deſerved the publick Praiſe and Thanks, by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing themſelves to the Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries of theſe Triflers.</q> It is in this ſtrain that Dr.
<hi>Bull</hi> has treated us, every where; in every Page of his two Books: therefore it could not be reaſonably expected, that in anſwering, we ſhould fall proſtrate to ſuch an inveterate and ſupercilious. Malevolence and Arrogance; or make court to ſuch a <hi>Hildebrand</hi> as this Man (even) affects to ſhow himſelf.</p>
               <p>I know not, whether he will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade many that <hi>a Diabolical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> is a fit Guide to be choſe, in the<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53124:40"/>Search of ſacred Truths: or that thoſe have the true
<hi>Faith,</hi> who have not the leaſt Grain of <hi>Charity?</hi> If Mr.
<hi>Bull</hi> had railed ſo bitterly, only at the preſent Engliſh Socinians, and their Writers, we might have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted his Intemperance to his Fear, or to his Ambition. We might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, that he begins to doubt, that this (growing) Sect may, one day, turn him out of his Parſonage, or his Prebend: or that by Zeal and Bigotry he intended to recommend himſelf to his Superiours in the Church, and merit a Biſhoprick or Deanery. But why has he inſulted the Dead; nay look'd back 1200, and 1400 Years, ſcattering his Gall and Venom into the U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Martyrs, of the ſecond and third Ages of Chriſtianity? Even thoſe whom <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Apoſtate, not only ſpared, but honoured and rewarded for their Sanctity and Learning; Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has broke up their Monuments, and ſcatter'd their Aſhes.</p>
               <p>His Metropolitan not only preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, to the moſt conſiderable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory of <hi>England;</hi> but publiſhed it too, from the Preſs, to all the World:
<q rend="inline margQuotes">"That the Socinians argue Matters, with Temper and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; that they reaſon <hi>cloſely,</hi> and <hi>clearly,</hi> with extraordinary Guard and Cantion, with as much Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity and Decency. The ableſt Managers, ſaith he, that ever yet meddled with Controverſy; in compariſon of whom the Jeſuit is a Scold and a Bungler.</q> Archbiſh.
2<hi>d</hi> Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> on the Divin. of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> But Mr.
<hi>Bull,</hi> becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> more Wit and Judgment than three Archbiſhops, anſwers immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the
<hi>Oxford</hi>-Preſs; that his <hi>Grace</hi> is either mad, or dotes; that ſince he (Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>) has wrote againſt the Socinians, 'tis impoſſible they ſhould have the leaſt Temper, Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, good Senſe, or ought elſe, that may recommend them to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem. The Man grows warm; let us part for the preſent, leſt we alſo grow as fooliſh as he.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Aug. 19. 1695.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:53124:40"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
